<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Plant Biotechnol (Tokyo)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Plant Biotechnol (Tokyo)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3560</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plantbiotech</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Plant Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1342-4580</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-6114</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society for Plant Biotechnology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11500582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11500582.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11500582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11500582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39464868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5511/plantbiotechnology.23.1214a</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of a novel Golgi-localized putative glycosyltransferase protein in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rzepecka</surname><given-names initials="N">Natalia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yura</surname><given-names initials="K">Kei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names initials="E">Emi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names initials="T">Tomohiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="corr1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Graduate School of Humanities and Sciences, Ochanomizu University, Tokyo 112-8610, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Institute for Human Life Science, Ochanomizu University, Tokyo 112-8610, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Natural Science Division, Faculty of Core Research, Ochanomizu University, Tokyo 112-8610, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Graduate School of Advanced Science and Engineering, Waseda University, Tokyo 169-8555, Japan</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Institute for Women&#8217;s Education in Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts and Mathematics, Ochanomizu University, Tokyo 112-8610, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>uemura.tomohiro@ocha.ac.jp</email> Tel: <phone>+81-3-5978-5713</phone></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">473402</issue-id><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-28 12:25:47.577"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 Japanese Society for Plant Biotechnology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Japanese Society for Plant Biotechnology</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License (CC BY, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a.pdf"/><abstract><p>SNAREs play an important role in the process of membrane trafficking. In the present research, we investigated subcellular localization of an uncharacterized <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> protein reported to interact with a <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network-localized Qa-SNARE, SYNTAXIN OF PLANTS 43. Based on the similarity of its amino acid sequence to metazoan fucosyltransferases, we have named this novel protein AtGTLP (<italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
<bold><underline>G</underline></bold>lycosyl<bold><underline>T</underline></bold>ransferase-<bold><underline>L</underline></bold>ike <bold><underline>P</underline></bold>rotein) and predicted that it should be a member of yet uncharacterized family of Arabidopsis fucosyltransferases, as it shows no significant sequence similarity to fucosyltransferases previously identified in Arabidopsis. AtGTLP is a membrane-anchored protein, which exhibits a type II-like topology, with a single transmembrane helix and a globular domain in the C-terminal part of its amino acid sequence. Colocalization data we collected suggest that AtGTLP should localize mainly to Golgi apparatus, especially to certain zones of <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi. As single <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp&#8722;/&#8722;</italic> mutants showed no obvious difference in phenotype (primary root length and fresh mass), AtGTLP and proteins related to AtGTLP with high similarity in amino acid sequences may have redundant functions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>glycosylation</kwd><kwd>Golgi apparatus</kwd><kwd>membrane trafficking</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>An efficient and well-organized intracellular transport system is a basic requirement for life to exist, as many components necessary for metabolic processes, that take place inside or outside of a eukaryotic cell, are produced and subsequently modified in different cell compartments. The transport system responsible for delivering cargo collected from one compartment (that is: a membrane-enclosed organelle, such as endoplasmic reticulum, Golgi, or vacuole) to its next destination has been given the name of &#8220;membrane traffic&#8221;.</p><p>In the membrane traffic, macromolecules are packed as cargo into vesicles, which then carry the cargo to another organelle, plasma membrane or extracellular space. SNARE (soluble <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment receptor) proteins, a family of membrane-anchored proteins comprising of more than 60 members in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="RSanderfoot2007" ref-type="bibr">Sanderfoot 2007</xref>), play an important role in this transport system. Assisted by other molecules, such as Rab GTPases and tethering factors, SNAREs mediate fusion between the membrane of vesicle carrying the cargo and the membrane of the organelle the cargo is addressed to (<xref rid="RStenmark2009" ref-type="bibr">Stenmark 2009</xref>). To facilitate the fusion, SNAREs form a complex comprising of four SNAREs&#8212;three Q-SNAREs (Qa-, Qb-, Qc-SNARE), which reside on the target membrane and are characterized by the presence of glutamine as the central amino acid in SNARE motif, in addition to one R-SNARE residing on the transport vesicle, with arginine as the central amino acid (<xref rid="RFasshauer1998" ref-type="bibr">Fasshauer et al. 1998</xref>). When a R-SNARE comes into contact with the three Q-SNAREs, first a link is formed between the vesicle and the target membrane, and subsequently, due to the change in conformation of the SNARE complex from &#8220;loose&#8221; to &#8220;tight&#8221; state, the vesicle is pulled toward the target membrane, allowing the two membranes to fuse together and the cargo to enter the lumen of the organelle (<xref rid="RJahn2006" ref-type="bibr">Jahn and Scheller 2006</xref>). To ensure the specificity of fusion, a large number of SNAREs localizes selectively to a specific cell compartment. This characteristic made it possible for those SNAREs to be successfully used as organelle markers in subcellular localization studies (<xref rid="RUemura2004" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2004</xref>).</p><p>Through their crucial role in membrane trafficking, members of SNARE family in plants were reported to be implicit in a variety of biological processes, ranging from growth to biotic/abiotic stress resistance. One group of SNAREs, that has been linked to secretion-dependent resistance against pathogens, is SYP4 (SYNTAXIN of PLANTs 4) group. SYP4 group comprises of three members (SYP41, SYP42 and SYP43) with partially overlapping functions, all localizing to the TGN (<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network). <italic toggle="yes">syp42&#8722;/&#8722;syp43&#8722;/&#8722;</italic> double mutant exhibits phenotype of shorter roots, semi-dwarfism, and early senescence, in addition to increase in susceptibility to host-adapted virulent powdery fungus <italic toggle="yes">Golovinomyces orontii</italic> infection, when compared to wild type (<xref rid="RUemura2012" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>A research focused on interactome of Qa-SNARE proteins in Arabidopsis reported a number of new interactions between specific SNARE proteins and numerous proteins of diverse functions, including novel proteins with unknown functions (<xref rid="RFujiwara2014" ref-type="bibr">Fujiwara et al. 2014</xref>). One such interaction was found between SYP43 and an uncharacterized protein, which we decided to name AtGTLP (<italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
<bold><underline>G</underline></bold>lycosyl<bold><underline>T</underline></bold>ransferase-<bold><underline>L</underline></bold>ike <bold><underline>P</underline></bold>rotein) due to the similarity to glycosyltransferases in its amino acid sequence.</p><p>Glycosyltransferases (GTs) are a large family of enzymes, characterized by their ability to transfer sugar moieties to a specific acceptor substrate creating a glycosidic bond. GTs are known to produce a variety of glycoproteins and small sugar-containing molecules with diverse biological roles, but in plants, these enzymes are especially important for processing products of photosynthesis and for biosynthesis of cell-wall (<xref rid="RKeegstra2001" ref-type="bibr">Keegstra and Raikhel 2001</xref>). At present, 567 Arabidopsis proteins recorded in the Carbohydrate Active Enzyme Database (CAZy) (<xref rid="RCantarel2009" ref-type="bibr">Cantarel et al. 2009</xref>; http://www.cazy.org/e1.html, accessed Nov 1, 2023) with &#8216;GlycosylTransferase&#8217; annotation have been further classified into 45 of 117 GT families known today (including GT0 or GTnc, &#8216;non-classified&#8217;). Independently from the sequence-based classification implemented in CAZy database, GTs can also be categorized according to the type of sugar they use as a substrate. One such example is the superfamily of fucosyltransferases (FUTs), which utilize guanidine 5&#8242;-diphosphate-&#946;-L-fucose (GDP-Fuc) as a substrate (<xref rid="RMartinez2003" ref-type="bibr">Martinez-Duncker et al. 2003</xref>). In plants, macromolecules known to incorporate fucose in their structures are <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycans, <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosylated proteins, as well as components of cell walls, such as xyloglucans, arabinogalactan proteins and pectic polysaccharides&#8212;rhamnogalacturonan I (RG-I) and rhamnogalacturonan II (RG-II) (<xref rid="RSoto2019" ref-type="bibr">Soto et al. 2019</xref>). Based on characteristics of FUTs that have been identified thus far (a majority of which are putative fucosyltransferases), it has been established that fucose is attached to each of these types of macromolecules by a specific FUT(s). As our knowledge about plant FUTs is still lacking, the full scope of their biological functions is, at present, not fully understood.</p><p>In the present study, we observed subcellular localization of AtGTLP by cross-pollinating a transgenic Arabidopsis line expressing AtGTLP-mGFP construct with organelle marker lines, as the first step to investigate the functions of AtGTLP.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p>For colocalization observations, Arabidopsis plants were grown in growth chamber, in 22&#176;C in long-day light (16&#8201;h/8&#8201;h, L/D) conditions on MS medium w/vitamins (Duchefa Biochemie), containing 0.3% gellan gum (Wako) and 2% sucrose. pH was adjusted to 6.265. Fluorescence was observed in cells in the elongation zone of roots of 5-day-old seedlings.</p><p>For analysis of mutant phenotype, two T-DNA insertion lines SALK_025999 (<italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic>) and SALK_011654 (<italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic>) were used. Columbia-0 accession plants were used as a control. Growth conditions and medium were the same as for colocalization analysis. For statistical analysis of primary root length and fresh mass, 25 individuals (11-day-old) were used for each genotype.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA extraction and RT-PCR</title><p>RNA was extracted from 10-day-old Arabidopsis seedling with RNeasy&#174; Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen). 100&#8201;mg of fresh tissue was used for each sample. cDNA was synthesized using SuperScript&#8482; III Reverse Transcriptase (ThermoFisher Scientific). 5&#8201;&#181;g of the extracted RNA was added to each reaction as a template. The presence or lack of <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic> expression in mutant lines was confirmed by PCR reaction using ExTaq polymerase (Takara). 1&#8201;&#181;g of cDNA was used as a template. Primers used for RT-PCR are listed in Supplementary Table S1.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene cloning</title><p>A 5.1&#8201;kbp fragment of nucleotide sequence comprising of the native promoter and <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">At2g04280</italic>) gene sequence flanked by 5&#8242; and 3&#8242; UTRs was amplified using PrimeSTAR&#174; GXL DNA Polymerase (Takara). The amplified sequence was subsequently subcloned into a pENTR&#8482; vector using pENTR&#8482;/D-TOPO Vector Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific) for directional cloning. The vector was used to transform One Shot&#8482; TOP10 Chemically Competent <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (ThermoFisher Scientific).</p><p>Transformants were selected on solid LB medium with kanamycin 50&#8201;mg&#8201;l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> and cultured overnight in liquid LB with the same antibiotic concentration. Isolated plasmid was linearized and fused with monomeric GFP (mGFP) (<xref rid="RSegami2014" ref-type="bibr">Segami et al. 2014</xref>) gene sequence using In-Fusion HD Kit (Takara). Product of this reaction was used to transform competent <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells and the transformants selection procedure was repeated. Isolated plasmid was used as the entry clone for pHGW vector (<xref rid="RKarimi2002" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al. 2002</xref>) as the destination vector in Gateway&#8482; LR Clonase&#8482; II reaction (ThermoFisher Scientific). <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP-mGFP</italic> in pHGW construct was transformed into competent <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells and transformant colonies were selected on solid LB medium with 100&#8201;mg&#8201;l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> spectinomycin.</p><p>For creation of mRFP-GOS12 Golgi marker line, translational fusion between <italic toggle="yes">mRFP</italic> (<xref rid="RCampbell2002" ref-type="bibr">Campbell et al. 2002</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">GOS12</italic> were generated by inserting cDNA encoding <italic toggle="yes">mRFP</italic> in front of the start codon of <italic toggle="yes">GOS12</italic> genomic sequence including 1.9&#8201;kb of the 5&#8242;-flanking sequence and 1.2&#8201;kb of the 3&#8242;-flanking sequence in pENTR&#8482; vector using In-Fusion HD Kit. The resulted mRFP-GOS12 construct was subcloned into pGWB1 by LR Clonase&#8482; II (<xref rid="RNakagawa2007" ref-type="bibr">Nakagawa et al. 2007</xref>).</p><p>Primers used for gene cloning and linearization are listed in Supplementary Table S1.</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of Arabidopsis transformants</title><p>Col-0 plants were infected with <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> transformed with the prepared plasmid containing the <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP-mGFP</italic> construct using flower dip method (<xref rid="RClough1998" ref-type="bibr">Clough and Bent 1998</xref>). Collected seeds were sown on MS medium with 2% sucrose, 0.8% agar with 25&#8201;mg&#8201;l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of hygromycin and 250&#8201;mg&#8201;l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of claforan.</p><p>Selection of T<sub>1</sub> lines with a single <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP-mGFP</italic> construct was conducted by sowing T<sub>2</sub> seeds on selective MS medium with hygromycin. Lines, for which we observed 3&#8201;:&#8201;1 segregation ratio of resistant to non-resistant plants, were selected as single-insertion lines.</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal laser scanning microscopy observations</title><p>For subcellular localization observations of AtGTLP protein, AtGTLP-mGFP single-insertion lines were cross-pollinated with organelle markers lines. mRFP-VAMP721 (<xref rid="RUemura2019" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2019</xref>) and tagRFP-VAMP727 (<xref rid="REbine2008" ref-type="bibr">Ebine et al. 2008</xref>) lines were used as markers for transport vesicle from the TGN to the cell plate/plasma membrane or to the vacuole, respectively. mRFP-SYP61 (<xref rid="RShimizu2021" ref-type="bibr">Shimizu et al. 2021</xref>), mRFP-SYP43 (<xref rid="RAsaoka2013" ref-type="bibr">Asaoka et al. 2013</xref>), and VHAa1-mRFP (<xref rid="RDettmer2006" ref-type="bibr">Dettmer et al. 2006</xref>) lines were used as TGN markers. ST-mRFP was used as a <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi marker (<xref rid="RUemura2012" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2012</xref>) and mRFP-GOS12 as a Golgi marker (in this study).</p><p>Colocalization observations were conducted using Zeiss LSM980 with Airyscan 2 confocal laser scanning microscope system equipped with Plan-Apochromat 63x/1.40 Oil DIC M27 immersion objective. Excitation laser wavelengths of 488&#8201;nm and 543&#8201;nm were used. Pinhole was set to 1AU.</p></sec><sec><title>Colocalization analysis</title><p>The degree of colocalization of each organelle marker with AtGTLP-mGFP was assessed by calculating Pearson correlation coefficient (PCC) (<xref rid="RAdler2010" ref-type="bibr">Adler and Parmryd 2010</xref>; <xref rid="RDunn2011" ref-type="bibr">Dunn et al. 2011</xref>). To obtain PCC values, Coloc 2 plugin for Fiji/ImageJ software (<xref rid="RSchindelin2012" ref-type="bibr">Schindelin et al. 2012</xref>) was used. For each organelle marker, three 50&#8201;&#181;m&#215;50&#8201;&#181;m images with 15 randomly selected regions of interest (ROIs), freehand-drawn around the observed dot-like structures, were used for analysis (45 ROIs total for each marker). Noise in the images was corrected using the &#8216;Smooth&#8217; function of Fiji/ImageJ. Line fluorescence intensity plots were generated using RGB profiler plugin for Fiji/ImageJ.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>AtGTLP is a putative glycosyltransferase</title><p>AtGTLP is predicted to be a membrane-anchored protein comprising of 568 residues. DeepTMHMM (<xref rid="RHallgren2022" ref-type="bibr">Hallgren et al. 2022</xref>; https://dtu.biolib.com/DeepTMHMM, accessed Nov 1, 2023) transmembrane topology prediction model for this protein indicates a presence of a single transmembrane helix near the N-terminus of AtGTLP protein (residues 24&#8211;44). The short N-terminal tail of the protein was predicted to localize on the cytosolic side of an organelle membrane, while residues 45&#8211;568 reside inside the lumen (<xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). AlphaFold2 (<xref rid="RJumper2021" ref-type="bibr">Jumper et al. 2021</xref>) model of AtGTLP&#8217;s three-dimensional structure includes a globular domain of unknown function in the C-terminal part of the amino acid sequence (<xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). The C-terminal part of the amino-acid sequence was modelled with high confidence, while N-terminal part had a lower reliability score (<xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C&#8211;E</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="figure1" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Figure&#8194;1.&#8195;(A) Schematic model of AtGTLP topology and (B) AlphaFold2 prediction of the three-dimensional structure of AtGTLP. AtGTLP comprises of a short N-terminal tail, single transmembrane helix and globular domain in the C-terminal part of amino-acid sequence positioned on a short stalk (type II topology). (C) The prediction reliability described by predicted Local Distance Difference Test (pLDDT). Some of the regions in the N-terminal side have score less than 50 and the structures of those regions are less reliable. (D) Predicted three-dimensional structure of AtGTLP in pLDDT coloring. An &#945;-helix at the bottom is the N-terminal side. Blue color indicates less reliable region and red color indicates region with high reliability. Note that the region with similar structure to <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 has high reliability. (E) Predicted Alignment Error (PAE). N-terminal side has high error (red), and C-terminal side has low error (blue). (F) Superposition between the three-dimensional structure of AtGTLP (from 260 to 566) and that of human protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 (PDB ID: 4AP6, A chain). The region in white in AtGTLP is the N-terminal region that was not included in the superposition. The gradation coloring scheme was employed from N-terminal to C-terminal side on the superposed region. Human <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 is colored in gray with GDP analogue in ball-and-stick model which suggests the active site of the protein. Root mean square deviation (RMSD) of the backbone is 5.9&#8201;&#197;. The similarity of the location of &#945;-helices can be noticed.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-figure01.jpg"/></fig><p>Analysis of AtGTLP&#8217;s amino acid sequence using Phyre<sup>2</sup> server (<xref rid="RKelley2015" ref-type="bibr">Kelley et al. 2015</xref>; http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/phyre2/html/page.cgi?id=index, accessed Nov 1, 2023) suggests a distant homology between the C-terminal domain of AtGTLP and human protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 (POFUT2; 19% of sequence identity, 99.2% confidence), protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 1 (POFUT1; 16% i.d., 98.9% confidence), as well as <italic toggle="yes">C. elegans</italic> protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 (CePOFUT2; 20% i.d., 98.9% confidence) and protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 1 (CePOFUT1; 18% i.d., 99.2% confidence). Superposition between AlphaFold2 model of C-terminal domain of AtGTLP and the top ranked template (human POFUT2; PDB ID: 4AP6, A chain) is shown in <xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>. Interestingly, among top ranked templates, we observed no plant GTs nor other types of plant enzymes. Moreover, although the Conserved Domain Database (<xref rid="RLu2020" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2020</xref>; https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi, accessed Nov 1, 2023) recognizes the presence of &#8216;<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-FUT-like&#8217; domain in the C-terminal region of AtGTLP, when its amino acid sequence was used as a query in BLAST search against Arabidopsis proteome, none of the 38 proteins that have been characterized as members of Arabidopsis FUT family in literature (<xref rid="RSmith2018" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2018</xref>) were present among the results. No other motif that could suggest possible functions of AtGTLP has been found to be present in its amino acid sequence. In the CAZy database, AtGTLP is currently classified as &#8216;GTnc&#8217;.</p></sec><sec><title>AtGTLP is localized mainly on the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi</title><p>To investigate the subcellular localization of AtGTLP, we established transgenic Arabidopsis expressing mGFP-tagged AtGTLP (AtGTLP-mGFP) under the control of native promoter. The fluorescence of AtGTLP-mGFP protein concentrated in dot- or ring-like structures scattered within the cell (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="figure2" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Figure&#8194;2.&#8195;Subcellular localization of AtGTLP. Confocal laser scanning microscopy images of elongation zone cells of Arabidopsis seedling expressing AtGTLP-GFP construct, and organelle marker fused with RFP (A) ST-mRFP, (B) mRFP-GOS12, (C) mRFP-SYP61, (D) VHAa1-mRFP, (E) mRFP-SYP43, (F) mRFP-VAMP721, (G) tagRFP-VAMP727. Scale bar=10&#8201;&#956;m. White arrow heads in (F) close up-dots of &#8216;free&#8217; tagRFP-VAMP727. Close-up scale bar=2&#8201;&#956;m.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-figure02.jpg"/></fig><p>In order to reveal which organelle those structures correspond to, we established double-visualization Arabidopsis lines expressing AtGTLP-mGFP with various RFP-tagged organelle markers. Among tested markers, the extent of colocalization of AtGTLP with <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi marker, ST (<xref rid="RBoevink1998" ref-type="bibr">Boevink et al. 1998</xref>) was the highest and relatively consistent among all analyzed ROIs (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; PCC=0.5&#8211;0.91; median=0.75), suggesting that a significant population of AtGTLP localizes to <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi. Visual observations of colocalization of these two proteins show that while both seem to often localize to the same disk-like structures, patches of magenta-only and green-only fluorescence within those structures were also visible (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, &#8216;close-up&#8217;). Based on this characteristic, we suspect that within <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi, AtGTLP segregates to specific zones only. As expected, relatively high PCCs were obtained also when colocalization with GOS12, a Golgi marker (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>; <xref rid="RUemura2004" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2004</xref>), was analyzed (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; 0.21&#8211;0.83, median=0.58). However, whereas for the AtGTLP-mGFP/ST-mRFP pair, the two peaks representing GFP and RFP in side-view line fluorescence profile of a single disk-like structure overlap almost entirely (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>), for the AtGTLP-mGFP/mRFP-GOS12 pair a slight shift between those two peaks was observed (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="figure3" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Figure&#8194;3.&#8195;Colocalization of AtGTLP with organelle markers. As a mean of assessing the degree of colocalization, for each marker line expressing AtGTLP-mGFP and organelle marker fused with RFP Pearson&#8217;s correlation coefficient was calculated for 45 ROIs hand-drawn around clusters of dot-like structures. Three separate images were analyzed (15 ROIs/image) for each marker. Median is shown for each marker.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-figure03.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="figure4" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Figure&#8194;4.&#8195;Line fluorescence intensity profile for (A) AtGTLP-mGFP and ST-mRFP, (B) AtGTLP-mGFP and mRFP-GOS12, (C) AtGTLP-mGFP and mRFP-SYP61, (D) AtGTLP-mGFP and VHAa1-mRFP; (E) AtGTLP-mGFP and mRFP-SYP43, (F) AtGTLP-mGFP and mRFP-VAMP721, (G) AtGTLP-mGFP and tagRFP-VAMP727 line. (A)&#8211;(G) left panel&#8212;en face orientation of AtGTLP ring; right panel&#8212;side orientation of AtGTLP ring. Intensity plot was generated along and in direction of the white arrow. Scale bar=1&#8201;&#956;m.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-figure04.jpg"/></fig><p>Moreover, we found that in some of the analyzed ROIs, AtGTLP partially colocalizes with TGN markers, SYP61 (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>; <xref rid="RUemura2004" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2004</xref>) and VHAa1 (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>; <xref rid="RDettmer2006" ref-type="bibr">Dettmer et al. 2006</xref>), whereas in other ROIs, PCC was close to zero (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; PCC=0.0&#8211;0.65; median=0.41 and PCC=&#8722;0.01&#8211;0.79; median=0.46, respectively). Side-view line fluorescence profiles for these two markers show a similar shift between the GFP and RFP peaks (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C, D</xref>). Interestingly, for the third analyzed TGN marker used in this study, SYP43 (<xref rid="RUemura2004" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2004</xref>), we observed that areas where the two colors of florescence overlap with each other, were scarcer (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2E</xref>). Relatively low degree of colocalization for AtGTLP-mGFP/mRFP-SYP43 pair was also reflected in lower PCC values (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; &#8722;0.17&#8211;0.64, with median of 0.26) and line fluorescence profile, which suggest that SYP43 localizes to the center of AtGTLP rings (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4E</xref>).</p><p>Taking into consideration the possibility that AtGTLP is transported within the cell as a cargo, two transport pathway markers&#8212;VAMP721, a marker of transport from the TGN to the cell plate and the plasma membrane, as well as VAMP727, a marker of vacuolar transport (<xref rid="RShimizu2022" ref-type="bibr">Shimizu and Uemura 2022</xref>)&#8212;were also included in the study. In case of VAMP721, we observed very little overlap of GFP and RFP fluorescence (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2F</xref>, <xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4F</xref>), and low PCCs (<xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; &#8722;0.48&#8211;0.48, median=0.15), whereas colocalization between AtGTLP and VAMP727, similarly to SYP61 and VHAa1, was inconsistent across the analyzed ROIs (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G</xref>, <xref rid="figure3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; PCC=0.01&#8211;0.7, median=0.42). Line fluorescence profiles for AtGTLP-GFP/tagRFP-VAMP727 pair also show a pattern similar to AtGTLP-GFP/mRFP-SYP61 pair (<xref rid="figure4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4G</xref>). When inspecting the degree of colocalization visually, we observed that the areas of overlapping fluorescence were present mainly within clusters of dot- or ring-like structures, which most likely correspond to Golgi/TGN. In addition to these clusters, &#8216;free&#8217; dots of tagRFP-VAMP727 signal, where AtGTLP-mGFP was absent, could also be observed (<xref rid="figure2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2G</xref>, arrowheads).</p></sec><sec><title>atgtlp mutants exhibit no obvious phenotypes</title><p>According to data available in eFP Browser (Klepikova Arabidopsis Atlas; <xref rid="RKlepikova2016" ref-type="bibr">Klepikova et al. 2016</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic> is expressed in most parts of a plant, including roots and young leaves, with the exception of dry seeds.</p><p>In both mutant lines used in this study, T-DNA insertion was confirmed to be present inside <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic>&#8217;s exon (<xref rid="figure5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>). Although the results of RT-PCR confirmed that transcription of <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic> in both of the T-DNA lines is absent or reduced to levels undetectable with this method (<xref rid="figure5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>), growth of mutant plants was comparable to wild type plants, and we could not observe any distinctive phenotype differences between <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic> single mutants and wild-type plants in 8-day-old and 11-day-old seedlings (<xref rid="figure5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C, D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="figure5" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Figure&#8194;5.&#8195;Characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic> single mutant lines. (A) T-DNA insertion sites inside nucleotide sequence of <italic toggle="yes">AtGTLP</italic> gene in <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic> (SALK_025999) and <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic> (SALK_011654) lines, (B) RT-PCR results, control&#8212;<italic toggle="yes">TUA3</italic> (tubulin), (C) Phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic> 8-day-old-seedlings no difference between Col-0 plants and mutants has been observed. Scale bar=1&#8201;cm. (D) Comparison of fresh weight and length of primary roots in Col-0 and <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp-2</italic> plants (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-figure05.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Trans</italic>-Golgi localization of AtGTLP</title><p>In our subcellular localization study, we found that AtGTLP colocalized well with the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi marker, ST, as well as with the Golgi marker, GOS12. Based on these results, we consider AtGTLP to be a resident Golgi protein, localizing mainly to <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi. Furthermore, the ring-like appearance of AtGTLP-mGFP fluorescence suggest that it localizes mainly to the rim of Golgi cisternae (<xref rid="RTie2018" ref-type="bibr">Tie et al. 2018</xref>).</p><p>The results of this study showed that the predicted characteristics of AtGTLP match that of glycosyltransferases. In eukaryotic cells, glycosylation processes are commonly thought to occur mainly in ER and Golgi (<xref rid="RHansen2010" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al. 2010</xref>). In plants, biosynthesis of many cell wall polysaccharides, another process that involves GTs, was also reported to take place in Golgi (<xref rid="RKeegstra2001" ref-type="bibr">Keegstra and Raikhel 2001</xref>; <xref rid="RSaint2004" ref-type="bibr">Saint-Jore-Dupas et al. 2004</xref>). Predicted topology model of AtGTLP suggests that it possesses a short cytoplasmic N-terminal tail and a single transmembrane helix, while its globular functional domain is positioned inside the lumen. Such topology, often described as &#8216;type II topology&#8217; in literature, is common among Golgi-resident enzymes known to take part in protein glycosylation processes (<xref rid="RBanfield2011" ref-type="bibr">Banfield 2011</xref>; <xref rid="RHansen2010" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="RWelch2019" ref-type="bibr">Welch and Munro 2019</xref>).</p><p>Our data suggest that whilst AtGTLP partially colocalized with TGN markers, SYP61 and VHAa1, and to a lesser extent, SYP43, in a portion of the analyzed ROIs, the number of ROIs, where the Pearson correlation coefficient was close to 0, which suggests no colocalization, is noteworthy. TGN is a vesicular-tubular compartment adjacent to the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic> side of a Golgi apparatus, but generally considered to be a distinct organelle with functions different from the Golgi (<xref rid="RGriffiths1986" ref-type="bibr">Griffiths and Simons 1986</xref>). Indeed, more recently, existence of two types of TGN in plant cells, Golgi-associated TGN (GA-TGN) and Golgi-independent TGN (free-TGN/GI-TGN)&#8212;a subpopulation of the TGN that is physiologically separated from Golgi stacks, has been reported (<xref rid="RStaehelin2008" ref-type="bibr">Staehelin and Kang 2008</xref>; <xref rid="RUemura2014" ref-type="bibr">Uemura et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="RViotti2010" ref-type="bibr">Viotti et al. 2010</xref>). The general role of TGN is to receive proteins modified in Golgi and direct them either for vacuoles, the plasma membrane or for secretion (<xref rid="RGriffiths1986" ref-type="bibr">Griffiths and Simons 1986</xref>) and therefore, this organelle is considered to be an important hub in the membrane traffic system, where cargo proteins are sorted, before being dispatched for their next destination (<xref rid="RKeller1997" ref-type="bibr">Keller and Simons 1997</xref>). In addition to TGN-resident SNAREs, involved in transport, other TGN-localized proteins include lipid-processing enzymes, which help to pack cargo proteins into transport vesicles (<xref rid="RGu2001" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al. 2001</xref>). Glycosylation is a sequential process, in which different types of sugar are added to glycans in a specific order, as the modified macromolecule travels from ER through Golgi apparatus to finally reach the TGN. In mammalian cells, some types of sugars, such as galactose and sialic acid, can be added to glycans in the TGN by TGN-localized GTs (<xref rid="RRabouille1995" ref-type="bibr">Rabouille et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="RStanley2011" ref-type="bibr">Stanley 2011</xref>). In plants, however, there are no reports of glycotransferase activity in the TGN. Based on the collected data, we therefore propose that AtGTLP is a <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi-localized protein.</p></sec><sec><title>AtGTLP&#8212;a novel fucosyltransferase?</title><p>Analysis of AtGTLP amino acid sequence has shown that its C-terminal domain bears resemblance to the conserved domain found in metazoan POFUTs, although no obvious sequence similarity was found between AtGTLP and the proteins which have been previously classified as members of FUT family in Arabidopsis. Although, at present, we lack evidence that would confirm GT or FUT activity in AtGTLP, we consider that this protein may potentially belong to a yet uncharacterized family of Arabidopsis proteins with either GT or FUT activity.</p><p>One interesting possibility that is worth considering is that AtGTLP is indeed a POFUT. Phylogenetic analyses report putative POFUTs in plants and suggest plant POFUTs are phylogenetically distant from POFUTs families in other organisms (POFUT1 and POFUT2 families) (<xref rid="RHansen2012" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="RSoto2019" ref-type="bibr">Soto et al. 2019</xref>). Interestingly however, recently described Arabidopsis putative POFUT, <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-FUCOSYLTRANSFERASE1 (AtOFT1), implicit in pollen tube penetration through the stigma-style interface, was reported to diverge from this pattern. Phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">AtOFT1</italic> has shown that it exhibits a relatively high sequence identity to members of POFUT1 family, compared to other putative POFUTs found in Arabidopsis (<xref rid="RSmith2018" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2018</xref>). As in silico analysis suggests that AtGTLP may also be potentially related to metazoan POFUTs, the possibility that yet uncharacterized families of POFUTs, more related to metazoan POFUTs than previously reported POFUTs, exist in Arabidopsis genome is worth further examinations.</p><p>In our subcellular localization study, we found that AtGTLP localizes mainly to <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi. Human POFUT1 and POFUT2 localize to the ER (<xref rid="RLuo2005" ref-type="bibr">Luo and Haltiwanger 2005</xref>; <xref rid="RLuo2006" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al. 2006</xref>), where the <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosylation process for most proteins starts (<xref rid="RStanley2011" ref-type="bibr">Stanley 2011</xref>). Arabidopsis POFUT with confirmed activity, SPINDY, is known to be active in nucleus/cytoplasm (<xref rid="RBi2023" ref-type="bibr">Bi et al. 2023</xref>; <xref rid="RKumar2023" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al. 2023</xref>; <xref rid="RZentella2023" ref-type="bibr">Zentella et al. 2023</xref>). However, it is the only POFUT discovered thus far with this subcellular localization (<xref rid="RSun2021" ref-type="bibr">Sun 2021</xref>). On the other hand, putative Arabidopsis POFUTs, such as AtOFT1 (<xref rid="RRobichaux2023" ref-type="bibr">Robichaux et al. 2023</xref>; <xref rid="RSmith2018" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2018</xref>), as well as FRIABLE1 (<xref rid="RNeumetzler2012" ref-type="bibr">Neumetzler et al. 2012</xref>) and ESMERALDA1 (<xref rid="RVerger2016" ref-type="bibr">Verger et al. 2016</xref>) were experimentally shown to localize to Golgi. In addition, &#945;1,3-fucosylation in sycamore cells, as well as &#945;1,4-fucosylation by FUT13 in Arabidopsis was shown to occur mainly in <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi cisternae (<xref rid="RFitchette1994" ref-type="bibr">Fitchette-Lain&#233; et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="RSchoberer2013" ref-type="bibr">Schoberer et al. 2013</xref>), suggesting that fucose is available at plant Golgi to be used as a substrate.</p><p>In relation to AtGTLP showing distant similarity to metazoan POFUTs, alternative possibility is that it may be a new type of plant fucosyltransferase. One type of macromolecules, which contain fucose are pectic polysaccharides&#8212;RG-I and RG-II. At present, biosynthesis of RG-I and RG-II is not fully understood, and no specific fucosyltransferase, which could be linked to synthesis of RG-I and RG-II side chains, has been identified (<xref rid="RSoto2019" ref-type="bibr">Soto et al. 2019</xref>; <xref rid="RVoxeur2012" ref-type="bibr">Voxeur et al. 2012</xref>), suggesting that yet uncharacterized type of fucosyltransferase is present in plants and responsible for this process.</p><p>GTs are a diverse family of enzymes and very few members of FUT family in Arabidopsis has been well-characterized thus far. Despite the fact that characteristics of AtGTLP, such as its <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi localization, type II topology and the presence of <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-FUT-like conserved domain, seem to agree with the assumption that it is a member of the glycosyltransferase family, the data currently available are not enough to conclusively state that AtGTLP is a GT or a type of FUT, precisely. Under standard growth conditions, <italic toggle="yes">atgtlp&#8722;/&#8722;</italic> single mutant displayed phenotype indistinguishable from Col-0 plants and one possible explanation for this result is that AtGTLP and related proteins with high amino acid sequence similarity to AtGTLP might have redundant functions. Protein At4g12700, which shows a very high sequence similarity to AtGTLP is one potential candidate. Further research is needed to confirm the presence of glycosyltransferase/fucosyltranferase activity, as well as the biological role of AtGTLP.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank K. Schumacher (Heidelberg University, Germany) for sharing materials.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Data</title><supplementary-material id="S1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="plantbiotechnology-41-1-23.1214a-s001.pdf" id="d67e827" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list id="DL1"><def-item><term>FUT</term><def><p>fucosyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GT</term><def><p>glycosyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POFUT</term><def><p>protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNARE</term><def><p>soluble <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SYP</term><def><p>syntaxin of plants</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TGN</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="RAdler2010"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Adler J, Parmryd I (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Quantifying colocalization by correlation: The Pearson correlation coefficient is superior to the Mander&#8217;s overlap coefficient.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cytometry</italic></source><volume>77A</volume>: <fpage>733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cyto.a.20896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20653013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RAsaoka2013"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Asaoka R, Uemura T, Ito J, Fujimoto M, Ito E, Ueda T, Nakano A (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis RABA1 GTPases are involved in transport between the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network and the plasma membrane, and are required for salinity stress tolerance.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J</italic></source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>240</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/tpj.12023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RBanfield2011"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Banfield DK (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of protein retention in the Golgi.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</italic></source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>a005264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21525512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/cshperspect.a005264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3140682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RBi2023"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bi Y, Shrestha R, Zhang Z, Hsu CC, Reyes AV, Karunadasa S, Baker PR, Maynard JC, Liu Y, Hakimi A, et al. (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>SPINDLY mediates <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosylation of hundreds of proteins and sugar-dependent growth in Arabidopsis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1318</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36739885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/plcell/koad023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10118272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RBoevink1998"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Boevink P, Oparka K, Santa Cruz S, Martin B, Betteridge A, Hawes C (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Stacks on tracks: The plant Golgi apparatus traffics on an actin/ER network.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J</italic></source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9750355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00208.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RCampbell2002"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Campbell RE, Tour O, Palmer AE, Steinbach PA, Baird GS, Zacharias DA, Tsien RY (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A monomeric red fluorescent protein.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source><volume>99</volume>: <fpage>7877</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.082243699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC122988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RCantarel2009"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cantarel BL, Coutinho PM, Rancurel C, Bernard T, Lombard V, Henrissat B (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes database (CAZy): An expert resource for Glycogenomics.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source><volume>37</volume>(Database): <fpage>D233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkn663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2686590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RClough1998"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Clough SJ, Bent AF (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: A simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana.</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J</italic></source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RDettmer2006"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dettmer J, Hong-Hermesdorf A, Stierhof YD, Schumacher K (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Vacuolar H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase activity is required for endocytic and secretory trafficking in Arabidopsis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16461582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.105.037978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1383645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RDunn2011"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dunn KW, Kamocka MM, McDonald JH (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A practical guide to evaluating colocalization in biological microscopy.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</italic></source><volume>300</volume>: <fpage>C723</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>C742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpcell.00462.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3074624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="REbine2008"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ebine K, Okatani Y, Uemura T, Goh T, Shoda K, Niihama M, Morita MT, Spitzer C, Otegui MS, Nakano A, et al. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A SNARE complex unique to seed plants is required for protein storage vacuole biogenesis and seed development of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana.</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>3006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18984676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.107.057711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2613668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RFasshauer1998"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fasshauer D, Sutton RB, Brunger AT, Jahn R (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Conserved structural features of the synaptic fusion complex: SNARE proteins reclassified as Q- and R-SNAREs.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source><volume>95</volume>: <fpage>15781</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9861047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.95.26.15781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC28121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RFitchette1994"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fitchette-Lain&#233; AC, Gomord V, Chekkafi A, Faye L (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Distribution of xylosylation and fucosylation in the plant Golgi apparatus.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J</italic></source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>682</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RFujiwara2014"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fujiwara M, Uemura T, Ebine K, Nishimori Y, Ueda T, Nakano A, Sato MH, Fukao Y (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Interactomics of Qa-SNARE in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana.</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell Physiol</italic></source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pcp/pcu038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RGriffiths1986"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Griffiths G, Simons K (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic> Golgi network: Sorting at the exit site of the Golgi complex.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source><volume>234</volume>: <fpage>438</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2945253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.2945253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RGu2001"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gu F, Crump CM, Thomas G (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Trans</italic>-Golgi network sorting.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Mol Life Sci</italic></source><volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1067</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11529500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/PL00000922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1424219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RHallgren2022"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hallgren J, Tsirigos KD, Pedersen MD, Almagro Armenteros JJ, Marcatili P, Nielsen H, Krogh A, Winther O (<year>2022</year>) DeepTMHMM predicts alpha and beta transmembrane proteins using deep neural networks. <italic toggle="yes">bioRxiv</italic>. doi: 10.1101/2022.04.08.487609</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RHansen2010"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hansen SF, Bettler E, Rinnan A, Engelsen SB, Breton C (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Exploring genomes for glycosyltransferases.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biosyst</italic></source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1773</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20556308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c000238k</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RHansen2012"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hansen SF, Harholt J, Oikawa A, Scheller HV (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plant glycosyltransferases beyond CAZy: A perspective on DUF families.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Front Plant Sci</italic></source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22629278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpls.2012.00059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3355507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RJahn2006"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jahn R, Scheller RH (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>SNAREs: Engines for membrane fusion.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm2002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RJumper2021"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jumper J, Evans R, Pritzel A, Green T, Figurnov M, Ronneberger O, Tunyasuvunakool K, Bates R, &#381;&#237;dek A, Potapenko A, et al. (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source><volume>596</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-021-03819-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8371605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKarimi2002"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Karimi M, Inz&#233; D, Depicker A (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>GATEWAY vectors for Agrobacterium-mediated plant transformation.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Plant Sci</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11992820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1360-1385(02)02251-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKeegstra2001"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Keegstra K, Raikhel N (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Plant glycosyltransferases.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Plant Biol</italic></source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11312132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1369-5266(00)00164-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKeller1997"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Keller P, Simons K (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Post-Golgi biosynthetic trafficking.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Sci</italic></source><volume>110</volume>: <fpage>3001</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9365270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.110.24.3001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKelley2015"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kelley LA, Mezulis S, Yates CM, Wass MN, Sternberg MJ (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The Phyre2 web portal for protein modeling, prediction and analysis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Protoc</italic></source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>845</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25950237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nprot.2015.053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5298202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKlepikova2016"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Klepikova AV, Kasianov AS, Gerasimov ES, Logacheva MD, Penin AA (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A high resolution map of the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> developmental transcriptome based on RNA-seq profiling.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant J</italic></source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1058</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/tpj.13312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RKumar2023"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kumar S, Wang Y, Zhou Y, Dillard L, Li FW, Sciandra CA, Sui N, Zentella R, Zahn E, Shabanowitz J, et al. (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Structure and dynamics of the Arabidopsis <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase SPINDLY.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36941311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-37279-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10027727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RLu2020"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lu S, Wang J, Chitsaz F, Derbyshire MK, Geer RC, Gonzales NR, Gwadz M, Hurwitz DI, Marchler GH, Song JS, et al. (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>CDD/SPARCLE: The conserved domain database in 2020.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source><volume>48</volume>(D1): <fpage>D265</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31777944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkz991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6943070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RLuo2005"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Luo Y, Haltiwanger RS (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosylation of notch occurs in the endoplasmic reticulum.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source><volume>280</volume>: <fpage>11289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M414574200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RLuo2006"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Luo Y, Koles K, Vorndam W, Haltiwanger RS, Panin VM (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase 2 adds <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucose to thrombospondin type 1 repeats.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source><volume>281</volume>: <fpage>9393</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M511975200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RMartinez2003"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martinez-Duncker I, Mollicone R, Candelier JJ, Breton C, Oriol R (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A new superfamily of protein-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferases, &#945; 2-fucosyltransferases, and &#945; 6-fucosyltransferases: Phylogeny and identification of conserved peptide motifs.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Glycobiology</italic></source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1C</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5C</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12966037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/glycob/cwg113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RNakagawa2007"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nakagawa T, Kurose T, Hino T, Tanaka K, Kawamukai M, Niwa Y, Toyooka K, Matsuoka K, Jinbo T, Kimura T (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Development of series of gateway binary vectors, pGWBs, for realizing efficient construction of fusion genes for plant transformation.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Biosci Bioeng</italic></source><volume>104</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17697981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1263/jbb.104.34</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RNeumetzler2012"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Neumetzler L, Humphrey T, Lumba S, Snyder S, Yeats TH, Usadel B, Vasilevski A, Patel J, Rose JK, Persson S, et al. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The FRIABLE1 gene product affects cell adhesion in Arabidopsis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e42914</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22916179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0042914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3419242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RRabouille1995"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rabouille C, Hui N, Hunte F, Kieckbusch R, Berger EG, Warren G, Nilsson T (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Mapping the distribution of Golgi enzymes involved in the construction of complex oligosaccharides.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Sci</italic></source><volume>108</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7615680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.108.4.1617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RRobichaux2023"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Robichaux KJ, Smith DK, Blea MN, Weigand C, Harper JF, Wallace IS (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>Disruption of pollen tube homogalacturonan synthesis relieves pollen tube penetration defects in the Arabidopsis <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-FUCOSYLTRANSFERASE1 mutant.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Reprod</italic></source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37222783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00497-023-00468-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSaint2004"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saint-Jore-Dupas C, Gomord V, Paris N (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Protein localization in the plant Golgi apparatus and the <italic toggle="yes">trans-</italic>Golgi network.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Mol Life Sci</italic></source><volume>61</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-003-3354-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11138554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSanderfoot2007"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sanderfoot A (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Increases in the number of SNARE genes parallels the rise of multicellularity among the green plants.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>144</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.106.092973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1913785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSchindelin2012"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, Preibisch S, Rueden C, Saalfeld S, Schmid B, et al. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fiji: An open-source platform for biological-image analysis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Methods</italic></source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3855844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSchoberer2013"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schoberer J, Liebminger E, Botchway SW, Strasser R, Hawes C (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Time-resolved fluorescence imaging reveals differential interactions of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycan processing enzymes across the Golgi stack in planta.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>161</volume>: <fpage>1737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23400704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.112.210757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3613452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSegami2014"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Segami S, Makino S, Miyake A, Asaoka M, Maeshima M (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of vacuoles and H<sup>+</sup>-pyrophosphatase visualized by monomeric green fluorescent protein in Arabidopsis: Artifactual bulbs and native intravacuolar spherical structures.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3416</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.114.127571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4371836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RShimizu2021"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shimizu Y, Takagi J, Ito E, Ito Y, Ebine K, Komatsu Y, Goto Y, Sato M, Toyooka K, Ueda T, et al. (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Cargo sorting zones in the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network visualized by super-resolution confocal live imaging microscopy in plants.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1901</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33772008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-021-22267-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RShimizu2022"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shimizu Y, Uemura T (<year>2022</year>) <article-title>The sorting of cargo proteins in the plant <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Front Plant Sci</italic></source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>957995</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36035717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpls.2022.957995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9402974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSmith2018"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith DK, Jones DM, Lau JBR, Cruz ER, Brown E, Harper JF, Wallace IS (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>A putative protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferase facilitates pollen tube penetration through the stigma-style interface.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>176</volume>: <fpage>2804</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29467178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.17.01577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSoto2019"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Soto MJ, Urbanowicz BR, Hahn MG (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Plant fucosyltransferases and the emerging biological importance of fucosylated plant structures.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Rev Plant Sci</italic></source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>338</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RStaehelin2008"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Staehelin LA, Kang BH (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Nanoscale architecture of endoplasmic reticulum export sites and of Golgi membranes as determined by electron tomography.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>147</volume>: <fpage>1454</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18678738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.108.120618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2492626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RStanley2011"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stanley P (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Golgi glycosylation.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</italic></source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>a005199</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/cshperspect.a005199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3062213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RStenmark2009"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stenmark H (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rab GTPases as coordinators of vesicle traffic.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</italic></source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19603039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm2728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSun2021"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sun TP (<year>2021</year>) <article-title>Novel nucleocytoplasmic protein <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosylation by SPINDLY regulates diverse developmental processes in plants.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Struct Biol</italic></source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33476897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sbi.2020.12.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8222059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RTie2018"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tie HC, Ludwig A, Sandin S, Lu L (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>The spatial separation of processing and transport functions to the interior and periphery of the Golgi stack.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">eLife</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e41301</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30499774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.41301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6294550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RUemura2012"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Uemura T, Kim H, Saito C, Ebine K, Ueda T, Schulze-Lefert P, Nakano A (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Qa-SNAREs localized to the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network regulate multiple transport pathways and extracellular disease resistance in plants.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source><volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1784</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22307646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1115146109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3277133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RUemura2019"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Uemura T, Nakano RT, Takagi J, Wang Y, Kramer K, Finkemeier I, Nakagami H, Tsuda K, Ueda T, Schulze-Lefert P, et al. (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>A Golgi-released subpopulation of the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network mediates protein secretion in Arabidopsis.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>179</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30545905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.18.01228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6426420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RUemura2014"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Uemura T, Suda Y, Ueda T, Nakano A (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Dynamic behavior of the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network in root tissues of Arabidopsis revealed by super-resolution live imaging.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell Physiol</italic></source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24443496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pcp/pcu010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RUemura2004"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Uemura T, Ueda T, Ohniwa RL, Nakano A, Takeyasu K, Sato MH (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Systematic analysis of SNARE molecules in Arabidopsis: Dissection of the post-Golgi network in plant cells.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Struct Funct</italic></source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1247/csf.29.49</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RVerger2016"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Verger S, Chabout S, Gineau E, Mouille G (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Cell adhesion in plants is under the control of putative <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosyltransferases.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Development</italic></source><volume>143</volume>: <fpage>2536</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27317803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.132308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4958334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RViotti2010"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Viotti C, Bubeck J, Stierhof YD, Krebs M, Langhans M, van den Berg W, van Dongen W, Richter S, Geldner N, Takano J, et al. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Endocytic and secretory traffic in Arabidopsis merge in the <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-Golgi network/early endosome, an independent and highly dynamic organelle.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Cell</italic></source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1344</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.109.072637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2879741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RVoxeur2012"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Voxeur A, Andr&#233; A, Breton C, Lerouge P (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of putative rhamnogalacturonan-II specific glycosyltransferases in Arabidopsis using a combination of bioinformatics approaches.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e51129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23272088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0051129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3522684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RWelch2019"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Welch LG, Munro S (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>A tale of short tails, through thick and thin: Investigating the sorting mechanisms of Golgi enzymes.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett</italic></source><volume>593</volume>: <fpage>2452</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31344261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/1873-3468.13553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RZentella2023"><label/><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zentella R, Wang Y, Zahn E, Hu J, Jiang L, Shabanowitz J, Hunt DF, Sun TP (<year>2023</year>) <article-title>SPINDLY <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-fucosylates nuclear and cytoplasmic proteins involved in diverse cellular processes in plants.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Plant Physiol</italic></source><volume>191</volume>: <fpage>1546</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36740243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/plphys/kiad011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10022643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes><title>Author contribution</title><p>N.R. carried out all experiments. Y.I., E.I., and T.U. designed the research. Y.K. performed AlphaFold2 analysis. N.R., Y.I., E.I., and T.U. interpreted the data and wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (grant number: 22K19327 and 22H02643 to T.U., 21K06210 to E.I., 23H00382 and 22K06260 to Y.I.), by JST (grant number: JPMJCR20E5 to T.U.), by the Asahi Glass Foundation to T.U., by Ito Science Foundation to E.I., and by Sasakawa Scientific Research Grant from the Japan Science Society to N.R. K.Y. was supported by Basis for Supporting Innovative Drug Discovery and Life Science Research (BINDS) [JP23am0101065] from Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (AMED). The AlphaFold2 calculation in this research was conducted on Chaen, the supercomputer of the Center for Interdisciplinary AI and Data Science at Ochanomizu University.</p></notes><notes><title>Description of Supplementary Files</title><p>Supplementary Table S1. List of primers.</p></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>