<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3242767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3242767.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3242767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3242767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22205979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-16586</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biodiversity</subject><subject>Community Ecology</subject><subject>Conservation Science</subject><subject>Freshwater Ecology</subject><subject>Microbial Ecology</subject><subject>Population Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied Microbiology</subject><subject>Host-Pathogen Interaction</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Herpetology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Wildlife</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Veterinary Microbiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of Microorganisms Cultured from Injured and Repressed Tissue Regeneration Sites in Endangered Giant Aquatic Ozark Hellbender Salamanders</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Microbes Cultured from Injured Hellbender Tissues</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names initials="CA">Cheryl A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names initials="CM">C. Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names initials="SL">Sarah L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names initials="VM">Veronica M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names initials="TC">Thomas C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names initials="JT">Jeffrey T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names initials="AL">Amber L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavano</surname><given-names initials="JJ">Joseph J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byram</surname><given-names initials="JK">J. Kelly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrila</surname><given-names initials="J">Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names initials="MA">Max A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Arizona State University, School of Life Sciences, The Biodesign Institute, Center for Infectious Diseases and Vaccinology, Tempe, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>NASA/Johnson Space Center, Habitability and Environmental Factors Division, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>EASI, Wyle Laboratories, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Missouri Department of Conservation, Jefferson City, Missouri, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>University of Florida, Florida Museum of Natural History, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liles</surname><given-names initials="MR">Mark R.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Auburn University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>maxn@flmnh.ufl.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MAN CAN CMO. Performed the experiments: ALP JTB SLC VMG TCM JJT JKB. Analyzed the data: MAN CAN CMO ALP JTB SLC VMG TCM JJT JKB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MAN CMO JTB. Wrote the paper: MAN CAN CMO ALP JB.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">203141</issue-id><elocation-id>e28906</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-16 19:25:18.817"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="cc0license">https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration, which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0028906.pdf"/><abstract><p>Investigation into the causes underlying the rapid, global amphibian decline provides critical insight into the effects of changing ecosystems. Hypothesized and confirmed links between amphibian declines, disease, and environmental changes are increasingly represented in published literature. However, there are few long-term amphibian studies that include data on population size, abnormality/injury rates, disease, and habitat variables to adequately assess changes through time. We cultured and identified microorganisms isolated from abnormal/injured and repressed tissue regeneration sites of the endangered Ozark Hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>, to discover potential causative agents responsible for their significant decline in health and population. This organism and our study site were chosen because the population and habitat of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> have been intensively studied from 1969&#8211;2009, and the abnormality/injury rate and apparent lack of regeneration were established. Although many bacterial and fungal isolates recovered were common environmental organisms, several opportunistic pathogens were identified in association with only the injured tissues of <italic toggle="yes">C.a. bishopi</italic>. Bacterial isolates included <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>, a known amphibian pathogen, <italic toggle="yes">Granulicetella adiacens</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Gordonai terrae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Aerococcus viridans</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and a variety of Pseudomonads, including <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P. stutzeri</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">and P. alcaligenes</italic>. Fungal isolates included species in the genera <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acremonium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Curvularia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic>, and the Class Hyphomycetes. Many of the opportunistic pathogens identified are known to form biofilms. Lack of isolation of the same organism from all wounds suggests that the etiological agent responsible for the damage to <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> may not be a single organism. To our knowledge, this is the first study to profile the external microbial consortia cultured from a Cryptobranchid salamander. The incidence of abnormalities/injury and retarded regeneration in <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> may have many contributing factors including disease and habitat degradation. Results from this study may provide insight into other amphibian population declines.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The amphibian decline controversy has focused on many factors that affect amphibian populations to varying degrees <xref rid="pone.0028906-Lannoo1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, including habitat loss and degradation, climate change, pollution, increased ultraviolet B (UV-B) radiation, direct exploitation, introduced species and disease, including infectious disease <xref rid="pone.0028906-Halliday1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Beebee1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Although evidence of disease in amphibian populations is not new, early literature on amphibian health in natural populations is quite scattered, deals primarily with anurans and/or local problems, or was initiated because of concerns related to supply and demand and decline of commercial harvest <xref rid="pone.0028906-Anonymous1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-National1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In the late 1960's and early 1970's, various biological supply houses noted problems in the commercial supply of amphibians causing Maugh <xref rid="pone.0028906-Maugh1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> to comment on &#8220;the apparent short supply and diseased state of amphibians collected in nature&#8221;.</p><p>The review of mycoses of amphibians by Reichenback-Klinke and Elkan <xref rid="pone.0028906-ReichenbachKlinke1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> primarily focuses on <italic toggle="yes">Basidiobolus ranarum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Saprolegnia parasitica</italic> and indicates the dearth of knowledge relating to the distribution and importance of microfungi associated with amphibians. With few exceptions, this void continued for the next two decades <xref rid="pone.0028906-Hutchison1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Tills1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The impetus for research on amphibian microbes became a major focal point of the 1<sup>st</sup> World Herpetology Congress in Canterbury, England in 1989, where herpetologists shared their observations on declining frog populations and developed initial strategies to investigate the potential problems. The discovery that the chytridiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic>, a zoosporic fungus related to infectious oomycete water molds, <italic toggle="yes">Saprolegnia</italic> spp., was capable of causing lethal dermatitis in amphibians led to a proliferation of studies <xref rid="pone.0028906-Taylor1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. After reviewing studies of microbes implicated in amphibian population declines, including chytridiomycosis, <italic toggle="yes">Ranavirus</italic> disease, saprolegniosis and <italic toggle="yes">Ribieroia</italic> spp., Daszak et al. <xref rid="pone.0028906-Daszak1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> concluded that &#8220;available data provide the clearest link for the fungal disease amphibian chytridiomycosis&#8221;. Herpetological Review dedicated an entire section to amphibian chytridiomycosis geographical distribution <xref rid="pone.0028906-Greenbaum1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Woodhams1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p><p>The advances in research on the secretions, structure, and functions of amphibian integument and their products reveal a remarkable complexity of bioactive secretions and diversity of amines, peptides, alkaloids, bufodienolides, and other compounds <xref rid="pone.0028906-Erspamer1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Heatwole1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The presence of antimicrobial agents in amphibian skin hypothesized by Csordas and Michl <xref rid="pone.0028906-Csordas1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> and Croce et al. <xref rid="pone.0028906-Croce1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> has led to an increased interest in the relationship of the bacteria and fungi present in the skin of amphibians and the antimicrobial peptides and metabolites that they produce <xref rid="pone.0028906-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Woodhams2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Some of these peptides and alkaloids can inhibit the growth of pathogenic fungi <xref rid="pone.0028906-RollinsSmith2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Simmaco1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> and common cutaneous bacteria from the terrestrial salamander <italic toggle="yes">Plethodon cinerus</italic> can inhibit pathogenic fungi <xref rid="pone.0028906-Lauer2" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Evidence also suggests that symbiotic bacteria may contribute to innate immune defense of some amphibians <xref rid="pone.0028906-Woodhams2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. While evidence suggests that these antimicrobial compounds and symbiotic bacteria can provide some level of protection for amphibians against microbial invaders <xref rid="pone.0028906-Woodhams2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Lauer2" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, the connection between disease and amphibian decline has been confirmed for some amphibian populations <xref rid="pone.0028906-Collins1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. However, long-term amphibian studies, especially those including population and environmental data, are so rare that we have very few data to support many claims related to decline or changes in, or the health of, wild amphibian populations <xref rid="pone.0028906-Blaustein1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. One long-term study subject, the Ozark Hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganensis bishopi</italic>, and its habitat within a 4.6 km section of the North Fork of White River (NFWR), has been the subject of numerous investigations since the intensive 110 day surveys conducted during 1969&#8211;1971 <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson4" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>.</p><p>In 1969, the 4.6 km research section within the North Fork of White River (NFWR), Ozark County, Missouri, was a crystalline, substantially spring-fed stream located in the least densely human populated area of the second least densely populated county in the state (9 people/sq mi; <xref rid="pone.0028906-OSEDA1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>). Only one rarely used sportsman's cabin graced the banks of the research section in 1969. The springs and occasionally the river were used as drinking water by some locals and visitors. From 1969 to 1980, 169 days of skin-diving surveys, coupled with environmental sampling, were conducted in this section, including some in every year and within every calendar month, but not every month of every year <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson5" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Population and ecological studies of the aquatic Ozark Hellbender <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> and its habitat were conducted in this section during 1969&#8211;1971 <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson4" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Other ecological studies included year-round water quality, benthic habitat, macro-invertebrate structure, cottid fish diet studies, and numerous shorter-term studies <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Cooper1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. These early studies in the NFWR found an immense and healthy population of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>, as many as 428 individuals/km, and almost no abnormalities/injuries. Only 2.9% of 479 individuals observed in 1969 were abnormal/injured and they exhibited rapid regeneration capabilities <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson5" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Hiler1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Additional surveys between 1972 to 1980 continued to show immense and healthy populations of Ozark Hellbenders <xref rid="pone.0028906-Peterson1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson6" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. All surveys during this time period ranged from between 9&#8211;12 individual Ozark hellbenders collected per hour per person (Nickerson et al, unpublished data). Reassessment of the ecological characteristics of the NFWR conducted in 2004&#8211;2007 revealed extensive habitat alteration and degradation, including increased land development, siltation, sedimentation, and water quality degradation <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson7" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Community changes included algal and nuisance aquatic vegetation blooms, otter establishment, and fish and macroinvertebrate community alterations <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson7" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Canoe use within the NFWR significantly increased <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson7" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Intensive surveys of the NFWR hellbender population conducted in 2005 yielded only 55 individuals, of which 26 (i.e., 47%) had visible abnormalities/injuries, including loss of limbs, limbs with exposed bones, and degeneration of other tissues which did not regenerate or had remarkably retarded regeneration (J. Briggler, unpublished data). The high prevalence of abnormalities/injuries and the lack of the historically characteristic (rapid) regeneration of injured/affected tissue in hellbenders in the NFWR was the impetus for our examination of the microbial community associated with the observed abnormalities/injuries.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>Our results reflect our strategy to optimize chances for successful culture of potentially pathogenic microorganisms by using three different media for each sample; blood agar (all purpose growth media), mannitol salts (differential and selective media), Sabouraud's (differential and selective media often used to isolate fungi) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028906-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0028906-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Representative microbial flora cultured from <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> on three different media.</title><p>Swabs from injured (or uninjured control) tissues of six adult hellbenders were streaked onto three different microbiological culture media: Sheep's blood agar (A&#8211;G), Mannitol Salt Agar (H), and Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (I). * Indicates uninjured control sample.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>An evaluation of the microbial flora sampled from <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> indicated the presence of common environmental flora from both abnormal/injured and uninjured limbs. A wide variety of both Gram positive and Gram negative bacteria were isolated. While no consistent pattern of bacterial colonization was observed between uninjured and abnormal/injured body parts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t002">2</xref>), several interesting microbial associations were observed. The genus <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> was identified in 9 separate occasions, although the amphibian pathogenic species <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>, was identified only once from an abnormal/injured animal (NFWR 139 - lower lip). Likewise, certain organisms that can cause human infection were also identified, including the opportunistic pseudomonal pathogens <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (NFWR 135 - right back limb), <italic toggle="yes">P. stutzeri</italic> (NFWR 134 - right back; NFWR- 135 right back), <italic toggle="yes">P. alcaligenes</italic> (NFWR &#8211; right front), and the pseudomonal-like pathogen, <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> (NFWR 136 &#8211; left front limb). In addition, the poultry pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Riemerella anatipestifer</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> was also isolated only from abnormal/injured animals. On rare occasion, one bacterial species would represent the vast majority of the colonies from a given abnormal/injured sample as exemplified by the known human pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella adiacens</italic> (formerly <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus adiacens</italic>; <xref rid="pone.0028906-Siqueira1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>), which represented 91% of the 163 bacterial isolates found on the blood agar plate associated with the NFWR 139 lower lip sample. When using Sabouraud Dextrose Agar, only fungi were isolated, except for one plate (from the injured animal NFWR 135 - left front limb) where 4 colonies of <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae (previously Micrococcus</italic>) were found, which is a common inhabitant on human skin that has been increasingly associated with infectious disease in humans <xref rid="pone.0028906-Ma1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Bacteria identified on Blood Agar.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb sampled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony Forming Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Riemerella anatipestifer</italic>&#10731;; Unidentified Gram positive species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Kocuria varians</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Microbacterium luteolum</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseomonas cervicalis</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas alcaligenes</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic> (3 morphologically different colonies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Kocuria rosea</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria varians</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> (2 morphologically different colonies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aerococcus viridans</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>&#10731;;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Delftia acidovorans</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Exiguobacterium acetylicum</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Acenitobacter baumannii</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria; Kocuria varians</italic> (2 morphologically different colonies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic> (2 morphologically different colonies); <italic toggle="yes">Kocurea rosea</italic>; Unidentified species - unable to isolate (3 morphologically different colonies); Unidentified Gram positive species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseomonas cervicalis</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria rosea</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria varians</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Myroides</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria rosea</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas aurantiaca</italic>; Unidentified species - unable to isolate; Unidentified Gram positive species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria varians</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas paucimobilis</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Lip</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella adiacens</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila/caviae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus sphaericus/fusiformis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium radiobacter</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus lentus</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Geobacillus thermoglucosidasius/thermodenitrificans</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lytae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium radiobacter</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas paucimobilis</italic>; Unidentified Gram positive species; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Dermacoccus</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Kytococcus</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus</italic>&#10731;; Unidentified Gram negative species; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium radiobacter</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Ewingella Americana</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Brachybacterium alementarium</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas paucimobilis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Gordonia terrae</italic>&#10731;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Colony Forming Units represent the number of microbial colonies counted on each plate. Sample plates which had no growth are not listed. The appearance of different morphologies for singles species is noted. Asterisk (*) indicates control sample from uninjured limb. Diamond (&#10731;) indicates an isolate identified by 16S sequencing (percent similarity of greater than or equal to 98%). NFWR&#8202;=&#8202;North Fork of White River samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Bacteria identified on Mannitol Salt Agar.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb sampled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony Forming Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Exiguobacterium acetylicum</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Curtobacterium flaccumfaciens</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus megaterium</italic>; Unidentified Gram positive species (2 morphologically different colonies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus hominis</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Brevibacterium casei</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus sciuri</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus warneri</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Exiguobacterium acetylicum</italic>&#10731;; <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus megaterium</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus hominus/novobisepticus</italic>; Unidentified Gram positive species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus vitulinus</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic> (2 morphologically different colonies); Unidentified Gram positive species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Dermacoccus</italic> species/<italic toggle="yes">Kytococcus</italic> species; <italic toggle="yes">Gemella morbillorum</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unidentified species - unable to isolate</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Dermacoccus/Kytococcus</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus megatarium</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Lip</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lytae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Brevibacterium casei</italic>&#10731;, <italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic> (2 morphologically different colonies); <italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta/vesicularis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus/lylae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus lentus</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pantoea agglomerans</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pantoea</italic> species</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Colony Forming Units represent the number of colonies counted on each plate. Sample plates without growth are not listed. The appearance of different morphologies for singles species is noted. Asterisk (*) indicates control sample from uninjured limb. Diamond (&#10731;) indicates an isolate identified by 16S sequencing. NFWR&#8202;=&#8202;North Fork of White River samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Fungal isolates were consistent with common environmental flora from genera that included <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acremonium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Curvularia</italic>, and the Class Hyphomycetes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t003">Tables 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t004">4</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t005">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Fungi identified on Blood Agar.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb sampled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony Forming Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species; <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species; <italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species (2 different species); <italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species; <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">750</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species (2 different species);</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> (2 different species); <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Colony Forming Units represent the number of colonies counted on each plate. Sample plates without growth were not listed. Genera with different morphological characteristics suggesting different species are noted. Asterisk (*) indicates control sample from uninjured limb. NFWR&#8202;=&#8202;North Fork of White River samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Fungi identified on Mannitol Salt Agar.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb sampled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony Forming Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladisporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (3 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Exophilia</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aureobasidium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acremonium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Lip</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">960</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Colony Forming Units represent the number of colonies counted on each plate. Sample plates without growth are not listed. Genera with different morphological characteristics suggesting different species are noted. Asterisk (*) indicates control sample from uninjured limb. NFWR&#8202;=&#8202;North Fork of White River samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Fungi identified on Sabouraud Dextrose Agar.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t005-5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t005.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb sampled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony Forming Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Exophilia</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Wangiella species</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acremonium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Curvularia</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species (3 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hyphomycetes</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower Lip</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Acremonium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Sporothrix</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species (2 different species)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Front</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right Back</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic> species</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic> species</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>Colony Forming Units represent the number of colonies counted on each plate. Sample plates without growth are not listed. Genera with different morphological characteristics suggesting different species are noted. Asterisk (*) indicates control sample from uninjured limb. NFWR&#8202;=&#8202;North Fork of White River samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> population decline in the NFWR is well documented and of significant concern <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson6" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Briggler1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Wheeler1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Many reasons for the decline in population and health of the Ozark Hellbender have been suggested, including flooding <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson5" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson8" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> amphibian harvesting <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson6" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, the use of the anesthetic MS-222 (Tricane) <xref rid="pone.0028906-Byram1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Byram2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, the reintroduction and introduction of species including otters and trout <xref rid="pone.0028906-Briggler1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Gall1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, habitat alteration and degradation <xref rid="pone.0028906-Trauth1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, disease including those having a genetic, chemical, or infectious etiology <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Hiler1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Wheeler1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Byram1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Byram2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Trauth1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Bodinof1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, and the interaction of these factors <xref rid="pone.0028906-Briggler1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Many of these hypothesized causal agents of decline have been investigated to various degrees, yet disease research has largely been limited to <italic toggle="yes">B. dendrobatidis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Briggler2" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Bodinof1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, and prior to our study, the microbial community associated with the abnormalities typifying the affected hellbenders had not been assessed. As a variety of pathogenic microbes have been linked to amphibian declines, it is critical that the microbial community be examined for all potential disease agents and that research not be initially limited to a single potential infectious agent until causation has been properly evaluated and established.</p><p>While our microbiological evaluations in this study indicated common environmental organisms in both abnormal/injured and uninjured Ozark Hellbenders, several opportunistic pathogenic organisms were identified that were associated only with the abnormal tissue/injuries of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>, such as <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>, a known pathogen of amphibians <xref rid="pone.0028906-JuliaManresa1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Barribeau1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella adiacens</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-DelPozo1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas malophilia</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Denton1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>, and a variety of opportunistic pathogen Pseudomonad species - <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Rumbaugh1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P. stutzeri</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Lalucat1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref> and <italic toggle="yes">P. alcaligenes</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0028906-Valenstein1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. These microbial pathogens are known to form biofilms in the environment and/or in vivo in the infected host. Several of the filamentous fungi isolated in this study, including <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">and Cladosporidium</italic> are genera containing opportunistic pathogens that are known to be associated with environmental biofilms <xref rid="pone.0028906-DeLucca1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. Multispecies biofilms may interact synergistically yielding an increased resistance to antibacterial agents <xref rid="pone.0028906-Burmlle1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. While a possible cause and effect role for biofilms in disease progression observed in the Ozark Hellbenders is outside the scope of this study, this observation warrants investigation in future studies. The lack of isolation of the same organism from multiple wounds suggests that none of the organisms identified were the sole etiological agent responsible for the damage to <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>. If the immune system of the injured <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> were repressed, it is possible that a combination of the isolated opportunistic pathogens may have contributed to the observed tissue damage. The Gram positive opportunistic pathogen, <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, was isolated from one animal. While the presence of <italic toggle="yes">S. pneumoniae</italic> may be the result of contamination during collection or processing, the genus <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> has been found by the EPA downstream of our NFWR research site.</p><p>Reintroduced or introduced species may not only be a source of pathogenic microbes in the NFWR, but in some cases may also increase injury, and subsequently infection rates by creating open sores. River otters (<italic toggle="yes">Lutra</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Lontra canadensis</italic>) used in reintroduction programs are known to carry a suite of pathogenic microbes, including Gram positive <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> spp. and Gram negative <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> spp. <xref rid="pone.0028906-Kimber1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Otters reintroduced into Missouri were sourced from Louisiana and could carry many different microbes which are not found in the streams of the Ozark Highlands <xref rid="pone.0028906-Low1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. We speculate that reintroduced otters may introduce pathogenic microbes into the environment through fecal transmission or direct contact with hellbenders, crayfish (the primary prey of both otters and hellbenders), or other species. In addition, river otters are capable of killing or injuring <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>. Non-lethal injuries such as bites or scratches yielding open sores may provide a pathway for pathogens. Non-native rainbow trout (<italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) and brown trout (<italic toggle="yes">Salmo trutta</italic>) are stocked in the NFWR annually. These trout come from multiple hatcheries with multiple water sources and are transferred between hatcheries, which have known reoccurring water quality issues, including harboring pathogenic microorganisms <xref rid="pone.0028906-Missouri1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. While we know of no predation of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> by salmonids in the wild, hatchery-raised trout released into the NFWR and other water bodies may serve as a source for pathogens.</p><p>Increased recreational use of NFWR may also be a source of hellbender injury and pathogenic microbes. Canoeing and other water activities may disturb or dislodge habitat rocks, inadvertently injuring hellbenders located underneath <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson7" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Humans may also be a source of pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">S. pneumoniae</italic>, one of the opportunistic bacteria found in this study.</p><p>The rapid regeneration that historically typified injured hellbenders was not apparent in recent studies of the NFWR population. Based on data collected in 1969, hellbender injuries (i.e., tail holes) induced by tagging healed completely with no sign of infection and no visible scars within two months (Nickerson unpublished data). The remarkable regenerative capacity of salamanders has been known since first reported by Spallanzani in 1769 <xref rid="pone.0028906-Scadding1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. Regenerative studies have included phylogenetic, seasonal, and environmental analysis of limb regeneration <xref rid="pone.0028906-Scadding1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0028906-Young1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>. Environmental factors that have been considered to affect regeneration include temperature, diet, photoperiod, parasitism, infection, and quality of terrestrial and aquatic microhabitats <xref rid="pone.0028906-Young1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>. Human-induced alterations to the NFWR and surrounding landscape have resulted in changes to the physical-chemical properties of the NFWR, including nutrient-loading, introduction of estrogenic chemical levels, algal blooms, and a microbial content deemed unsafe for full body contact by state and federal agencies <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson7" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Previous studies investigating the impact of human activities on NFWR water quality revealed relatively high concentrations of total phosphorus (6&#8211;52 &#181;g L&#8722;<sup>1</sup>) and total nitrogen (0.35&#8211;3.06 mg L&#8722;<sup>1</sup>) in the 4.6 km research site originally investigated by Nickerson and Mays <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. The impact of this type of increased nutrient level on the hellbenders was investigated by Solis et al., which focused on a historically populated area, located 11.3 km downstream of the Nickerson and Mays site <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis2" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Not unexpectedly, the site studied by Solis et al. indicated that nutrient concentrations (including total phosphorous and nitrogen) exceeded the EPA recommended criteria in two thirds of the samples <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. However, a direct correlation between these elevated levels and abnormalities/disease of the hellbenders was not supported, as all individual concentrations of nutrients and organic chemicals were at much lower levels than any laboratory and field experiments shown to have deleterious effects on amphibians <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. Likewise, serum samples from <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> collected at the Solis et al. site were analyzed for possible endocrine disrupting chemicals, however, none were detected at levels above the EPA and Missouri Clean Water Commission criteria for aquatic organisms <xref rid="pone.0028906-Solis2" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Thus, the direct impact of increased chemical levels on the hellbenders remains inconclusive.</p><p>The impact of eutrophication associated with human activity was further investigated in a periphyton survey of the NFWR in 2006 to determine if changes in the periphyton communities could be a factor in the Ozark Hellbender decline <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Some Periphyton, such as cyanobacteria (i.e., blue-green algae) may cause cutaneous damage, neural and hepatic effects, tumor induction, diarrhea, vomiting, respiratory dysfunction, convulsions and occasionally death <xref rid="pone.0028906-Communicable1" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>. The periphyton community within the NFWR 4.6 km Nickerson and Mays research section consisted of diatoms, chlorophytes, and cyanobacteria <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. The green algae <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora spp.</italic> achieved relative abundances of &gt;90% of the total periphyton community <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Blooms of the benthic, filamentous <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora spp.</italic> are a visible indicator of eutrophication and are linked to phosphorus concentration with 20 &#181;g &#181;L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> being the threshold for <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora</italic> dominance <xref rid="pone.0028906-Cattaneo1" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Chetelat1" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>. High nitrate concentrations are an issue with karst topography such as that in the NFWR drainage <xref rid="pone.0028906-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref> and increases in human usage and poor sewage facilities. Large <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora</italic> spp. blooms have been a component of the NFWR since at least 1968, but have increased over the decades and large floating algal masses seen during recent summers were not a component of the NFWR 4.6 km section during the early surveys <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Increased algal levels are known to increase both biofilm formation and antimicrobial resistance, and <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora spp</italic> mats maintain higher <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> densities than the surrounding aquatic habitat <xref rid="pone.0028906-Caramujo1" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Englebert1" ref-type="bibr">[87]</xref>. Green algae (<italic toggle="yes">Cladophora sp.</italic>) mats may have almost ubiquitous populations of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and enterococci, which may survive at least six months of drying <xref rid="pone.0028906-Whitman1" ref-type="bibr">[88]</xref>. A 2007 study of total coliform (TC) bacteria and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> content was conducted at multiple sites and habitats in the NFWR between Mark Twain National Forest Campground Access and Norfork Reservoir, as well as springs which flow into the NFWR <xref rid="pone.0028906-Pitt1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>. Total coliform levels exceeded the values deemed safe for full body contact by Missouri Department of Natural Resources (MDNR) in 70 of 94 individual water samples and 25 of the 94 samples also surpassed concentrations of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> deemed safe for full body contact <xref rid="pone.0028906-Pitt1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>.</p><p>Our results do not preclude that an infectious agent caused or exacerbated the tissue damage observed in Ozark Hellbenders, as other microorganisms, which would not grow on the media used in this experiment, may have been present (i.e., the microbial diversity observed in this study is likely a subset of the total microbial diversity). Alternatively, if the immune system of the abnormal/injured <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> was suppressed, many of the opportunistic pathogens that were isolated in this study, alone or in combination, may have caused infection which was responsible for or served to exacerbate the tissue damage. As such, the increase in incidence of abnormalities/injuries and retardation of tissue regeneration may have multiple contributing factors including changes in the Ozark Hellbenders' susceptibility to infection and exposure to microorganisms. The Ozark hellbender is a federally listed endangered species that has yet to have successfully reproduced in captivity. The unavailability of healthy Ozark hellbenders, small sample size, and conservation status precluded our ability to evaluate all of Koch's Postulates. However, this study provides the most complete analysis of potential microbial stressors on Ozark hellbenders to date and places these findings in the context of habitat alterations. Follow up studies are planned to identify causative mechanism(s) and environmental factors that are contributing to health and population declines in this endangered species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The Ozark Hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>, is now listed as endangered and populations have been extirpated and face extinction in much of the former range. The NFWR currently supports only a very small population of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic>, of which about 50% within the original NFWR research section of Nickerson and Mays <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson3" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0028906-Nickerson4" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> have substantial abnormalities/injuries (J. Briggler unpublished data). On 17 August 2007, we methodically searched a portion of the NFWR by snorkeling and lifting rocks. We located and captured six adult hellbenders, all with abnormalities/injuries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0028906-t006">Table 6</xref>). Each individual hellbender was placed into a clean bucket filled with river water and then measured, weighed, and individually photographed. All <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> were visually inspected for the presence of leeches, injuries, or abnormalities. The feet/limbs showing signs of infection (e.g., lesions, sores or exposed bone) were swabbed with sterile, buffered swabs. In addition, the lower lip of one individual with a raw sore was swabbed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028906-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Swabs were then streaked onto three different microbiological culture media: sheep's blood agar (SBA), a general all purpose growth medium that supports the culture of a large number of microorganisms and also indicates hemolytic activity; Mannitol Salt Agar (MSA), primarily selective for halo-tolerant bacteria such as staphylococci; and Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDX), primarily selective for fungi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0028906-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Given the very small population of <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> currently existing in the NFWR and given that no animals without abnormality/injury were captured throughout the duration of this study, two feet showing no signs of infection from two <italic toggle="yes">C. a. bishopi</italic> were swabbed in the same manner and served as uninfected controls. The swabs were streaked onto the different agar plates, and sample plate lids were immediately added and secured with tape. Secured plates were immediately placed into styrofoam coolers with ice packs and transported by vehicle to St. Louis, MO, and flown to the Microbiology Laboratory at the NASA Johnson Space Center (Houston, TX) for microbial identification. Bacterial and fungal isolates were enumerated and then sub-cultured on the medium from the parent culture at room temperature. Bacterial isolates were identified using biochemical analysis with the Vitek 2 system (bioM&#233;rieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France). Bacterial isolates that could not be identified by the Vitek 2 system were identified by 16S ribosomal DNA sequencing using a MicroSeq 500 16S rDNA Bacterial Identification Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Sequences were compared to those on the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) website for microorganisms. Speciation was reported for isolates having greater than 98% sequence similarity. Fungal isolates were identified by microscopic morphological characteristics <xref rid="pone.0028906-Castro1" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0028906-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Representative samples of normal and abnormal lesions on Ozark Hellbenders, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>.</title><p>All individuals sampled were captured from the North Fork of the White River, Ozark County, Missouri on 17 August 2007. A shows a normal left back foot (NFWR 138), B shows lesion on palm of right back foot (NFWR 136), C shows lesion on toes of left front foot (NFWR 136), D shows lesion on right back limb with all toes missing (NFWR 135), E shows lesion on right back limb with all toes missing (NFWR 139), and F shows lesion on lower lip (NFWR 139).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0028906-t006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0028906.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Ozark Hellbenders, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>, captured and swabbed for microbial flora from the North Fork of the White River, Ozark County, Missouri on 17 August 2007.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0028906-t006-6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0028906.t006.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample No.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL (cm)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVL (cm)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 134<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">1</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">559</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 135<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">2</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">610</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 136<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">3</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">569</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 137<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">4</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 138<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">5</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">971</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFWR 139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">6</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">545</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label>1</label><p>Two sample location (right back limb and right front limb) were swabbed.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>2</label><p>Four sample locations (all limbs) were swabbed.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>3</label><p>Three sample locations (right back limb, left back limb, and left front limb) were swabbed.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>4</label><p>Three sample locations (right back limb, right front limb, and left front limb) were swabbed.</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label>5</label><p>Two sample locations (left back limb and left front limb) were swabbed.</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label>6</label><p>Five sample locations (all limbs and lower lip) were swabbed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></body><back><ack><p>Research was conducted in compliance with applicable animal care guidelines. We also thank the Missouri Department of Conservation for permits to conduct this research. Dr. Lawrence M. Page kindly read and commented on the manuscript. Special thanks to L. Davis for assistance with graphics.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>V. M. Garcia and T. C. Molina are employees of EASI, Wyle Laboratories. There are no patents, products in development or marketed products to declare. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials, as detailed online in the guide for authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>NASA student grant NNX07AM16G, NASA grant NCC2-1362, The St. Louis Zoological Park, and The Reptile and Amphibian Conservation Corps. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0028906-Lannoo1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lannoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><source>Amphibian declines: The conservation status of United States species</source><publisher-loc>Berkley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name><size units="page">1094</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Halliday1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Diverse phenomena influencing amphibian population declines.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lannoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Amphibian declines: The conservation status of United States species</source><publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Beebee1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beebee</surname><given-names>TJC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The amphibian decline crisis: a watershed for conservation biology?</article-title><source>Biological Conservation</source><volume>125</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Anonymous1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anonymous</surname></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>Where have all the frogs gone?</article-title><source>Modern Medicine</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Gibbs1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nace</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>The live frog is almost dead.</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-National1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Academy of Sciences</collab><year>1974</year><source>Amphibians: guidelines for the breeding, care and management of lab animals</source><publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc><size units="page">162</size><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25032435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Maugh1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maugh</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>Frog shortage possible this winter.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>387</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17815359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.178.4059.387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-ReichenbachKlinke1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichenbach-Klinke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1965</year><article-title>Amphibia.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichenbach-Klinke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>The principle diseases of lower vertebrates</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>384</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Hutchison1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Comments on the distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Basidiobolus ranarum</italic>.</article-title><source>Mycologia</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5448287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>A study of the distribution of the fungus <italic toggle="yes">Basidiobolus ranarum</italic> Eidam in fish, amphibians and reptiles.</article-title><source>American Midland Naturalist</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>502</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson2"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>Mexican isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Basidobolus ranarum</italic> Eidam.</article-title><source>Southwestern Naturalist</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Tills1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tills</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>The distribution of the fungus, <italic toggle="yes">Basidobolus ranarum</italic> Eidam in fish, amphibians, and reptiles of the southern Appalachian Region of the United States.</article-title><source>Transactions Kansas Academy of Science</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Taylor1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Chapter 14: Mycoses.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Amphibian medicine and captive husbandry</source><publisher-loc>Malabar, Florida</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kreiger Publishing Company</publisher-name><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Daszak1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daszak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Infectious disease and amphibian population declines.</article-title><source>Diversity and Distribution</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Greenbaum1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusamba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aristote</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Amphibian chytrid fungus infections in <italic toggle="yes">Hyperolius</italic> (Anura: Hyperoliidae) from eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Reeves1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic> in wood frogs (<italic toggle="yes">Rana sylvatica</italic>) from three national wildlife refuges in Alaska, USA.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Woodhams1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodhams</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollins-Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The northern leopard frog <italic toggle="yes">Rana pipiens</italic> is a widespread reservoir species harboring <italic toggle="yes">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic> in North America.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Erspamer1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erspamer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Bioactive secretions of the amphibian integument.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heatwole</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barthalmus</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Amphibian biology volume 1: The integument</source><publisher-loc>Chipping Norton, NSW</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Surry Beatty and Sons</publisher-name><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>350</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Heatwole1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heatwole</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barthalmus</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><source>Amphibian biology volume 1: The integument</source><publisher-loc>Chipping Norton, NSW</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Surry Beatty and Sons</publisher-name><size units="page">418</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Csordas1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csordas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1969</year><article-title>Primary structure of two oligopeptides of the toxin of <italic toggle="yes">Bombina variegata</italic>.</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5823347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0041-0101(69)90072-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Croce1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giglioli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolognani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>Antimicrobial activity in the skin of <italic toggle="yes">Bombina variegata pachypus</italic>.</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4579863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0041-0101(73)90159-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Becker1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brucker</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwantes</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minbiole</surname><given-names>KPC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The bacterially-produced metabolite violacein is associated with survival in amphibians infected with a lethal disease.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>6635</fpage><lpage>6638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.01294-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2772424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Brucker1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brucker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The identification of 2,4-diacetylphloroglucinol as an antifungal metabolite produced by cutaneous bacteria of the salamander <italic toggle="yes">Plethodon cinereus</italic>.</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18058176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10886-007-9352-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Brucker2"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brucker</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwantes</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallaher</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Amphibian chemical defense: antifungal metabolites of the microsymbiont <italic toggle="yes">Janthinobacterium lividum</italic> on the salamander <italic toggle="yes">Plethodon cinereus</italic>.</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>1429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18949519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10886-008-9555-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Fedewa1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedewa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Inhibition of growth for select Gram-negative bacteria by tricaine methane sulfonate (MS-222).</article-title><source>Journal of Herpetological Medicine and Surgery</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Lauer1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banning</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Diversity of cutaneous bacteria with antifungal activity isolated from female four-toed salamanders.</article-title><source>The ISME Journal</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ismej.2007.110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Peterson1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year><source>Age and growth of the Ozark hellbender</source><publisher-loc>Springfield, Missouri</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Southwest Missouri State University</publisher-name><size units="page">52</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-RollinsSmith1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollins-Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptide defenses against chytridiomycosis, an emerging infectious disease of amphibian populations.</article-title><source>Dev Comp Immunol</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dci.2004.11.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Sheafor1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheafor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollins-Smith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptide defenses in the salamander, <italic toggle="yes">Ambystoma tigrinum</italic>, against emerging amphibian pathogens.</article-title><source>J Wildl Dis</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7589/0090-3558-44.2.226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Woodhams2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodhams</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vredenburg</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billheimer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhtour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Symbiotic bacteria contribute to innate immune defenses of the threatened mountain yellow-legged frog, <italic toggle="yes">Rana muscosa</italic>.</article-title><source>Biological Conservation</source><volume>138</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>398</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-RollinsSmith2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollins-Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doersam</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longcore</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamblin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptide defenses against pathogens associated with global amphibian declines.</article-title><source>Developmental &amp; Comparative Immunology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0145-305x(01)00041-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Simmaco1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmaco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mignogna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Antimicrobial peptides from amphibian skin: What do they tell us?</article-title><source>Peptide Science</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10333736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0282(1998)47:6&lt;435::AID-BIP3&gt;3.0.CO;2-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Lauer2"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banning</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Common cutaneous bacteria from the eastern red-backed salamander can inhibit pathological fungi.</article-title><source>Copeia</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>640</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Collins1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><source>Extinction in our times: Global amphibian declines</source><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><size units="page">273</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Blaustein1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaustein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wake</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Amphibian declines: judging stability, persistence, and susceptibility of populations to local and global extinctions.</article-title><source>Conservation Biology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson3"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>The hellbenders: North American &#8220;giant salamanders&#8221;.</article-title><source>Milwaukee Public Museum Publications in Biology and Geology</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson4"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>A study of the Ozark hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>.</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1165</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-OSEDA1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>OSEDA</collab><year>2011</year><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oseda.missouri.edu/historicdata/popsqmi/29153.htm">http://www.oseda.missouri.edu/historicdata/popsqmi/29153.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 2011 July 20</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson5"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prysby</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The effects of flooding on hellbender salamander, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic> Daudin, 1803, populations.</article-title><source>Salamandra</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Cooper1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><source>Food and feeding selectivity of two cottid species in an Ozark stream. Masters Thesis</source><publisher-loc>Jonesboro, Arkansas</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Arkansas State University</publisher-name><size units="page">45</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Hiler1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiler</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Abnormalities in the Ozark hellbender (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>) in Arkansas: A comparison between two rivers with a historical perspective.</article-title><source>Journal of the Arkansas Academy of Science</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson6"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Harvesting as a factor in population decline of a long-lived salamander, the Ozark hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic> Grobman.</article-title><source>Applied Herpetology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson7"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Decline of the Ozark hellbender (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>) in the North Fork of White River, Ozark County, Missouri: A historical perspective.</article-title><comment>Final report to the St. Louis Zoo and the Reptile and Amphibian Conservation Corps</comment><size units="page">53</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Yu1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Genomic diversity and molecular differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">Riemerella anatipestifer</italic> associated with eight outbreaks in five farms.</article-title><source>Avian Pathol</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03079450802056546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Siqueira1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#244;&#231;as</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Catonella morb</italic>i and <italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella adiacens</italic>: new species in endodontic infections.</article-title><source>Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, Oral Pathology, Oral Radiology, and Endodontics</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tripleo.2005.09.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16876072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Ma1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yam</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Kocuria kristinae</italic> infection associated with acute cholecystitis.</article-title><source>BMC Infectious Diseases</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16029488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2334-5-60</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1181815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Briggler1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utrup</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Hellbender population and habitat viability assessment: final report, IUCN/SSC Conservation Breeding Specialist Group.</article-title><comment>Apple Valley, Minnesota</comment><size units="page">46</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Wheeler1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Abnormalities in the Ozark hellbender.</article-title><source>Journal of the Arkansas Academy of Science</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Nickerson8"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krysko</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Habitat differences affecting age class distributions of the hellbender salamander, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic>.</article-title><source>Southeastern Naturalist</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>629</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Byram1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><source>Effects of nitrogen ammonia and MS-222 on <italic toggle="yes">Xenopus laevis</italic> development and foraging behavior. Masters Thesis</source><publisher-loc>Gainesville</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Florida</publisher-name><size units="page">49</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Byram2"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byram</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The use of Tricaine (MS-222) in amphibian conservation.</article-title><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><comment>Reptile and Amphibian Conservation Corps Occasional Papers in Reptile and Amphibian Conservation</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Gall1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Innate predator recognition and the problem of introduced trout.</article-title><source>Ethology</source><volume>116</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Trauth1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><source>The amphibians and reptiles of Arkansas</source><publisher-loc>Fayetteville</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Arkansas Press</publisher-name><size units="page">421</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Harshbarger1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harshbarger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Squamous cell carcinoma upgrade of the epidermal papilloma reported in an Ozark hellbender (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishop</italic>).</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinnell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Proceedings of the sixth international symposium on the pathology of reptiles and amphibians</source><publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Minnesota Printing Services</publisher-name><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Miller1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Prevalence of physical abnormalities in eastern Hellbender (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis alleganiensis</italic>) populations of middle Tennessee.</article-title><source>Southeastern Naturalist</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>520</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Pfingsten1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfingsten</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>The status and distribution of the hellbender, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic> in Ohio.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Smith1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1911</year><article-title>A case of defensive self-mutilation in <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus</italic>.</article-title><source>Bulletin of the Wisconsin Natural Society</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>65</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Trauth2"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauth</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harshbarger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Epidermal papilloma in an Ozark hellbender (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>) from the Spring River of northern Arkansas.</article-title><source>Journal of the Arkansas Academy of Science</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Briggler2"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ettling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic> (hellbender). Chytrid fungus.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>174</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Briggler3"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Presence of the amphibian chytrid fungus (<italic toggle="yes">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic>) on hellbenders (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic>) in the Ozark Highlands.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>444</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Bodinof1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodinof</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggler</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millspaugh</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Historic occurrence of the amphibian chytrid fungus <italic toggle="yes">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic> in hellbender <italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic> populations from Missouri.</article-title><source>Diseases of Aquatic Organisms</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21991660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3354/dao02380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-JuliaManresa1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Julia Manresa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gene Giralt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Ensenat</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Aeromonas hydrophila folliculitis associated with an inflatable swimming pool: mimicking <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infection.</article-title><source>Pediatr Dermatol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19840320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1525-1470.2009.00993.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Barribeau1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barribeau</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Major histocompatibility complex based resistance to a common bacterial pathogen of amphibians.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e2692</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18629002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0002692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2443284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-DelPozo1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Pozo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Quetglas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernaez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella adiacens</italic> breast implant-associated infection.</article-title><source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18206331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2007.12.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Denton1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Microbiological and clinical aspects of infection associated with <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9457429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/cmr.11.1.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC121376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Rumbaugh1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rumbaugh</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamood</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> strains obtained from patients with tracheal, urinary tract and wound infection: variations in virulence factors and virulence genes.</article-title><source>Journal of Hospital Infection</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10582188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/jhin.1999.0252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Lalucat1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalucat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennasar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Valdes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palleroni</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Biology of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>.</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MMBR.00047-05</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1489536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Valenstein1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardy</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwadyk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas alcaligenes</italic> endocarditis.</article-title><source>American Journal of Clinical Pathology</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6823910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajcp/79.2.245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-DeLucca1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Lucca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Harmful fungi in both agriculture and medicine.</article-title><source>Revista Iberoamericana Micrologia</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17592884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Gonalves1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#231;alves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>FISH and Calcofluor staining techniques to detect in situ filamentous fungal biofilms in water.</article-title><source>Revista Iberoamericana Micrologia</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1130-1406(06)70044-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Suihko1"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suihko</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alakomi</surname><given-names>H-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorbushina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortune</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Characterization of aerobic bacterial and fungal microbiota on surfaces of historic Scottish monuments.</article-title><source>Systematic and Applied Microbiology</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17583461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.syapm.2007.05.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Sun1"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szczotka-Flynn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghannoum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>A murine model of contact lens-associated <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> keratitis.</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19875664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.09-4237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2868423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Burmlle1"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burm&#248;lle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Enhanced biofilm formation and increased resistance to antimicrobial agents and bacterial invasion are caused by synergistic interactions in multispecies biofilms.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>3916</fpage><lpage>3923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16751497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.03022-05</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1489630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Kimber1"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kollias</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Infectious and parasitic diseases and contaminant-related problems of North American river otter (<italic toggle="yes">Lontra canadensis</italic>): a review.</article-title><source>Journal of Zoo and Wildlife Medicine</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11428392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1638/1042-7260(2000)031[0452:IAPDAC]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Low1"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Problems provide measure of otter program's success.</article-title><comment>Missouri Department of Conservation, Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mdc.state.mo.us/news/out/1996/out04196.html#problems%20provide">http://www.mdc.state.mo.us/news/out/1996/out04196.html#problems%20provide</ext-link>. Accessed 2004 October 20</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Missouri1"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Missouri Department of Conservation Trout Plan Committee</collab><year>2003</year><source>A plan for Missouri trout fishing</source><publisher-loc>Jefferson City</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Missouri Department of Conservation</publisher-name><size units="page">34</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Scadding1"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scadding</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Phylogenic distribution of limb regeneration capacity in adult amphibia.</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Zoology</source><volume>202</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Schauble1"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schauble</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>Seasonal variation of newt forelimb regeneration under controlled environmental conditions.</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Zoology</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5047367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jez.1401810215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Young1"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalley</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Environmental conditions prerequisite for complete limb regeneration in the postmetamorphic adult land-phase salamander, <italic toggle="yes">Ambystoma</italic>.</article-title><source>Anat Rec</source><volume>206</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6614511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ar.1092060307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Solis1"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solis</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niyogi</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandeff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Occurrence of organic chemicals in two rivers inhabited by Ozark hellbenders (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis bishopi</italic>).</article-title><source>Arch Environ Contam Toxicol</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00244-006-0208-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Quinlan1"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phlips</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Preliminary investigation of periphyton in the North Fork branch of the White River, Missouri.</article-title><comment>St. Louis Zoological Park and the Reptile and Amphibian Conservation Corps Report</comment><size units="page">7</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Solis2"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solis</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandeff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Hematology and serum chemistry of Ozark and eastern hellbenders (<italic toggle="yes">Cryptobranchus alleganiensis</italic>).</article-title><source>Herpetologica</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Communicable1"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Communicable Disease Center: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab><year>2011</year><article-title>Harmful algal blooms.</article-title><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/hab/cyanobacteria/facts.htm#cynolabs">http://www.cdc.gov/hab/cyanobacteria/facts.htm#cynolabs</ext-link>. Accessed 2001 May 13</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Cattaneo1"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Periphyton in lakes of different trophy.</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>303</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Chetelat1"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Periphyton biomass and community composition in rivers of different nutrient status.</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>569</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Caramujo1"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caramujo</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartaxana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brotas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boavida</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Influence of drought on algal biofilms and meiofaunal assemblages of temperate reservoirs and rivers.</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><volume>598</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Englebert1"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Englebert</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinheinz</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Effects of the nuisance algae, Cladophora, on <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> at recreational beaches in Wisconsin.</article-title><source>Science of The Total Environment</source><volume>404</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18639919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.05.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Whitman1"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawlik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevers</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byappanahalli</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and enterococci in <italic toggle="yes">Cladophora</italic> (Chlorophyta) in nearshore water and beach sand of Lake Michigan.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>4714</fpage><lpage>4719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12902262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.69.8.4714-4719.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC169104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Pitt1"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Coliform bacterial content of the North Fork of White River, Ozark County, Missouri.</article-title><comment>St. Louis Zoological Gardens and Reptile and Amphibian Conservation Corps Report</comment><size units="page">12</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0028906-Castro1"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trasher</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Microbial characterization during the early habitation of the International Space Station.</article-title><source>Microbial Ecology</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00248-003-1030-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>