<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">750</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4321547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4321547.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4321547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4321547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25403917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru444</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Natural variation in the expression of <italic toggle="yes">ORGANIC CATION TRANSPORTER 1</italic> affects root length responses to cadaverine in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohm</surname><given-names initials="AK">Allison K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names initials="LM">Laura M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names initials="PH">Patrick H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><institution>Laboratory of Genetics, University of Wisconsin Madison</institution>, <addr-line>425G Henry Mall, Madison, WI 53706</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c2">* These authors contributed equally to this work.</corresp><corresp id="c1"><sup>&#8224;</sup> To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>phmasson@wisc.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>66</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">249105</issue-id><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-06 01:25:16.887"><day>06</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="eru444.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><title>Highlight</title><p>How the polyamine cadaverine alters plant development is poorly understood. Here it is shown that natural variation in <italic toggle="yes">ORGANIC CATION TRANSPORTER 1</italic> affects root length sensitivity to exogenous cadaverine.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Polyamines, including cadaverine, are organic cations that affect numerous biological processes including transcription, translation, cell signalling, and ion channel activity. They often function in biotic and abiotic stress responses in plants. Because little is known about how plants respond to cadaverine, a quantitative natural variation approach was used to identify genetic factors that contribute to this response. Here it is shown that <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> accessions have varying root length responses to exogenous cadaverine: Cape Verde Islands (Cvi) was one of the most resistant accessions tested, whereas Landsberg <italic toggle="yes">erecta</italic> (L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>) was one of the most sensitive. Recombinant inbred lines, near isogenic lines, and a microarray were used to show that variation in <italic toggle="yes">ORGANIC CATION TRANSPORTER 1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>) is at least partially responsible for this difference. <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression was higher in Cvi than in L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">oct1</italic> mutants were more sensitive to cadaverine than wild-type plants. In <italic toggle="yes">oct1</italic> mutants transformed with an ectopic copy of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> originating from either Cvi or L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>, the expression level of the transgene, not its accession, correlated with the cadaverine response. These results suggest that decreased <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression confers cadaverine sensitivity in some accessions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic></kwd><kwd>cadaverine</kwd><kwd>natural variation</kwd><kwd>polyamines</kwd><kwd>roots</kwd><kwd>transporter.</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Polyamines are organic cations that are prevalent in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes. Putrescine, spermidine, and spermine are the most common polyamines in plants, although thermospermine and cadaverine have also been found in many species including <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Shevyakova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Knott <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Polyamines exist both as free molecules and as conjugates to other small molecules, mainly hydroxycinnamic acids, or proteins (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Bagni and Tassoni, 2001</xref>). Both free and conjugated polyamines are important for cellular processes including cell growth, cell division, transcription, translation, and cell death. Their positive charges allow for interactions with nucleic acids, lipids, and proteins, which affect the activities and stabilities of these molecules (for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Hussain <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Polyamines accumulate in certain plant tissues under many abiotic stresses including drought, salt, osmotic, and temperature stress, which all result in metabolic reprogramming and modifications to growth (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Cuevas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Alet <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Polyamines may protect against these stresses in several ways, including by altering gene expression, increasing the activities of antioxidant enzymes, and altering the cellular accumulation of ions (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Takahashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Tang and Newton, 2005</xref>). They may also function as signals that regulate cross-talk between hormonal pathways during stress responses (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Obata and Fernie, 2012</xref>). Though essential for proper development, and beneficial at higher levels during stress, catabolism of polyamines produces H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Tisi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Although it is toxic, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> also diffuses to nearby tissues where it activates various responses (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Neill, 2002</xref>). To balance these effects, polyamine synthesis, degradation, localization, and conjugation must be tightly controlled.</p><p content-type="indent">Five potential <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> POLYAMINE UPTAKE TRANSPORTER (PUT) proteins were identified based on sequence similarity to known polyamine transporters in <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania major</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trympanosoma cruzi</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Mulangi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>
</xref>). When expressed in the polyamine uptake-deficient <italic toggle="yes">&#916;agp2 Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> mutant (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Aouida <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), these proteins partially restored sensitivity to the polyamine analogue paraquat as well as to putrescine and spermidine. They also partially restored putrescine and spermidine uptake into the cells (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Mulangi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>
</xref>). PAR1/PUT2 has subsequently been shown to localize to the Golgi where it is required for the subcellular localization of paraquat in the chloroplast (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">RMV1</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">PUT3</italic> has been shown to be plasma membrane associated and to function in paraquat, putrescine, spermidine, and spermine uptake in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Fujita <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). However, cadaverine transport by these proteins was not tested.</p><p content-type="indent">Less is known about cadaverine compared with the other polyamines. It is synthesized from lysine and therefore not directly derived from the polyamine putrescine, unlike spermidine, spermine, and thermospermine. Cadaverine is produced by some soil bacteria and yeast, possibly contributing to rhizosphere&#8211;root signalling (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Perrig <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Cloete <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Exogenous cadaverine affects root development in several ways: it increases adventitious root growth in pine trees, lateral root formation in soybeans, and root weight in rice (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Gamarnik and Frydman, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Niemi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cass&#225;n <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), whereas it shortens primary roots in soybeans (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Gamarnik and Frydman, 1991</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Cadaverine levels and localization change upon exposure to stress. This molecule accumulates dramatically upon oxidative stress in rape leaves and upon drought stress in peppers (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Aziz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Sziderics <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In the ice plant, salt stress causes cadaverine to accumulate in true leaves (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Kuznetsov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), and heat shock stimulates cadaverine transport away from the heated tissue (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Shevyakova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Cadaverine also confers protection against stress. It induces stomatal closure, a common stress response, in fava beans (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), and it prevents decreases in root and shoot weight upon oxidative stress in rice (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cass&#225;n <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Despite its profound impacts on overall cellular homeostasis and plant growth under stressful conditions, the underlying mechanisms that explain how cadaverine alters plant growth and development are still unknown. To address this gap, natural variation in root length sensitivity to exogenous cadaverine was examined, and <italic toggle="yes">ORGANIC CATION TRANSPORTER 1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">AT1G73220</italic>) was identified as an important quantitative trait locus (QTL) involved in this response.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Plant materials</title><p>QTL analysis used the following stocks from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (Columbus, OH, USA): Cape Verde Islands (Cvi; CS8580), Landsberg <italic toggle="yes">erecta</italic>-2 L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>-2; CS8581), and a population of Cvi/L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> recombinant inbred lines (RILs; CS22000). This population consists of 162 individual RILs that were genotyped at 293 marker loci (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Blanco <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). The near isogenic lines (NILs) LCN1-12, -15, -14, -21, -22, and -28 (N717058, N17060, N17061, N17067, N17068, and N17074) (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Keurentjes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) were obtained from the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Center (Nottingham, UK). An-1 (CS22626), Bs-1 (CS6627), Knox-18 (CS22567), Sq-8 (CS22601), Ull2-3 (CS22587), and Wei-0 (CS22622) seed came from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center. The <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutant and <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> [35S<sub>pro</sub>:OCT1<sup>WS</sup>] transgenic lines were provided by Christine Lelandais-Briere (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lelandais-Bri&#232;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Growth conditions</title><p>The seeds were sterilized by washing them with 95% ethanol. Except where noted in the text, they were plated on half-strength buffered Linsmaier and Skoog medium containing micro- and macronutrients, vitamins, and 1.5% sucrose (Caisson Laboratories, North Logan, UT, USA) that was supplemented with 1.5% agar type E (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and polyamines (Sigma-Aldrich) as required. The seedlings were stratified for 2&#8211;8 d and grown in either a Conviron TC16 growth chamber or an Enconair (now BioChambers, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada) Controller 6000 growth chamber for each experiment. Both chambers were set at 22 &#176;C and a 16h light/8h dark cycle, and the light intensity was 50&#8211;70 &#956;mol m<sup>&#8211;2</sup> s<sup>&#8211;1</sup> and provided by cool-white fluorescent bulbs (Grainger, Lake Forest, IL, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Root length measurements</title><p>Seedling images were taken from the backs of the plates using a scanner (Epson, Suwa, Nagano Prefecture, Japan). Root length was measured using the segmented line tool in NIH Image (publically available at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/</uri>) or the Neuron J plugin (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Meijering <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>) for Image J (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Schneider <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Microscopy</title><p>To calculate cell length, the cell walls were stained by transferring the seedlings to 10 &#956;g ml<sup>&#8211;1</sup> propidium iodide (Sigma-Aldrich) for ~20min. Imaging was conducted using a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta Confocal microscope (Zeiss, Thornwood, NY, USA), and cell length measurements were performed in Adobe Photoshop.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>QTL mapping</title><p>Plants were grown at a 30 &#176; tilt for 6 d on media with or without cadaverine. A concentration of 50 &#956;M cadaverine was used in trial 1, and 100 &#956;M cadaverine was used in trial 2. The mean root length value on medium containing cadaverine was subtracted from the mean value on control medium and then divided by the mean on control medium. This number was subtracted from 1, and this ratio, along with genotypic data for each RIL (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Blanco <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), was entered into WinQTL Cartographer version 2.5 (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) and the r/qtl package in R (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</uri>). For WinQTL Cartographer, maps were created using the Kosambi map function. During composite interval mapping, the model incorporated a 0.5 step rate with a 1.0 cM window size and 10 control markers. LOD thresholds were determined by 1000 permutations. In r/qtl, the function &#8216;scanone&#8217; was used for interval mapping, and &#8216;scantwo&#8217; was used to generate the two-dimensional plot. Significance levels were determined by 1000 permutations, implementing the EM algorithm. Fine mapping of the NILs was performed using standard methods and the primers listed in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RT&#8211;PCR and qRT-PCR</title><p>Approximately 24 seedlings were grown at a 30 &#176; backward tilt at staggered times for each biological replicate on medium containing no cadaverine unless otherwise indicated. Whole roots from 7-day-old seedlings were dissected and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. RNA was prepared using an RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Venlo, The Netherlands) and stored at &#8211;80 &#186;C until use, typically within a few days. RNA samples were treated with RQ1 DNase (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) according to the instructions. The ratios at absorbencies of 260 to 280 and at 260 to 230 as well as gel electrophoresis were used to verify RNA quality. Poor quality samples were not used for subsequent experiments. RNA concentrations were determined using a NanoDrop 2000 (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA).</p><p content-type="indent">For reverse transcription&#8211;PCR (RT&#8211;PCR), cDNA was made using the iScript&#8482; cDNA Synthesis Kit (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). For quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR), cDNA synthesis and qRT&#8211;PCR were done simultaneously using a qScript&#8482; One-Step qRT-PCR Kit (Quanta Biosciences, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). The samples were run on a LightCycler<sup>&#174;</sup> 480 Real Time-PCR System (Roche Applied Science, Basel, Switzerland). Each 6 &#956;l reaction contained RNA at a final concentration of 2ng &#956;l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> and each primer at a concentration of 0.65 &#956;M. Other components were included at the concentrations defined by the kit. Control reactions without reverse transcriptase were included and did not yield any detectable expression. Cycling conditions were 49 &#186;C for 10min, 95 &#186;C for 5min, and 45 cycles of 95 &#186;C for 5 s, 55 &#186;C for 15 s, and 72 &#186;C for 10 s. Melt curves were used to verify specificity. Four technical replicates were performed for each sample for each biological replicate, and three biological replicates were performed. LinRegPCR was used to analyse the data (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Ramakers <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">The primers used to amplify <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> were: 1F (5&#8242; GTGGCTGTT CCTTCCACACT 3&#8242;), 1R (5&#8242; AAAGGCCGTGACGAAAGTTA 3&#8242;), 2F (5&#8242; CATCCTCGACAGCGTATGAC 3&#8242;), 2R (5&#8242; CCTTC CTAACGCAACTAGCA 3&#8242;), 3F (5&#8242; TTTGGTGTTGCATCAGTG CT 3&#8242;), and 3R (5&#8242; CGGAGCGTTTCGAGTTTCT 3&#8242;). 4R (5&#8242; CGTGAAATGCGTGTTGAAAG 3&#8242;) was used to detect possible transcript that extended into the T-DNA region. Primers 3F and 3R as well as 5&#8242; CCTCTTGGATACGCGGTTT 3&#8242; and 5&#8242; CAAGA AGCCATCGAGGAGAC 3&#8242; were used for <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> qRT&#8211;PCR. Primers used to amplify the reference gene At1g58050 (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Czechowski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) were: 5&#8242; CCATTCTACTTTTTGGCGGCT 3&#8242; and 5&#8242; TCAATGGTAACTGATCCACTCTGATG 3&#8242;. This reference gene was chosen due to its consistent expression and its similar expression level to <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Czechowski <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>)</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Transgenic constructs</title><p>Genomic DNA from Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> was used to amplify the region extending from 2079 bases before the start codon through to 417 bases after the stop codon of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>. This region was cloned in between the attL1 and attL2 sites in the Gateway entry vector pENTR/D-TOPO (Life Technologies, Madison, WI, USA). An LR reaction was performed to transfer this region into the binary vector pMDC99 (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Curtis and Grossniklaus, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Xu and Li, 2008</xref>). The constructs were sequenced and transformed into plants using the <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated floral dip method (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>). T<sub>3</sub> seedlings likely to all carry the transgene as determined by antibiotic resistance were used in all experiments (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Harrison <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Results</title><sec id="s11"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> accessions vary in their root length responses to cadaverine</title><p>As a first step toward identifying genes involved in root growth responses to exogenous cadaverine, seedlings of eight <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> accessions were grown on media containing 0, 100, and 500 &#956;M cadaverine. A decrease in root length between control and increasing cadaverine treatments was observed for all accessions tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Alterations in root waving and skewing and an increase in adventitious and lateral root emergence were also noticed in most accessions (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). In terms of root length, Cvi-1 and Knox-18 were some of the most resistant accessions to cadaverine, whereas L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>-2 was one of the most sensitive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">B</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> accessions show varying root length inhibition responses to exogenous cadaverine. (A) Seedlings were grown vertically for 3 d and then at a 30 &#176; backward tilt for another 3 d. Average root length on control medium was set to 1. Absolute average root lengths on control medium were 1.4, 1.6, 2.5, 2.1, 2.1, 2.3, 2.0, and 2.3cm in the accessions as shown from left to right. The asterisk indicates the first cadaverine concentration corresponding to a significantly shorter root compared with control medium (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test). Error bars indicate &#177;SE, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=12&#8211;27. (B) Images of Cvi-1 (top) and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>-2 (bottom) seedlings growing on media without (left) and with (right) 100 &#956;M cadaverine. The white scale bar is 1cm. (C) Average length of epidermal cells in the mature root zone from seedlings grown vertically for 7 d on either control medium or medium containing 100 &#956;M cadaverine. Error bars indicate &#177;SE, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=11&#8211;18.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0001.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">To determine whether the effect of cadaverine on root length was due to reduced cell elongation or division, the length of the epidermal cells in the mature root zone of L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> seedlings grown on media containing 0 &#956;M or 100 &#956;M cadaverine was measured. It was found that although L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> roots were only ~35% as long on this concentration of cadaverine as on control medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), the average cell length of the seedlings on the medium containing cadaverine was ~64% of that of seedlings on control medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). This suggests that the reduction in root length is probably due to a combination of reduced cell elongation and division.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>A QTL on chromosome 1 affects root length responses to cadaverine</title><p>Due to the large difference between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> in root growth responses to exogenous cadaverine, a QTL study was performed with a group of RILs created from the two accessions. Other pairs of accessions would have been equally interesting to use for QTL analysis but, at the time this experiment was initiated, the Cvi&#215;L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> population was the available population created from accessions with the most differing cadaverine responses. These RILs were previously characterized for genotypic contribution from the two parental lines along the five chromosomes (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Blanco <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). For both the parental lines and the RILs, root growth on medium containing cadaverine compared with growth on control plates lacking this compound was quantified. RIL mean root length ratios showed transgression with respect to the parental means (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Furthermore, growth on 0 &#956;M and 50 &#956;M cadaverine displayed broad sense heritability values of 0.46 and 0.56, respectively. Taken together, these results indicate that this population is well suited for QTL mapping of root growth responses to exogenous cadaverine.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>QTL analysis of root length responses to cadaverine in the Cvi/L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> RIL population. (A) Histogram showing root length ratios for the RILs on 100 &#956;M cadaverine compared with control medium. (B) Composite interval mapping analysis for the root length ratio. The top portion of the graph gives the LOD score across each chromosome. The LOD significance threshold is shown as a horizontal line across the graph. The bottom graph shows the additive value toward the phenotype of each genomic region with respect to the L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> allele. (C) Two-dimensional QTL scan for the root length ratio from trial 1. The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axes represent positions along each chromosome. The region of the plot below the diagonal gives the additive QTL model, while the region above the diagonal shows epistatic interactions. A scale relating colour to LOD score is provided on the right of the heat map. Numbers on the left of this scale represent LOD scores for the epistatic portion of the plot, whereas those on the right represent scores for the additive model. The arrows indicate the significance thresholds for the epistatic (left) and additive (right) portions of the plot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0002.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">Using both composite interval mapping and a 2D scan approach, a strong QTL for relative root growth response to cadaverine was identified at the end of chromosome 1 in two independent trials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The additive portion of the QTL graph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>, bottom) predicts that having a L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> allele at this location results in a shorter root upon cadaverine treatment compared with a Cvi allele. No epistasis was observed between this QTL and other parts of the genome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Near isogenic lines confirm the chromosome 1 QTL</title><p>Six NILs with Cvi introgression of varying segments of chromosome 1 within an otherwise L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> background (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Keurentjes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) were used to confirm the root length QTL. The four LCN1 lines that contain a Cvi introgression at the end of chromosome 1 showed greater, more Cvi-like resistance to cadaverine than LCN1-12 and LCN1-22, the NILs that do not contain a Cvi introgression in this region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> to Cvi breakpoints in these lines were fine-mapped, and the candidate region was narrowed to a 5.3Mb interval at the end of chromosome 1 (primers shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Cadaverine root length responses of chromosome 1 NILs and fine mapping. Relative root lengths on media containing 0, 100, and 500 &#956;M cadaverine are shown. Plants were grown at a 30 &#176; backward tilt for 6 d. The average root length on control medium was set to 1. Absolute average root lengths on control medium were 1.0, 1.2, 1.2, 1.2, 1.1, 1.2, 1.1, and 1.1cm in the lines as shown from left to right. The asterisk indicates the first concentration on which the root length was significantly different from the length on control medium (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test). Error bars indicate &#177;SE, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=18&#8211;34. In the diagram of chromosome 1 NILs (bottom), white bars are L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> chromosomal regions, black bars are Cvi regions, and grey bars indicate regions in which the breakpoint is undetermined. The parallel dashed lines flank the probable region of a locus controlling root length responses to cadaverine. Accession breakpoints were determined using primers based on polymorphisms described by Monsanto/CEREON between Columbia and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Jander <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Identification of candidate genes for the chromosome 1 QTL</title><p>Because many of the causative loci behind the QTL are due to differences in gene expression (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Blanco <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), gene expression differences between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> were examined in the candidate region using previously published microarray data (<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Vaughn and Masson, 2011</xref>). The primary data are publicly available at Gene Expression Omnibus (NCBI; accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE28275">GSE28275</ext-link>). From these arrays, 19 probe sets representing genes located in the candidate chromosomal segment give hybridization signals that differ significantly (95% confidence interval) by &#8805;2-fold between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The largest predicted differentially expressed gene in this region was <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>, which was estimated to show a 73-fold increase in Cvi compared with L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Probe sets on chromosome 1 between 25.3Mb and 30.6Mb that show &#8805;2-fold differential expression between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> at the 95% confidence level</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe set ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> over Cvi fold change</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Log<sub>2</sub> expression level</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cvi</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260097_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G73220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic cation transporter (OCT1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264100_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G78970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lupeol synthase (LUP1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245215_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G67830</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;-Fucosidase (FXG1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245736_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G73330</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protease inhibitor (DR4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259941_s_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G71280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEAD/DEAH box helicase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260806_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G78260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260401_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G69840</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264144_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G79320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 down</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metacaspase (MC6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259705_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G77450</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC transcription factor (NAC032)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259977_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G76590</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261901_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G80920</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-J protein (J8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260411_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G69890</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264957_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G77000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-box protein (SKP2B)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">262362_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G72840</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP-binding transmembrane receptor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260207_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G70730</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphoglucomutase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245731_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G73500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP kinase kinase (MKK9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260101_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G73260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trypsin protease inhibitor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259866_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G76640</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calmodulin-related protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264720_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G70080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene synthase</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn0001" fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: NIL, near isogenic line; OCT, organic cation transporter; RIL, recombinant inbred line.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p content-type="indent">No other genes in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> encode proteins that are directly relevant to polyamine metabolism or transport. Genes encoding a transglutaminase (<italic toggle="yes">At1g69820</italic>) and a cinnamyl alcohol dehydrogenase (<italic toggle="yes">At1g72680</italic>), both possibly linked to the formation of polyamine conjugates (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Serafini-Fracassini and Del Duca, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Fellenberg <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), are found in this QTL interval; however, they do not show &#8805;2-fold expression differences between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>.</p><p content-type="indent">
<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> from Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> genomic DNA was sequenced. No large insertions or deletions were found, and only one amino acid change was found: residue 431 in the second exon is serine in Cvi and alanine in L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). Analysing the 2kb of sequence upstream of the start codon revealed numerous single nucleotide polymorphisms and small insertions but no large insertions or deletions (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Based on these data, it was hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression differences contribute to root length responses to exogenous cadaverine. qRT-PCR data confirmed the microarray result and showed that <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression was ~14 times as high in Cvi roots as in L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Cadaverine treatment did not significantly change <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression in either accession (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>
<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression relative to the reference gene <italic toggle="yes">At1G58050</italic> is higher in Cvi roots than in L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> roots. Seedlings were grown on 0 &#956;M or 50 &#956;M cadaverine. Error bars indicate &#177;SE among biological replicates, and <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression for L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> on control medium was set to 1. The asterisk indicates a significant difference in expression compared with L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> for the given condition (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test). Differences within each accession between cadaverine treatments are not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutants express a truncated <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> transcript</title><p>To evaluate a role for <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> in root length responses to cadaverine, the <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutant, which was previously found to carry a single T-DNA insertion near the 3&#8217; end of the gene, was obtained; both ends of the insertion were characterized (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lelandais-Bri&#232;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). This mutant was also reported to not express any <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> RNA, as determined by RT&#8211;PCR using primers aligning on each side of the intron (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lelandais-Bri&#232;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). To confirm this result, RT&#8211;PCR was performed on <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> and (Wassilewskija) WS wild-type root RNA samples. As expected, PCR products were obtained from WS wild-type cDNA samples of the expected sizes using multiple primer sets (1F/1R, 2F/2R, and 3F/3R) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). Also, no transcript was observed for <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutants using primer sets near the 3&#8242; end of the gene (2F/2R, 3F/3R, and 2F/4R) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>).</p><p content-type="indent">However, it was found that <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> plants do express a partial <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> transcript using primers on each side of the intron (1F/1R) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). This product size corresponds to approximately the predicted length if the intron is not spliced out of the RNA (238 bases instead of 135 bases), which would result in a premature stop codon in the intron. No product for any primer set was detected in control reactions without reverse transcriptase, which confirms the lack of genomic DNA contamination (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>). Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> produces a truncated <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> transcript that is highly unlikely to encode a functional protein.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> shows increased cadaverine sensitivity</title><p>If L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> roots have higher sensitivity to cadaverine compared with Cvi roots because they have lower <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression, then <italic toggle="yes">oct1</italic> mutant roots should also respond more strongly to cadaverine than wild-type plants. To test this, WS wild type, <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic>, and two independent transgenic rescue lines (<italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> [35S<sub>pro</sub>:OCT1<sup>WS</sup>]) were grown on control medium and medium supplemented with cadaverine. Rescue line 1 had significantly higher <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression compared with the WS wild type, whereas rescue line 2 had a similar level of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). It was found that all of these plants had the same root length on control medium lacking cadaverine, but <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutant roots were significantly shorter than wild-type roots on media containing 50 &#956;M and 500 &#956;M cadaverine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). Robust root growth on medium containing cadaverine was restored in both independent transgenic rescue lines. Rescue line 2 showed a wild-type-like response to cadaverine, and rescue line 1 showed increased resistance to cadaverine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). These results suggest that reduced <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression confers increased cadaverine sensitivity.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>
<italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> roots are more sensitive to exogenous cadaverine compared with wild-type plants but respond similarly to putrescine-derived polyamines. (A) <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression relative to the reference gene <italic toggle="yes">At1G58050</italic> is shown. Error bars indicate &#177;SE among biological replicates, and <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression for the WS wild type on control medium was set to 1. The asterisk indicates a significant difference in expression compared with the WS wild type (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test). The abbreviation n.d. indicates that expression was not detected. (B) Plants were grown for 6 d at a 30 &#176; backward tilt on media containing 0, 50, and 500 &#956;M cadaverine. Root tips were marked after 3 d of growth, and the root growth over the following 3 d was measured for each treatment. Average root growth over the final 3 d on control medium was 1.2cm for the wild type, 1.4cm for <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic>, 1.3cm for rescue line 1, and 1.4cm for rescue line 2; these lengths were set to 1. For each cadaverine concentration, the letters indicate significant differences in relative root length (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01, pairwise Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests). <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=37&#8211;68, and error bars indicate &#177;SE. (C) Plants were grown for 6 d at a 30 &#176; backward tilt on media containing various concentrations of polyamines as indicated. Average root length on control medium was 1.3cm for the wild type and 1.4cm for oct1-1; these lengths were set to 1. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=33&#8211;44, and error bars indicate &#177;SE. No significant root length differences were observed for any treatment other than cadaverine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0005.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">The WS wild type and <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> had similar root lengths on media containing the polyamines putrescine, spermidine, and spermine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>), which shows that this sensitivity is specific to cadaverine. Polyamines have been shown to shorten root growth through the generation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> by diamine and polyamine oxidases, which promotes premature cell differentiation and programmed cell death (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Tisi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). However, because the cadaverine-hypersensitive response of <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> was specific to cadaverine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>), OCT1 probably functions in a different aspect of polyamine-mediated root growth regulation.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>The expression level of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>, not its accession origin, correlates with cadaverine sensitivity</title><p>To determine if differences in the <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> sequence between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> or only <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression levels correlated with the cadaverine response, <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> was cloned from Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>, and these constructs were introduced into <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutants. These transgenic lines were then tested on media containing 0 &#956;M and 50 &#956;M cadaverine, and their relative root lengths were measured. A range of cadaverine resistance levels that did not correlate with the accession source of the transgene was found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Higher <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression correlates with cadaverine resistance. OCT1<sup>Cvi</sup> and OCT1<sup>L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic></sup> indicate <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> [OCT1<sub>pro</sub>:OCT1<sup>Cvi</sup>] and <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> [OCT1<sub>pro</sub>:OCT1<sup>L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic></sup>], respectively. (A) Relative root lengths of plants on media containing 0 &#956;M and 50 &#956;M cadaverine. Plants were grown for 6 d at a 30 &#176; backward tilt. Average root length on control medium was set to 1. Absolute average root length on control medium was 2.2cm for Cvi, 1.9cm for L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>, 2.0cm for WS, 2.0cm for <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic>, and 1.9, 2.0, 1.7, and 2.1cm for the transgenic lines as shown from left to right. Error bars indicate &#177;SE, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=17&#8211;24. (B) Root <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression determined by qRT-PCR is shown relative to the reference gene <italic toggle="yes">At1G58050</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression in L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> was set to 1. Error bars indicate &#177;SE among the biological replicates. The abbreviation n.d. indicates that expression was not detected.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_eru444_f0006.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">Because the insertion location can affect transgene expression, it was predicted that the <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression levels would correlate with cadaverine sensitivity. To test this, <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression was measured in four of these lines by qRT-PCR. As expected, a range of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression levels was found in the transgenic lines regardless of whether the <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> untranslated and coding regions came from Cvi or L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>. In general, lines with increased resistance to cadaverine had higher <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Genes other than <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> probably also contribute to the cadaverine response</title><p>The data suggest that differences in <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression contribute significantly to the different cadaverine root length responses in Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>. To determine if differences in <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression among other natural accessions also correlate with variability in cadaverine sensitivity, <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression was measured in two other accessions, one resistant to cadaverine (Knox-18) and one sensitive to cadaverine (Sq-8). It was found that both lines had higher <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression than L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> even though only Knox-18 was more resistant to cadaverine than L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>. Furthermore, Sq-8 displayed higher <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression than Knox-18 despite being more sensitive to cadaverine (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). The <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> sequences of the eight natural accessions initially selected for the analysis of cadaverine response were also compared. Polymorphisms shared among the three most resistant accessions (Cvi-1, Knox-18, and Ull2-3) or the three most sensitive accessions (An-1, L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>-2, and Sq-8) were not seen (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Together, these data suggest that factors other than <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression may also contribute significantly to differential cadaverine sensitivity among these accessions.</p><p content-type="indent">Ectopic copies of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> derived from Cvi or L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> were also introduced into Columbia and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> wild-type plants. L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> root length is highly sensitive to cadaverine, whereas Columbia root length is less sensitive to it. In general, the Columbia plants showed a range of responses to cadaverine regardless of the accession from which the transgene was derived (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S4</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). This result is similar to that obtained when these constructs were transformed into the <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). In contrast, when these constructs were transformed into L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> plants, the tested lines generally did not show increased resistance to cadaverine (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S4</ext-link>). Therefore, the ability of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> to affect the cadaverine response may depend on the genetic background.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Discussion</title><p>It was found that <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> roots exhibited varying responses to exogenously applied cadaverine depending on the accession. In general, when cadaverine concentrations increased, a reduction in root length as well as alterations in skewing, lateral root branching, and root waving were seen. The reduction in root length is probably due to a combination of reduced cell division and expansion. A major QTL was identified on chromosome 1 that at least partially explains the root length difference in response to cadaverine between Cvi and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>. By comparing phenotypes and gene expression in natural accessions, a mutant, and transgenic lines, <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> was identified as a key gene involved in this response. Restoring <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression in the mutant background resulted in a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression levels and cadaverine resistance. Because the <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression levels in other natural accessions do not correlate well with cadaverine resistance, other genes are also likely to contribute to the variation of this trait between <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> accessions. These genes could contribute to endogenous cadaverine homeostasis, transport, and/or response. Unfortunately, the levels of endogenous cadaverine in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> seedling roots and shoots were below the level of detection using HPLC methods, preventing a distinction from being made between these possibilities.</p><p content-type="indent">OCT1 encodes an organic cation transporter. In animals, OCT proteins take up a wide variety of endogenous compounds and xenobiotics, and, therefore, they affect substrate absorption, distribution, and excretion in many tissues. Most are polyspecific, and transport can occur in either direction (for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Roth <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> OCT1 is one of six OCT-like proteins in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lelandais-Bri&#232;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). It was previously reported to localize to the plasma membrane, and promoter&#8211;&#946;-glucuronidase (GUS) fusions showed activity in the vasculature of many organs including roots (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lelandais-Bri&#232;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">K&#252;fner and Koch, 2008</xref>). Because the other six OCT-like proteins localize to the tonoplast rather than the plasma membrane, it is likely that OCT1 has a different function.</p><p content-type="indent">The present work expands on these studies and suggests a role for OCT1 in affecting root growth responses to cadaverine. Future experiments will be aimed at clarifying the mechanism by which this occurs. One possibility is that OCT1 transports cadaverine away from elongating root cells and through the vasculature, causing it to accumulate in aerial tissues. Alternatively, cadaverine may alter the transport of another molecule through the membranes. Polyamines block many kinds of channels in multiple organisms. For example, spermine and spermidine directly block fast vacuolar cation channels in barley (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bruggemann <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), and all natural polyamines including cadaverine can regulate cation channel activity through cytoplasmic pathways (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Shabala <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">It has been demonstrated that exogenous cadaverine affects <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> root morphology and that there is natural variation in this response due in part to varying expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic>. This work has potential implications for better understanding how polyamines contribute to development and mediate stress responses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s20"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Figure S1.</ext-link>
<italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> natural accessions show varying root growth behaviours in response to cadaverine.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Figure S2.</ext-link>
<italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> produces a truncated transcript.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Figure S3.</ext-link>
<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression does not correlate with cadaverine sensitivity in all natural accessions.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Figure S4.</ext-link>
<italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> expression results in varying degrees of cadaverine sensitivity in Col and L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Table S1.</ext-link> Primers for chromosome 1 fine mapping.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/eru444/-/DC1">Table S2.</ext-link> Comparison of <italic toggle="yes">OCT1</italic> sequences from eight <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> natural accessions.</p><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_66_3_853__index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_eru444_jexbot126433_file001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by grants from the University of Wisconsin&#8211;Madison College of Agricultural and Life Sciences Hatch program and the National Science Foundation (IOS-0821884 and IOS-1121694) to PHM, by a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship to AKS, and by a National Institutes of Health Training Grant in Genetics at the University of Wisconsin&#8211;Madison to LMV. We thank Hiroshi Maeda for critically reviewing the manuscript and Christine Lelandais-Bri&#232;re for giving us the <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> mutant and the <italic toggle="yes">oct1-1</italic> [35S<sub>pro</sub>:OCT1<sup>WS</sup>] rescue lines. We also thank Katherine Baldwin and Shih-Heng Su for help with figures and technical assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alet</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrando</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Homeostatic control of polyamine levels under long-term salt stress in Arabidopsis: changes in putrescine content do not alleviate ionic toxicity</article-title>. <source>Plant Signaling and Behavior</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21330788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/psb.6.2.14214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3121984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>MGM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentsink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keurentjes</surname><given-names>JJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>What has natural variation taught us about plant development, physiology, and adaptation?</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1877</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19574434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.109.068114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2729614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bosch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Development of an AFLP based linkage map of L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>, Col and Cvi <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ecotypes and construction of a L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic>/Cvi recombinant inbred line population</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00115.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aouida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leduc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramotar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">AGP2</italic> encodes the major permease for high affinity polyamine import in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>280</volume>, <fpage>24267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M503071200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Tanguy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Plasticity of polyamine metabolism associated with high osmotic stress in rape leaf discs and with ethylene treatment</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regulation</source><volume>21</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tassoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Biosynthesis, oxidation and conjugation of aliphatic polyamines in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11354606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s007260170046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggemann</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pottosin</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schonknecht</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Cytoplasmic polyamines block the fast-activating vacuolar cation channel</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cass&#225;n</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masciarelli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Cadaverine production by <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum brasilense</italic> and its possible role in plant growth promotion and osmotic stress mitigation</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Soil Biology</source><volume>45</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cloete</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stander</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomerus</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Evidence of symbiosis between the soil yeast <italic toggle="yes">Cryptococcus laurentii</italic> and a sclerophyllous medicinal shrub, <italic toggle="yes">Agathosma betulina</italic> (Berg.) Pillans</article-title>. <source>Microbial Ecology</source><volume>57</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>632</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18958514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00248-008-9457-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>743</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuevas</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Cobollo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alc&#225;zar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarza</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koncz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altabella</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiburcio</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrando</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Putrescine is involved in Arabidopsis freezing tolerance and cold acclimation by regulating abscisic acid levels in response to low temperature</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>148</volume>, <fpage>1094</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18701673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.108.122945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2556839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A gateway cloning vector set for high-throughput functional analysis of genes in planta</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>133</volume>, <fpage>462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>469</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.103.027979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC523872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>W-R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>139</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.105.063743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1203353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fellenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#246;ttcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Phenylpropanoid polyamine conjugate biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> flower buds</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>70</volume>, <fpage>1392</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.08.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Natural variation in a polyamine transporter determines paraquat tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>109</volume>, <fpage>6343</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1121406109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3341036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamarnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frydman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Cadaverine, an essential diamine for the normal root development of germinating soybean (<italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic>) seeds</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>97</volume>, <fpage>778</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>785</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16668466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.97.2.778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1081074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspinall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottage</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>A rapid and robust method of identifying transformed <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings following floral dip transformation</article-title>. <source>Plant Methods</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17087829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1746-4811-2-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1636043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>KHM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Polyamines: natural and engineered abiotic and biotic stress tolerance in plants</article-title>. <source>Biotechnology Advances</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21241790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2011.01.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rounsley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Last</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Arabidopsis map-based cloning in the post-genome era</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>129</volume>, <fpage>440</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12068090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.003533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1540230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keurentjes</surname><given-names>JJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentsink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blankestijn-de Vries</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Effgen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Development of a near-isogenic line population of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and comparison of mapping power with a recombinant inbred line population</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>175</volume>, <fpage>891</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>905</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1534/genetics.106.066423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1800614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#246;mer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Putative spermine synthases from <italic toggle="yes">Thalassiosira pseudonana</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> synthesize thermospermine rather than spermine</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source><volume>581</volume>, <fpage>3081</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3086</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17560575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.05.074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#252;fner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Stress regulated members of the plant organic cation transporter family are localized to the vacuolar membrane</article-title>. <source>BMC Research Notes</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18710496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1756-0500-1-43</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2519074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aronova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stetsenko</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shevyakova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>NaCl- and ethylene-dependent cadaverine accumulation and its possible protective role in the adaptation of the common ice plant to salt stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source><volume>172</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lelandais-Bri&#232;re</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>GAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corre-Menguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Disruption of <italic toggle="yes">AtOCT1</italic>, an organic cation transporter gene, affects root development and carnitine-related responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>51</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03131.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>PARAQUAT RESISTANT1, a Golgi-localized putative transporter protein, is involved in intracellular transport of paraquat</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>162</volume>, <fpage>470</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23471133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.113.213892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3641224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Inward potassium channel in guard cells as a target for polyamine regulation of stomatal movements</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>124</volume>, <fpage>1315</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.124.3.1315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC59229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabanl</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Massive genomic variation and strong selection in Arabidopsis thaliana lines from Sweden</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>45</volume>, <fpage>884</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>890</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.2678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3755268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijering</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarria</surname><given-names>J-CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Design and validation of a tool for neurite tracing and analysis in fluorescence microscopy images</article-title>. <source>Cytometry</source><volume>58A</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cyto.a.20022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chibucos</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phuntumart</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012a</year><article-title>Kinetic and phylogenetic analysis of plant polyamine uptake transporters</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>236</volume>, <fpage>1261</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1273</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00425-012-1668-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulangi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phuntumart</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aouida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramotar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012b</year><article-title>Functional analysis of OsPUT1, a rice polyamine uptake transporter</article-title>. <source>Planta</source><volume>235</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00425-011-1486-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide signalling</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>395</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1369-5266(02)00282-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#228;ggman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarjala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Effects of exogenous diamines on the interaction between ectomycorrhizal fungi and adventitious root formation in Scots pine <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiology</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11960762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/treephys/22.6.373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The use of metabolomics to dissect plant responses to abiotic stresses</article-title>. <source>Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences</source><volume>69</volume>, <fpage>3225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22885821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-012-1091-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3437017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boiero</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masciarelli</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cass&#225;n</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Plant-growth-promoting compounds produced by two agronomically important strains of <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum brasilense</italic>, and implications for inoculant formulation</article-title>. <source>Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</source><volume>75</volume>, <fpage>1143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17345081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00253-007-0909-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramakers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruijter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deprez</surname><given-names>RHL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moorman</surname><given-names>AFM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Assumption-free analysis of quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) data</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience Letters</source><volume>339</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0304-3940(02)01423-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obaidat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagenbuch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>OATPs, OATs and OCTs: the organic anion and cation transporters of the SLCO and SLC22A gene superfamilies</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Pharmacology</source><volume>165</volume>, <fpage>1260</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22013971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1476-5381.2011.01724.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3372714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasband</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliceiri</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>671</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>675</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5554542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serafini-Fracassini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Duca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Transglutaminases: widespread cross-linking enzymes in plants</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source><volume>102</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aob/mcn075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2712369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuin</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pottosin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Polyamines prevent NaCl-induced K<sup>+</sup> efflux from pea mesophyll by blocking non-selective cation channels</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source><volume>581</volume>, <fpage>1993</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1999</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.04.032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shevyakova</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitin</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadomov</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Heat shock-induced cadaverine accumulation and translocation throughout the plant</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source><volume>161</volume>, <fpage>1125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sziderics</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oufir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trognitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopecky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matus&#237;kov&#225;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausman</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Organ-specific defence strategies of pepper (<italic toggle="yes">Capsicum annuum</italic> L.) during early phase of water deficit</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source><volume>29</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20087595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00299-010-0822-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berberich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Spermine signalling in tobacco: activation of mitogen-activated protein kinases by spermine is mediated through mitochondrial dysfunction</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source><volume>36</volume>, <fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>829</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2003.01923.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Polyamines reduce salt-induced oxidative damage by increasing the activities of antioxidant enzymes and decreasing lipid peroxidation in Virginia pine</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regulation</source><volume>46</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tisi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucretti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moschou</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubelakis-Angelakis</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Perturbation of polyamine catabolism can strongly affect root development and xylem differentiation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source><volume>157</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>215</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21746808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.111.173153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3165870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A QTL study for regions contributing to <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> root skewing on tilted surfaces</article-title>. <source>G3</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1534/g3.111.000331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3276130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X-Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>An arginine decarboxylase gene <italic toggle="yes">PtADC</italic> from <italic toggle="yes">Poncirus trifoliata</italic> confers abiotic stress tolerance and promotes primary root growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><volume>62</volume>, <fpage>2899</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2914</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jxb/erq463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basten</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year> Windows QTL Cartographer 2.5. Department of Statistics, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://statgen.ncsu.edu/qtlcart/">http://statgen.ncsu.edu/qtlcart/</uri>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Protocol: streamline cloning of genes into binary vectors in Agrobacterium via the Gateway(R) TOPO vector system</article-title>. <source>Plant Methods</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1746-4811-4-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2257932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>