<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4411111</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4411111.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4411111</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4411111</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25915922</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-00996</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>REGULATOR OF BULB BIOGENESIS1 (RBB1) Is Involved in Vacuole Bulb Formation in Arabidopsis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RBB1 Regulates of Vacuole Morphology</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names initials="SW">Sang Won</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jose M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Pierce</surname><given-names initials="M">Marcela</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<addr-line>Department of Plant and Microbial Biology, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names initials="D">Diane</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Iowa State University, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SH MRP. Performed the experiments: SH. Analyzed the data: SH MRP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JMA. Wrote the paper: SH MRP.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>mrojasp@ncsu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">251292</issue-id><elocation-id>e0125621</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-27 02:25:22.677"><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2015 Han et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Han et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0125621.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0125621.pdf"/><abstract><p>Vacuoles are dynamic compartments with constant fluctuations and transient structures such as trans-vacuolar strands and bulbs. Bulbs are highly dynamic spherical structures inside vacuoles that are formed by multiple layers of membranes and are continuous with the main tonoplast. We recently carried out a screen for mutants with abnormal trafficking to the vacuole or aberrant vacuole morphology. We characterized <italic toggle="yes">regulator of bulb biogenesis1-1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>), a mutant in Arabidopsis that contains increased numbers of bulbs when compared to the parental control. <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants also contain fewer transvacuolar strands than the parental control, and we propose the hypothesis that the formation of transvacuolar strands and bulbs is functionally related. We propose that the bulbs may function transiently to accommodate membranes and proteins when transvacuolar strands fail to elongate. We show that RBB1 corresponds to a very large protein of unknown function that is specific to plants, is present in the cytosol, and may associate with cellular membranes. RBB1 is involved in the regulation of vacuole morphology and may be involved in the establishment or stability of trans-vacuolar strands and bulbs.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National Science Foundation grant MCB-1244354 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov">http://www.nsf.gov</ext-link>) to M.R.P. and North Carolina State University. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="20"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The lytic vacuole in vegetative cells may occupy more 90% of the cell volume. This essential organelle is highly dynamic and has critical functions in cellular homeostasis, maintenance of turgor, storage and recycling [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Vacuoles are dynamic compartments with constant membrane fluctuations and transient and highly mobile structures such as trans-vacuolar strands (TVS), sheets and bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. TVS are dynamic tubules delimited by the tonoplast that are thought to distribute cytoplasmic contents, including organelles between opposite sides of the cortical cytoskeleton [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In root hairs of <italic toggle="yes">Hydrocharis dubia</italic>, TVS form predomindantly along the tip growing axis and are thought to deliver cytosolic components to the growing tip [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Many TVS sorrounding the phragmoplast were also observed in tobacco BY-2 cells during cell division [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The actin cytoskeleton has been localized to TVS [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and disruption of actin filaments results in their dissasembly [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, microinjection of antiserum against two actin-binding proteins of the villin group disrupted the TVS in root hair cells of <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">dubia</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The current model for TVS formation is that the actomyosin system regulates TVS formation and dynamics [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Bulbs are spherical structures of diameters between 1 and 10 &#956;m that are highly dynamic in the lumen of the vacuole. These membrane structures are associated with the outer tonoplast membrane or transvacuolar strands and contain cytoplasmic structures, even organelles, between the folded membranes [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Imaging by electron microscopy has indicated that bulbs are formed by multiple layers of tonoplast membranes, which explains the increased intensity of bulbs in fluorescently labeled tonoplasts [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Bulbs are present in LVs of cotyledon and leaf epidermis and their numbers decrease during cotyledon expansion [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and leaf maturation [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Bulbs have been visualized by fluorescencence microscopy of fluorescent protein (FP) fusions with several tonoplast proteins and in multiple cell types. For example, in vacuoles of tobacco leaves, bulbs were observed when GFP-VAM3/SYP22 [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] or a GFP fusion with the phosphate transporter NPT2 [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] were transiently expressed. In Arabidopsis, bulbs have been detected in epidermis of the root elongation zone and the leaf, sepal bundle sheet, and germinating pollen of stably transformed plants expressing either GFP-AtVAM3 [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], TPK1-GFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], TIP1;1-GFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], or FP fusions with other tonoplast intrinsic proteins [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In addition, the phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate sensor 2xFYVE-YFP also labels the bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. These structures are not simply the result of ectopic expression of FP fusions because they were also detected in Arabidopsis WT plants by electron microscopy [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It was recently proposed that bulbs may form by dimerization of GFP or YFP tags when fused to tonoplast markers, and that some of these structures may be artifacts from this interaction [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Two types of structures were distinguished: bulbs associated with high levels of expression of GFP fusions that showed 3 or more fold increase in fluorescence intensity compared to the tonoplast, and &#8220;intra-vacuolar spherical structures&#8221; (IVSPs) present in transgenic lines in which the intensity of fluorescence was only two fold that of the tonoplast and were visualized with a non-dimerizing GFP molecule. This distinction was most dramatic in the root elongation zone where only very bright bulbs were observed, but it was more complex in other tissues, such as the cotyledon epidermis, where both types of structures existed [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>Two hypotheses for the function of bulbs have been proposed. Bulbs may act as reservoirs of membranes for cell expansion or they may represent the first step for proteolysis of tonoplast proteins inside the vacuole [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Only two mutants with bulb phenotypes have been identified thus far. These are <italic toggle="yes">sgr2-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">vti11</italic>, and in both cases these mutants show a reduced number of bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. SGR2 encodes a protein similar to phospholipase A1, and <italic toggle="yes">sgr2</italic> mutants have an abnormal vacuole morphology with multiple small vacuole-like structures and abnormal distribution of the vacuole and the cytosol in shoot endodermal cells [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. VTI11 encodes a SNARE (soluble N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment protein receptor) protein that mediates membrane fusion between pre-vacuolar compartments and the vacuole [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. VTI11 is also involved in vacuole homotypic fusion, and <italic toggle="yes">vti11</italic> mutant alleles have highly fragmented vacuoles [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Given the highly abnormal vacuole morphology of these two mutants, it is unclear if the lack of bulbs is a direct or indirect effect of the loss of SGR2 and VTI11.</p><p>Here we describe the phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">regulator of bulb biogenesis1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>), a novel mutant in Arabidopsis that displays increased numbers of bulbs in otherwise normal vacuoles. We show that <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants make fewer TVS than the parental control. We propose the hypothesis that RBB1 may function in TVS formation and that increased bulb accumulation in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> may result from impaired formation of TVS. In addition, we show that the differential labeling of bulbs between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the parental line does not result from abnormal trafficking to the vacuole. We also identified <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus, which encodes a large plant-specific protein of unknown function.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Plant Material and Growth Conditions</title><p>The parental line carrying GFP-TIP2;1 and mCherry-HDEL [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and the marker lines TIP1;1-YFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and SYP22-RFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] were previously described. SALK_095160, SALK_067590 and SALK_074387 were obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC) and genotyped by PCR. pUBQ10::RFP-TIP1;1 was generated by Gateway cloning (Invitrogen). Briefly, the TIP1;1 CDS was amplified from Col-0 cDNA by PCR and the amplicon was introduced into pENTR-D-TOPO vector (Invitrogen). A RFP-TIP1;1 expression clone was generated by recombination with pUBN-RFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] using LR clonase II (Invitrogen). The promoter of the resulting construct was substituted with the full pUBQ10 promoter (1,596 bp) from pNIGEL07 (Geldner et al 2009) to generate <italic toggle="yes">pUBQ10</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">RFP-TIP1;1</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">3xYpet-RBB1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">RBB1-3xYpet</italic> constructs were generated by a Recombineering-based gene tagging system [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] using the JAtY76M24 clone and the primers listed in <xref rid="pone.0125621.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. After introducing 3xYpet, the JAtY clone was shortened by homologous recombination using "delleft" and "RB-amp" primers (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). This resulted in a fragment of the chromosomal region containing 12.8 kb upstream of start codon of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> and up to 5 kb downstream from the stop codon. These constructs were transformed into Agrobacterium GV3101 and then transformed into Col-0 wild type plants via floral dip [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>Seeds were plated on AGM (0.5X MS media and 1% sucrose) with 4 g /L GelRite. For light-grown seedlings, seeds were cold treated for 4 days in the dark to break dormancy and then incubated at 22&#176;C under a 16 h light photoperiod. For dark-grown seedlings, seeds were cold treated in the dark and then incubated at 22&#176;C while covered in aluminum foil.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Chemical Stocks and Treatments</title><p>C834 (ID 6982834) was from Chembridge, Brefeldin A from Sigma and Lysotracker Red and FM4-64 from Invitrogen. All chemicals were dissolved in 100% DMSO and all treatments were carried out with 4-day old seedlings, unless specified. BFA treatment was done in liquid AGM containing 75 &#956;M BFA and for 3 h. C834 treatment was done with 3-d-old seedlings in solid AGM-GelRite supplemented with 55&#956;M C834 for 48 hours as described [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. For staining, seedlings were incubated in liquid AGM containing 2 &#956;M Lysotracker Red for 2 h or 5 &#956;M FM4-64 for 5 min.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Microscopy</title><p>A Zeiss LSM 710 confocal microscope was used for all imaging experiments. A 40x water objective (1.1 N.A.) was used to image embryos and roots. A 20x objective (0.8 N.A.) was used to image hypocotyls and cotyledons. The excitation/emission wavelengths during acquisition were 488 nm/492&#8211;570 nm for GFP and Ypet, 561 nm/588&#8211;696 nm for mCherry and RFP, 514 nm/588&#8211;700 nm for FM4-64, and 561 nm/566-690 nm for Lysotracker red. To count the number of TVS, seedlings were imaged using a large pinhole to generate 600 &#956;m thick optical sections for hypocotyls and 102 &#956;m sections for cotyledons. A 40X objective was used and image zoom was kept at 0.6. Epidermal cells within the bottom half of the hypocotyl, but excluding the root-shoot junction, were used for TVS counting in hypocotyls. Epidermal cells from the adaxial side were used for cotyledons. TVS were counted in each cell from the collected images.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>RT-PCR</title><p>Total mRNA was extracted using TRI reagent (Ambion) and treated with DNase I (NEB). cDNA was synthesized using iScript cDNA Synthesis Kit (BioRad) and was used a template for RT-PCR. Oligo sequences used for PCR are shown in <xref rid="pone.0125621.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref> and 30 cycles were used for all reactions.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Map-based cloning and genome sequencing</title><p>A mapping population was generated from a cross between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the L<italic toggle="yes">er</italic> wild type background, and segregating homozygous <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants were identified based on the bulb phenotype. Two Single Sequence Length Polymorphism (SSLP) markers [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] co-segregated with the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype and placed the mutation in Chromosome 5. For SNP detection, 12 homozygous F<sub>3</sub> families from 1 backcross to the parental line were selected based on the bulb phenotype and 500 seedlings per family were used to generate DNA libraries. Samples were sequenced in an Illumina HiSeq sequencer as 100 bp reads at BGI (formerly Beijing Genomics Institute). The expected genome coverage was 35X. Data analysis was carried out at the Bioinformatics Consulting and Service Core at North Carolina State University as follows. Sequence reads were aligned to the TAIR10 genome using bowtie2 and variant calls were made using samtools mpileup. Variants were filtered for those located within TAIR10 genes and data was exported to a spreadsheet. Only SNPs located between markers RBCS-B and PINHEAD in Chromosome 5 were analyzed further. From these, mutations that were originally present in the parental line were identified from the sequencing of an unrelated mutant from the same mutagenesis screen. In addition, mutations in introns or UTRs, silent mutations and mutations unlikely to result from EMS mutagenesis were discarded.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Western Blot</title><p>Total proteins were extracted from 7 day-old seedlings. Samples were homogenized in 50mM HEPES-KOH, pH 6.5, 5 mM EDTA, 8% sucrose, 1mM DTT and proteinase inhibitors (Complete Mini, EDTA-free, Roche Diagnostics) in a chilled mortar. The homogenates were spun at 5,000g for 10 min at 4&#176;C and the supernatant was filtered through 3 layers of miracloth. For membrane protein fractions (P100), filtered total proteins were spun at 100,000g for 1 h at 4&#176;C and the pellet was resuspended in buffer. Protein concentration was quantified by the Bradford assay. For immunoblot of 3xYpet-RBB1, 8 &#956;g of proteins were loaded in a NuPAGE 3&#8211;8% Tris-Acetate gel (Life Technologies) following manufacturer instructions. The following antibodies were used: anti-GFP (Thermo MA5-15256), anti-cFBase (Agrisera AS04043), anti-H<sup>+</sup>ATPase (Agrisera AS07260) and anti-calreticulin [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Peroxidase-Conjugated Goat Anti-Mouse IgG (Thermo 32430) or peroxidase-conjugated Goat Anti-Rabbit (Thermo 32460) antibodies were used as secondary antibodies. Immunoblots were visualized by chemiluminescence with Clarity Western ECL Substrate (BioRad) using a G:BOX Chemi XRQ system (Syngene) for image capture. Signal was quantified using the GeneTools image analysis software (Syngene).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec009"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec010"><title>GFP-TIP2;1 labels excess bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">regulator of bulb biogenesis1</italic>
</title><p>We recently carried out a screen for mutants in tonoplast protein trafficking and vacuole biogenesis and characterized the function of the VTI11 SNARE protein and phosphoinositides in vacuole fusion [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. During the course of this work, we identified a mutant in which the tonoplast protein GFP-TIP2;1 labeled many vacuolar bulbs and it was named <italic toggle="yes">regulator of bulb biogenesis1-1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1)</italic>. In the parental line, the GFP-TIP2;1 protein labels the tonoplast and very few bulbs in root epidermis and cortex and the epidermis of hypocotyls, cotyledons and rosette leaves (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A&#8211;1D</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant, GFP-TIP2;1 also labels the tonoplast, and the size and morphology of the vacuole appeared normal. However, many more bulbs were evident as bright sub-vacuolar structures in multiple tissues (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1E&#8211;1H</xref>). In hypocotyls, bulbs were observed consistently in many cells in the epidermis and cortex (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1E</xref>). Bulbs were also apparent in high numbers in the epidermis of cotyledons and rosette leaves of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1F and 1H</xref>). Vacuolar bulbs were detected in roots (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1G</xref>), but this phenotype was variable amongst different seed stocks and was not characterized further. The variability in the root phenotype may be due to root-specific modifying factors that segregate in the population. No major defects in plant morphology were detected in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> homozygous plants (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Sequencing demonstrated that the <italic toggle="yes">GFP-TIP2;1</italic> transgene is intact in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and consequently, the bulb phenotype is not related to a mutation in the GFP-TIP2;1 protein sequence.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">regulator of bulb biogenesis1</italic> contains many bulbs in many cell types.</title><p>(a-h) <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants have more bulbs than the parental line. GFP-TIP2;1 localization in the parental line (WT, a-d) or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (e-h). Four-day-old seedlings were imaged by confocal microscopy to visualize morphology of the vacuole in the epidermis of hypocotyl (a, e) and cotyledon (b, f), and in root epidermis and cortex (c, g). The bulb phenotype was also observed in rosette leaves of 6-week-old plants (d, h). Scale bar = 20 &#956;m. (i-n) GFP-TIP2;1 and RFP-TIP1;1 co-localize in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs. The hypocotyls of 4-day-old dark-grown seedlings expressing GFP-TIP2;1 (green, i, l) and RFP-TIP1;1 (magenta, j, m) in the parental line (i-k) and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants (l-n) are shown. Merged images (k, n) are also shown. Scale bar: 20 &#956;m. (o) <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants do not accumulate higher levels of GFP-TIP2;1 in seedlings. Immunoblot of GFP-TIP2;1 accumulation in the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> using antibodies against GFP (&#945;-GFP) and Calreticulin (&#945;-CRT) as loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>TIP1;1-YFP is often found in vacuolar bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In order to determine if the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs accumulate TIP1;1 in a similar manner, we introduced a RFP-TIP1;1 fusion in the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant background. In the parental line, RFP-TIP1;1 localized to the tonoplast, and labeled very few bulbs in roots and hypocotyls (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1I&#8211;1K</xref>). RFP-TIP1;1 co-localized with GFP-TIP2;1 in the tonoplast and the bulbs when the two markers were co-expressed in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1L&#8211;1N</xref>). It was previously proposed that vacuolar bulbs are involved in the degradation of membrane proteins [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and that bulbs may form as a response to overexpression of dimer-type FP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. We then tested whether the increased number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> could be caused by enhanced accumulation of GFP-TIP2;1 in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> by Western blot. No significant differences in GFP-TIP2;1 protein accumulation were detected between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the parental control, indicating that the increased number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> is not related to differences in protein accumulation or stability (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1O</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125621.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1C Fig</xref>). These results overall indicate that, independent on the nature of the bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus is required to prevent the formation or accumulation of bulbs in the vacuole.</p><p>In order to compare <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs with the IVSPs and bulbs previously described [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], we measured the maximum intensity values for bulb membranes in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0125621.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>, maximum intensity values for the bulbs in the parental line are 1.2- and 1.3-fold higher than the outer tonoplast in cotyledons and hypocotyls, respectively. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs have 2 fold higher intensity than the tonoplast in hypocotyl, and 3.5-fold higher in cotyledons. Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs would fit the description of both IVSPs and bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Moreover, given the fact that the GFP-TIP2;1 protein levels in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants is similar to the parental line, we conclude that the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs are not simply the result of increased GFP dimerization in the mutant. However, we can not discard the possibility that GFP dimerization acts as an enhancer of the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1</italic> phenotype. Given the complexity of these structures, we will refer to them here simply as bulbs.</p><p>The vacuole membrane in many plant species constantly remodels with the formation of transvacuolar strands (TVS). We then hypothesized that the mechanisms involved in bulb formation and the dynamics of TVS may be related and that <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> may have a role in TVS formation. In order to test this possibility, we compared the number of TVS between the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants. In contrast to the parental line, which shows 4.06 &#177; 0.39 TVS per cell in cotyledon epidermis, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants have only 1.40 &#177; 0.16 (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125621.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3A and S3B Fig</xref>). Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> has ~3-fold fewer TVS than the parental line, and this result provides support to a hypothesis that RBB1 is involved in TVS formation. This phenotype was also observed in the hypocotyls of light- and dark-grown seedlings. Thus, the parental line showed an average of 2.2 &#177; 0.2 TVS per cell in the light and 1.75 &#177; 0.21 in the dark, while the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant had 1.25 &#177; 0.15 and 1.03 &#177; 0.19, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>). This indicates that <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> had a 40% reduction in the number of TVS per cell in hypocotyls in both light and dark-grown seedlings. These results point towards important roles of RBB1 in the remodeling of the vacuole that generates either bulbs or TVS.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants have fewer transvacuolar strands.</title><p>(a) The number of trans-vacuolar strands (TVS) per cell was counted in cotyledon cells from the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> seedlings that were grown in the light. n = 48 cells from 8 seedlings. (b) <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants have fewer TVS in hypocotyl from light- and dark-grown seedlings. Seedlings were germinated in the light or dark for 4 days and TVS were counted. n = 60 cells from 10 seedlings. Bars represent standard error. * Significantly different to the parental line in a t-test (P &#8804; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>The <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype can be detected 3 days post-germination</title><p>In order to characterize the developmental progression of the bulb phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, vacuoles were visualized at different times during seed germination (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A&#8211;3J</xref>). No bulbs were observed in PSVs of imbibed seeds or 1 d after incubation at 22&#176;C in either the parental line or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A, 3B, 3F and 3G</xref>). Bulbs were first detected at day 2 post-germination in both the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> when the large lytic vacuole is already established [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The bulbs were very transient in the parental line and very few were observed at 3 days or later. In contrast, the number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> continued to increase at days 3 and 4. These results indicate that <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> function may be important after day 3, but not during the early stages of germination.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Developmental progression of the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype and effects from light.</title><p>(a-j) The bulb phenotype is apparent in hypocotyls after 3 d of germination. Germinating seedlings from the parental line (GFP-TIP2;1, a-e) and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants (f-j) were imaged after 0&#8211;4 days of incubation. (k-n) The bulb phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> is present in light- and dark-grown seedlings. GFP-TIP2;1 localization in hypocotyls was visualized in 4-d-old seedlings from the parental line (WT, k, m) or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (l, n) when grown under light (k, l) or dark (m, n) conditions. n = 36 cells from 6 seedlings. All scale bars = 20 &#956;m. (o) Dark treatment does not alter the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype. The number of bulbs was counted in hypocotyls from parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> seedlings that were grown in the light or in the dark as in k-n. n = 9&#8211;15 seedlings. Bars represent standard error. (p) <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> hypocotyls have fewer TVS after 3 d of germination. Seedlings were germinated in the light and TVS were counted after 2 days of incubation. n = 50 cells from 5 seedlings. Bars represent standard error. * Significantly different to the parental line in a t-test (P &#8804; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>One proposed function of the bulbs is to contribute membranes during cell expansion [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This prompted us to investigate whether the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype was affected by conditions that promoted cell expansion such as the elongation of hypocotyls in the dark. To this end, vacuoles from the hypocotyl epidermis of parental and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> seedlings that were grown either in the light or the dark were imaged in the microscope, and bulbs were counted. While the parental control seedlings grown in the light contain 0.10 &#177; 0.03 bulbs per 10<sup>3</sup> &#956;m<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3K and 3O</xref>), the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant contains 1.00 &#177; 0.16 (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3L and 3O</xref>). Therefore, the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant contains 10 fold more bulbs per area in hypocotyls when compared to the parental control grown under normal light conditions. Next we analyzed the phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants in the dark. In contrast to the dark-grown parental control, which contains 0.07 &#177; 0.01 bulbs per 10<sup>3</sup> &#956;m<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3M and 3O</xref>), the dark-grown <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant showed 1.18 &#177; 0.09 bulbs per 10<sup>3</sup> &#956;m<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3N and 3O</xref>), or a 16-fold increase. Thus, the number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> was higher than the parental under both light treatments, but light availability did not significantly alter the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> phenotype. We then tested whether the increased number of bulbs would enhance the elongation rate of dark-grown <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> seedlings, but no differences in hypocotyl length were detected between the mutant and the parental control at 3 or 5 d (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3C Fig</xref>). Furthermore, cell elongation was not affected, as we could not detect significant differences in cell size between the wild type and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> hypocotyls when grown in the dark (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3D Fig</xref>).</p><p>Finally, if the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> is responsible for the bulb and TVS phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, we expected a similar developmental progression, which can be tested by quantification of TVS during germination. TVS could not clearly be detected before day 2, and no significant difference was detected at day 2 between wild type and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> hypocotyls when grown in the light (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3P</xref>) However, the number of TVS was reduced by 28% in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> when compared to the wild type. This reduction was even greater (41%) at day 4. Therefore, the appearance of the bulb phenotype at days 3 and 4 correlates well with the reduction of TVS numbers in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>GFP-TIP2;1 trafficking to the vacuole is not altered in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>
</title><p>The increased number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> could be the result of abnormal GFP-TIP2;1 protein trafficking to the vacuole. To test this hypothesis, two inhibitors for tonoplast protein trafficking were used. Brefeldin A (BFA) inhibits a Golgi-dependent pathway for tonoplast proteins in hypocotyls and C834 inhibits a Golgi-independent traffic of GFP-TIP2;1 to the tonoplast [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We treated the GFP-TIP2;1 (parental control), the TIP1;1-YFP line and the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant with BFA and visualized each fusion protein in hypocotyls. The fusion proteins localized to the tonoplast (GFP-TIP2;1) or tonoplast and bulbs (<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and TIP1;1-YFP) in the DMSO control as expected (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A&#8211;4C</xref>). In BFA-treated cells, the GFP-TIP2;1 localization was unchanged in the parental control (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4D</xref>) or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4E</xref>), indicating that the trafficking of this protein was still BFA-insensitive. In contrast and consistent with previous reports [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the TIP1;1-YFP marker line displayed large and bright aggregates in the presence of BFA (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4F</xref>). Next we tested sensitivity to C834. GFP-TIP2;1 localized to the tonoplast and did not co-localize with the ER marker mCherry-HDEL in neither the parental line or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4G&#8211;4I and 4M&#8211;4O</xref>). In contrast, GFP-TIP2;1 co-localized with the ER marker in C834-treated roots of the parental line (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4J&#8211;4L</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4P&#8211;4R</xref>). Therefore, we conclude that GFP-TIP2;1 traffics in a similar pathway in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the parental line, at least early in the secretory pathway, and that the bulb-localization of GFP-TIP2;1 in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> does not appear to be the result of altered trafficking to the vacuole.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>GFP-TIP2;1 trafficking to the vacuole is similar between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the parental line.</title><p>(a-f) BFA inhibits trafficking of TIP1;1YFP but not GFP-TIP2;1 in the parental line or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>. Four-day-old seedlings from the parental (GFP-TIP2;1, a, d), <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (b, e) or TIP1;1-YFP (c, f) were exposed to 0.1% DMSO (control, a, b, c) or 75 &#956;M BFA (d, e, f) for 3 hours and hypocotyl cells were imaged. BFA compartments are indicated with arrows. Scale: 20 &#956;m. (g-r) C834 inhibits GFP-TIP2;1 trafficking in the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>. Three-day-old seedlings from the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> were exposed to 0.5% DMSO (g-i, m-o) or 55 &#956;M C834 (j-l, p-r) for 48 h, and root cells were imaged in the microscope. Signal from GFP-TIP2;1 (green, g, j, m, p), the ER marker mCherry-HDEL (magenta, h, k, n, p) or the merged image is shown (i, l, o, r). Co-localization of GFP with mCherry-HDEL at the ER is indicated with arrowheads. Scale bar: 20 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus corresponds to <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic>
</title><p>The bulb phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> segregated as 25 out of 96 (1/3.84) in a backcross to the GFP-TIP2;1 parental line, suggesting that the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutation is recessive. In order to identify the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus, we used a combination of map-based cloning and whole genome sequencing. The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> gene mapped to a region of 2.2Mb in Chromosome 5 between markers RBCS-B and PINHEAD. Using Illumina whole-genome sequencing, we identified nucleotide variants in the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant genome between these two markers. From those, only two SNPs located within gene coding sequences and corresponding to EMS-type non-silent mutations were detected, in <italic toggle="yes">At5g38540</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic>. In order to determine which gene corresponded to the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus, we identified Salk T-DNA insertion alleles [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] for both candidate genes. Only one T-DNA line, SALK_095160, for <italic toggle="yes">At5g38540</italic> was available, but no homozygote plants could be recovered. Heterozygous plants were crossed to <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the vacuole phenotype of F<sub>1</sub> seedlings grown in the dark was analyzed. Out of 27 F<sub>1</sub> seedlings, none showed the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulb phenotype indicating that <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> was unlikely to correspond to <italic toggle="yes">At5g38540</italic>. We obtained two SALK T-DNA alleles for <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>). However, one of the T-DNA lines, SALK_067590, had a complex transgene insertion and could not be used. We used RT-PCR to determine if <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic> was expressed in SALK_074387. The expression of the full length <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic> was disrupted in SALK_074387 (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>), and therefore, this was a good mutant allele to test for the bulb phenotype. However, it is unclear if this allele is a complete loss of function allele because partial transcripts can be detected by RT-PCR. We named this allele <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus corresponds to <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic>.</title><p>(a) Schematic structure of the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus indicating the positions of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1</italic> alleles. Exons are indicated as black boxes and introns are indicated as white boxes. 5' and 3' UTRs are indicated in gray. Triangles indicate T-DNA insertions of SALK lines. The position of three diagnostic RT-PCR amplicons at the 5&#8217; end, middle and 3&#8217; end are shown. (b) Accumulation of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> transcripts as determined by RT-PCR with gene specific primers in seedlings from Col-0 (WT), <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>, the GFP-TIP2;1 parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>. Three pairs of gene specific primers were used to detect the transcript at the 5' end, middle, and 3' end of the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> gene as indicated in (a). Numbers represent amplicon size. (c-e) Lack of genetic complementation between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>. Hypocotyls of four-day-old dark-grown seedlings from the parental control (WT, c), <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (d) and the F<sub>1</sub> progeny from a cross between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1/rbb1-2</italic> double heterozygotes, e) were imaged by confocal microscopy. Scale bar: 20&#956;m. (f-g) <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> contains bulbs in a similar manner as <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>. Four-day-old seedlings were stained with 2 &#956;M Lysotracker Red for 2 hours to label the vacuole in Col-0 (WT) and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>. Bulbs are indicated with arrows. Scale: 20 &#956;m. (h) <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> is expressed in many developmental stages. The accumulation of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> transcripts was determined by RT-PCR with gene specific primers in various tissues of 4 and 7-day old Col-0 (WT) plants. Two pairs of gene specific primers detected the 5' end and 3' end of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> gene as indicated in (a).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine if <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> is <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic>, a complementation test between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> was carried out. F<sub>1</sub> seedlings from a cross between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and homozygous <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> were incubated in the dark and analyzed by fluorescence microscopy for the bulb phenotype. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5E</xref>, the double heterozygote F<sub>1</sub> plants display the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1</italic> phenotype and indicate the lack of complementation between the two mutant alleles. We were unable to confirm this result in the F<sub>2</sub> population as the GFP-TIP2;1 transgene was consistently silenced in the segregating population whenever the SALK insertion was present. This result is consistent with highly silenced transgenes in SALK insertion lines [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. To confirm the identity of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>, we visualized the vacuole morphology of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> mutants with Lysotracker Red, a fluorescent dye that stains acidic organelles including plant vacuoles [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and the tonoplast membrane [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig</xref>). This experiment could only be carried out in cotyledons from light-grown seedlings as penetration of fluorescent dyes in hypocotyls is very poor. Similar to the reduced number of bulbs in the GFP-TIP2;1 line, bulbs were rarely detected in wild type Col-0 cotyledons (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5F</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125621.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Movie</xref>). On the contrary, the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> mutant allele showed a similar bulb phenotype as the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant with 4&#8211;5 vacuolar bulbs per cell in these cells (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5G</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125621.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Movie</xref>). This phenotype also segregated as ~1/4 and therefore <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> is likely to be recessive. These results confirmed that the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus corresponds to <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic> and that the bulb phenotype may be detected in the absence of the GFP-TIP2;1 transgene.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic> encodes a large protein of 2,890 amino acids. The mutation in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> is a C/T nucleotide substitution that results in an A1070V substitution in the predicted protein sequence. BLASTp analysis in NCBI identified only two proteins with protein similarity covering at least 40% of the RBB1 protein sequence, CARUB_v10003962mg from <italic toggle="yes">Capsella rubella</italic> and EUTSA_v10027617mg from <italic toggle="yes">Eutrema salsugineum</italic>. All other hits (~40) show high similarity to a 75 amino acid region at the C terminus of RBB1. Remarkably, no significant similarity was found outside of plant taxa using BLASTp, which indicates that RBB1 is a plant-specific protein. In addition, no specific domain hits were detected using the Conserved Domain Database search function in NCBI [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], but regions of similarity to three multi-domain structures were detected. Only two proteins were identified with significant similarity to RBB1 in <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">rubella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">salsugineum</italic>. RBB1 belongs to the putative Plant Model Organism Orthologous Group APK_ORTHOMCL5144, which includes genes from Rice, Poplar, Sorghum, Maize, and Brachypodium (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/cgi-bin/ortholog_group_apk.pl">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu/cgi-bin/ortholog_group_apk.pl</ext-link>). This group is also supported by gene family clustering of orthologous genes in Phytozome (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net">www.phytozome.net</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The putative orthologs also encode very large proteins (up to 3,715 aa). One of the putative orthologs, <italic toggle="yes">Ricinus communis</italic> gene 29917.t000066, contains a 32 amino acid region that is 32% identical to the microtubule-associated protein futsch in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. These results overall indicate that RBB1 is a novel plant-specific protein with unknown molecular function.</p><p>In order to determine the spatial and temporal expression of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>, the accumulation of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> transcripts was analyzed by RT-PCR in Col-0 wild type plants. <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> accumulated at similar levels in 4- and 7-day-old light-grown seedlings, and in rosette leaves and inflorescences (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5H</xref>). These results are consistent with publicly available databases for <italic toggle="yes">At5g40450</italic>. According to Arabidopsis eFP browser [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> is expressed in leaves and roots of both seedlings and mature plants, flowers and all stages of embryo development. Seedlings treated for 12 h with ABA, heat, cold and osmotic stress have decreased levels of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> transcripts [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In contrast, 3 h treatment with photosystem II inhibitor N-octyl-3-nitro-2,4,6-trihydroxybenzamide (PNO8) or the brassinosteroid biosynthesis inhibitor brassinazole 220 resulted in a 2-fold induction of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. These results indicate that <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> may have important functions in multiple developmental stages. The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> transcript accumulation was also analyzed in the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, but no differences in the expression level were detected (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>). Therefore, the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutation did not affect the expression of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> at the transcriptional level.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>RBB1 is a cytosolic protein</title><p>In order to characterize the function of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>, a fluorescent protein (FP) fusion was generated to visualize its protein localization. Given the large size of the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> coding sequence, we used Recombineering [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] to generate a FP fusion with RBB1 driven by its own promoter and other regulatory sequences. This system utilizes homologous recombination with TAC clones to fuse the gene encoding 3xYpet (YFP for energy transfer), a bright variation of YFP [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], to the gene of interest within the native genomic context. Both N- and C-terminal fusions of RBB1 with 3xYpet were generated and introduced into Col-0 wild type. We could not detect fluorescence in RBB1-3xYpet lines after selection of 15 independent transformants. However, 3xYpet-RBB1 was detected in cotyledon epidermal cells, root cortical cells and, although very faint, in the cortex of hypocotyls of light-grown seedlings (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5A and S5B Fig</xref>). No Ypet signal was detected at the root tip corresponding to the cell division zone. In order to determine if the 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion is functional, we introgressed the transgene into the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> allele by crossing. This experiment was carried out in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> because the GFP-TIP2;1 marker in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> is tightly linked to the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> locus and the probability of identifying <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> segregants without GFP-TIP2;1 was very low. In contrast to <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> seedlings stained with Lysotracker red, which showed many bulbs in cotyledons (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6A</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> seedlings expressing the 3xYpet-RBB1 protein have vacuole morphology very similar to the wild type (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B and 6C</xref>). Therefore, the 3xYpet-RBB1 construct complements the bulb phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> indicating that this fusion protein is functional.</p><fig id="pone.0125621.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0125621.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>3xYpet-RBB1 is a cytoplasmic protein that associates with the tonoplast.</title><p>(a-c) A 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion complements the bulb phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>. Four-day-old seedlings from <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> (a) or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> 3xYpet-RBB1 (b, c) were stained with Lysotracker Red (magenta, a, b) to label the vacuole. The signal from 3xYpet-RBB1 (c) for the complemented plant is shown. (d-f) 3xYpet-RBB1 does not co-localize with FM4-64. Images show the cotyledon of 7-d-old seedlings expressing 3xYpet-RBB1 (d) stained with 5 &#956;M FM4-64 (e) and the merged image (f). (g-i) 3xYpet-RBB1 and RFP-SYP22 do not co-localize. Cotyledons of 7-d-old seedlings expressing 3xYpet-RBB1 (g) and RFP-SYP22 (h) were imaged. Merged image (i) is shown. (j-l) 3xYpet-RBB1 and Lysotracker Red do not co-localize in rosette leaves. Seedlings from the 3xYpet-RBB1 line were stained with Lysotracker Red. Signal from 3xYpet-RBB1 (j), Lysotracker Red (k) and the merged image (l) are shown. Arrowheads indicate the localization of 3xYpet-RBB1 at the tip of elongating trans-vacuolar strands. (m-o) GFP molecules can also label the tips of transvacuolar strands. Seedlings from a 35::GFP marker line were stained with Lysotracker Red. The GFP signal (m), Lysotracker Red (n) and the merged image (o) are shown. Arrowheads indicate the tip of TVS. All scale bars = 20 &#956;m. (p) 3xYpet-RBB1 accumulates in the soluble (S100) and membrane pellet (P100) fractions from whole seedlings. Immunoblot of 3xYpet-RBB1 soluble (S100) and membrane (P100) fractions from Col-0 and 3xYpet-RBB1 transgenic plants using antibodies against GFP (&#945;-GFP), cFBPase (&#945;-cFBPase, control for soluble fraction), and Plasma Membrane H+ATPase (&#945;-H+ATPase, control for membrane fraction).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0125621.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The localization of 3xYpet-RBB1 was diffuse and suggestive of cytosolic localization in cotyledons of 7-day-old seedlings (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6D</xref>). In order to determine its sub-cellular distribution in detail, we tested for co-localization between 3xYpet-RBB1 and the plasma membrane dye FM4-64, a marker for the tonoplast, RFP-SYP22 [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and the vacuole dye Lysotracker Red. The 3xYpet-RBB1 marker does not co-localize with FM4-64 (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6D&#8211;6F</xref>) or with RFP-SYP22 (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6G&#8211;6I</xref>). The marker was found in the cytosol and did not co-localize with Lysotracker Red (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6J&#8211;6L</xref>), even though occasionally there was good co-localization between these two signals (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5C&#8211;S5E Fig</xref>). These results indicate 3xYpet-RBB1 protein is most likely a soluble protein that accumulates in the cytosol. We also detected 3xYpet-RBB1 in a punctate pattern inside the vacuole that seemed to correspond to the tip of TVS labeled with Lysotracker Red in confocal images (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6J&#8211;6L</xref>). Interestingly, 3xYpet-RBB1 remained associated with the tip during the elongation of those TVS (<xref rid="pone.0125621.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5F Fig</xref>) in a similar manner as actin bundles [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These TVS structures may represent cross-sections of membrane sheets that transverse the vacuole, as previously proposed [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In order to determine the significance of this localization, we compared it to the localization of a soluble GFP marker in the same manner. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6M&#8211;6O</xref>, a simple GFP marker can also label the tip of TVS, and therefore, the punctate localization of RBB1 may simply result from accumulation of cytoplasmic proteins at the tip of emerging TVS. Immunoblot analysis was used to confirm that the 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion protein accumulates as the expected size of ~400 kDa in seedlings. Membrane and soluble fractions were isolated from wild type Col-0 and the 3xYpet-RBB1 line and the fusion protein was detected with an anti-GFP antibody. The cytosolic fructose-1,6-bisphosphatase (cFBPase) and plasma membrane H<sup>+</sup>ATPase were used as soluble and membrane protein controls, respectively. 3xYpet-RBB1 was detected in both the soluble (S100) and the membrane (P100) fractions in 4 days-old seedlings (<xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6L</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0125621.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Fig</xref>). These results overall indicate that 3xYpet-RBB1 is a large soluble protein that is likely to associate with cellular membranes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have identified <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, a novel mutant with defects in vacuole morphology. Vacuoles in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> contain increased numbers of bulbs in the large central vacuole of cotyledons and hypocotyl cells when compared to the parental control. These defined vacuolar sub-structures can be visualized with fluorescent protein markers for the tonoplast [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It was recently proposed that bulbs, specially when they have more than double the intensity of fluorescence when compared to the tonoplast, are artifacts that result from GFP dimerization that stabilizes the adhesion of tonoplast membranes [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This model, however, does not explain the accumulation of bulbs in the 2xFYVE-YFP line in which the fusion protein associates with the membrane in a reversible manner by binding to a specific phosphoinositide [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The GFP-TIP2;1-labeled bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> showed between 2 and 3.5-fold higher fluorescence intensity when compared to the tonoplast, indicating that they are likely to have a similar structure as previously characterized IVPS and bulbs [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. We can not discard the possibility that the GFP fusion enhances the stability of the bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, but <italic toggle="yes">rbb1</italic> mutant alleles comprise a sensitized genetic background for studying the formation and regulation of these structures, which are quite elusive under normal conditions. The two other mutants that have been identified as having abnormal bulb accumulation, <italic toggle="yes">sgr2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">vti11</italic>, have fewer bulbs, also have very abnormal vacuole morphology [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Hence, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> is a unique tool to characterize the structure and function of the bulbs in the absence of other vacuolar defects.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> encodes a very large protein with unknown molecular function. In order to determine the function of <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic>, we generated a 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion protein under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> promoter. This construct complemented the <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> mutant phenotype indicating that the 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion is functional. In seedlings, 3xYpet-RBB1 was detected in the root in the elongation and differentiation zones, but not in the cell division zone, and in hypocotyl and cotyledon epidermal cells. Therefore, 3xYpet-RBB1 accumulates in cells that contain a large lytic vacuole [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], consistent with a role of RBB1 in regulating the morphology of this important organelle. Confocal scanning laser microscopy with the 3xYpet-RBB1 line indicated that this protein accumulates in the cytosol, and that in a few instances also co-localizes with Lysotracker red, a fluorescent dye that labels the tonoplast. RBB1 was found both in the soluble and membrane fractions by fractionation experiments, which raises the possibility that RBB1 may associate with membranes. 3xYpet-RBB1 was often present at the tips of elongating TVS in cotyledons and leaves, but visualization of a GFP control indicated that this localization may be detected some times with other cytosolic proteins.</p><p>We detected a significant decrease in the number of TVS in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants both in light- and dark-grown hypocotyls and in cotyledons of light-grown seedlings. The TVS phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> supports the hypothesis that RBB1 functions in the formation or stability of TVS. This hypothesis is supported by the observation that both the bulb phenotype and the reduced TVS phenotype can be detected at day 3 during germination. TVS are very dynamic structures that require the actomyosin cytoskeleton [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and are thought redistribute cytoplasmic contents or to enhance the structural stability of the cytoskeleton [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A potential role of RBB1 in TVS formation is consistent with the expression of 3xYpet-RBB1 in cells that contain a large vacuole. Given the localization of 3xYpet-RBB1 to the cytosol and its accumulation in both the soluble and membrane fractions, it is tempting to speculate that RBB1 interacts with the tonoplast during the formation and elongation of TVS and contributes to the remodeling of the vacuolar membrane. However, more experiments beyond the scope of this work are needed to test this possibility. Moreover, we speculate that the increased number of bulbs in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> results from its inability to form functional TVS. Therefore, we propose an alternative model for bulb biogenesis in which a bulb forms when a TVS initiates but fails to elongate and the bulb functions as a mean to accommodate tonoplast membranes and cytoskeletal proteins that may have accumulated at the initiation site, until the bulb membrane is reabsorbed back into the tonoplast. It follows that the bulbs may have no specific function in the vacuole other than the transient accumulation of membranes and proteins when TVS failed to elongate. Further characterization of the function of RBB1 and interacting partners may shed light in the mechanisms that remodel the vacuole membrane into TVS or bulbs. Unlike the effects of GFP dimerization in vacuole morphology after fusion with vacuolar H+-pyrophosphatase [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], it is unlikely that GFP dimerization plays a big role in the TVS phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1</italic>. While the bulb fluorescence intensity for cotyledons was 3.5 fold higher than that of tonoplast, this ratio is only 2.0 for hypocotyls in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, the same tissue that was used to quantify TVS in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>. Therefore, a ratio higher than 2.0 is not necessary in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> to induce the accumulation of bulbs or a reduction in TVS.</p><p>Previously proposed functions of vacuolar bulbs include acting as a tonoplast reservoir for rapid growth or serving as the sites of degradation of tonoplast membrane and proteins (Saito et al. 2002 and Ma&#238;trejean et al. 2011). We tested one of these hypotheses by measuring the hypocotyl growth of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> in the dark, a condition that promotes cell elongation. However, no obvious growth differences were observed between <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> and the parental line. One possibility is that the additional tonoplast membranes contained in <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> bulbs do not contribute to cell elongation. Alternatively, other factors such as the elasticity of the cell wall [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] may be limiting and would prevent us from detecting a difference in this assay.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> gene is expressed in seedlings and adult plants both in shoots and roots. That <italic toggle="yes">RBB1</italic> is expressed as a full-length transcript of 8,957 bp is supported by several ESTs as well as the alignment of RNAseq reads spanning the entire coding sequence by the Integrated Genome Browser [<xref rid="pone.0125621.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0125621.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The molecular function of RBB1 is unknown as the protein has no conserved domains, and it represents a new plant-specific protein. The identification of proteins that interact with RBB1 may shed light on the molecular mechanisms by which RBB1 could regulate the morphology of the vacuole.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec016"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutants show normal growth.</title><p>(a-b) Normal growth phenotype of 4 day-old seedlings (a), and 6 week-old plants (b) from the parental line, <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>, Col-0, and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic>. (c) Relative GFP content in the parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> by immunoblotting. The intensity values for GFP from <xref rid="pone.0125621.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1O</xref> were normalized against the Calreticulin (CRT) loading control.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Maximum fluorescence intensity for bulbs and tonoplast.</title><p>(a, b) Examples of fluorescence intensity profiles that were used to estimate intensity values in the parental line (a) and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> (b). Intensity value profiles from a line selection (white lines) across each bulb or the tonoplast were extracted in Image J from confocal images. Only the maximum value was collected for each line selection (arrowheads). (c, d) Maximum fluorescence intensity of bulbs and the tonoplast from cotyledon (c) and hypocotyl cells (d) in the parental line or <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> grown in the light. Images were analyzed as in (a, b). Data shown is the average of maximum intensity values for 10&#8211;15 images from at least 3 seedlings each. The numbers inside the white bars correspond to the calculated ratio between the maximum fluorescence intensity in the bulbs and that of the tonoplast. Identical microscope settings were used when collecting data for cotyledons or when collecting data for hypocotyls.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s002.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Quantification of TVS and growth phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic>.</title><p>(a-b) An example of images used for TVS quantification. Thick optical sections were captured from hypocotyls (a). A seedling from the parental line is shown. The boxed area is enlarged in (b) to show the TVS that were counted (arrowhead). Bar = 20 &#956;m. (c-d) The parental line and <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> have similar hypocotyl growth in the dark. Seedlings were grown in the dark for up to 5 days and seedlings were imaged in a scanner. Hypocotyl length was measured using Image J (NIH) from seedlings at days 3 and 5 (n = 10). Black bars represent parental line; gray bars represent <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-1</italic> mutant.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S4 Fig</label><caption><title>Lysotracker Red labels the tonoplast in addition to the vacuole lumen in Arabidopsis.</title><p>GFP-TIP2;1 seedlings were stained with Lysotracker Red for 2 h and imaged by confocal microscopy. The tonoplast marker GFP-TIP2;1 (green, a) co-localizes with the membrane signal of Lysotracker Red (magenta, b). White signal in the merged image (c) represents co-localized pixels. Scale bar = 20 &#956;m.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s004.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S5 Fig</label><caption><title>Localization of 3xYpet-RBB1.</title><p>(a-b) 3xYpet-RBB1 can be detected in cotyledons, hypocotyls and roots. Four-day-old seedlings expressing 3xYpet-RBB1 under the control of its native promoter were imaged by confocal microscopy. An overlay of the fluorescence signal and the bright field image is shown in (a) and the fluorescence signal is shown in (b). The arrow in (b) indicates the position of the root tip. Scale bar = 200&#956;m. (c-e) An example where the 3xYpet-RBB1 co-localizes with Lysotracker Red. 3xYpet-RBB1 is shown in green (c), Lysotracker Red is shown in magenta (d) and the merged image is shown (e). Scale bar = 10 &#956;m. (f) The 3xYpet-RBB1 signal remains associated with the TVS tip. Cotyledons that were stained with Lysotracker were captured by time lapse microscopy every 7.75 sec. Note that the 3xYpet-RBB1 signal (green) remains associated with the tip of the elongating TVS labeled with Lysotracker Red (magenta). Scale bar = 10 &#956;m.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s005.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S6 Fig</label><caption><title>3xYpet-RBB1 Immunoblot.</title><p>This blot corresponds to the image shown in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6O</xref> but includes the entire blot to show the size of the 3xYpet-RBB1 fusion. * Non-specific bands.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s006.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Movie</label><caption><title>Z-stack of Col-WT cotyledon stained with Lysotracker Red.</title><p>Four-day-old Col-WT seedlings stained with Lysotracker Red as in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5F</xref>. The stack represents 20 optical sections every 1 &#956;m. Image dimensions are x:106.17 &#956;m, y:106.17 &#956;m.</p><p>(AVI)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s007.avi" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Movie</label><caption><title>Z-stack of <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> cotyledon stained with Lysotracker Red.</title><p>Four-day-old <italic toggle="yes">rbb1-2</italic> seedlings stained with Lysotracker Red as in <xref rid="pone.0125621.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5G</xref>. The stack represents 45 optical sections every 1 &#956;m. Image dimensions are x:106.17 &#956;m, y:106.17 &#956;m.</p><p>(AVI)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s008.avi" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s009" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>List of primers used for Recombineering.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s009.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0125621.s010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>List of primers used for RT-PCR.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0125621.s010.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank W. Boss, T. Long and G. Drakakaki for critical reading of the manuscript, and B. Boston and J. Gillikin for sharing of materials. We thank the Rojas-Pierce laboratory and the plant genetics group for useful discussions.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0125621.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bassham DC, Brandizzi F, Otegui MS, Sanderfoot AA. The secretory system of Arabidopsis. The Arabidopsis Book 2008. p. 1&#8211;29.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1199/tab.0116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3243370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muntz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein dynamics and proteolysis in plant vacuoles</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2391</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Etxeberria</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Ende</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vacuolar protein sorting mechanisms in plants</article-title>. <source>FEBS J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>280</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>979</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.12092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruthardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gulde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Four-dimensional imaging of transvacuolar strand dynamics in tobacco BY-2 cells</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>225</volume>(<issue>3&#8211;4</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-005-0093-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16228899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeyasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vacuolar membrane dynamics revealed by GFP-AtVam3 fusion protein</article-title>. <source>Genes to Cells</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12081650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2443.2002.00550.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebenfuhr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunahay</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frohlick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazurkiewicz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meehl</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Stop-and-go movements of plant Golgi stacks are mediated by the acto-myosin system</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.121.4.1127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC59480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonobe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimmen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of plant villin in the organization of the actin cytoskeleton, cytoplasmic streaming and the architecture of the transvacuolar strand in root hair cells of Hydrocharis</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>210</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>836</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonobe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimmen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanism of Inhibition of Cytoplasmic Streaming by Auxin in Root Hair Cells of Hydrocharis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1342</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kutsuna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasezawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamic Organization of Vacuolar and Microtubule Structures during Cell Cycle Progression in Synchronized Tobacco BY-2 Cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcf138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kutsuna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okubo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasezawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Actin Microfilaments Regulate Vacuolar Structures and Dynamics: Dual Observation of Actin Microfilaments and Vacuolar Membrane in Living Tobacco BY-2 Cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>839</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcj056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valenta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warn</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Microinjected profilin affects cytoplasmic streaming in plant cells by rapidly depolymerizing actin microfilaments</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: S0960-9822(00)00050-6
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7922326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0960-9822(00)00050-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morizane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Plant 115-kDa Actin-Filament Bundling Protein, P-115-ABP, is a Homologue of Plant Villin and is Widely Distributed in Cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1088</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14581634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Honing</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Ruijter</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emons</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ketelaar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Actin and myosin regulate cytoplasm stiffness in plant cells: a study using optical tweezers</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>185</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03017.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19761443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nebenf&#252;hr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamic rearrangements of transvacuolar strands in BY-2 cells imply a role of myosin in remodeling the plant actin cytoskeleton</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>224</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-004-0068-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15614481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroiwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hisada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A complex and mobile structure forms a distinct subregion within the continuous vacuolar membrane in young cotyledons of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11844103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.0960-7412.2001.01189.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craddock</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Benedetto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fluorescent reporter proteins for the tonoplast and the vacuolar lumen identify a single vacuolar compartment in Arabidopsis cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1371</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17905861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.107.103945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2151705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bottanelli F, Foresti O, Hanton S, Denecke J. Vacuolar transport in tobacco leaf epidermis cells involves a single route for soluble cargo and multiple routes for membrane cargo. Plant Cell. 2011. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.085480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3180807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boevink</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oparka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>High-throughput viral expression of cDNA-green fluorescent protein fusions reveals novel subcellular addresses and identifies unique proteins that interact with plasmodesmata</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1507</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.013284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC165397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maitrejean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>How are tonoplast proteins degraded?</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1809</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: 17867 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.6.11.17867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22057339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3329355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maitrejean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wudick</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voelker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prinsi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller-Roeber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czempinski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Assembly and sorting of the tonoplast potassium channel AtTPK1 and its turnover by internalization into the vacuole</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>156</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1783</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.177816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21697507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3149923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beebo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Der</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leborgne-Castel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Life with and without <italic toggle="yes">AtTIP1;1</italic>, an Arabidopsis aquaporin preferentially localized in the apposing tonoplasts of adjacent vacuoles</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>1&#8211;2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-009-9465-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19229639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geminating pollen has tubular vacuoles, displays highly dynamic vacuole biogenesis, and requires VACUOLESS1 for proper function</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1227</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.103.037382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC389947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Awai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The occurrence of 'bulbs', a complex configuration of the vacuolar membrane, is affected by mutations of vacuolar SNARE and phospholipase in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04665.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21645145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Segami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asaoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maeshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamics of Vacuoles and H+-Pyrophosphatase Visualized by Monomeric Green Fluorescent Protein in Arabidopsis: Artifactual Bulbs and Native Intravacuolar Spherical Structures</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3416</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.127571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4371836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niihama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>SGR2, a phospholipase-like protein, and zig/sgr4, a SNARE, are involved in the shoot gravitropism of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.010215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC150549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niihama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A SNARE complex unique to seed plants is required for protein storage vacuole biogenesis and seed development of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.057711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18984676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2613668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderfoot</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovaleva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interactions between syntaxins identify at least five SNARE complexes within the Golgi/prevacuolar system of the Arabidopsis cell</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1091/mbc.12.12.3733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC60751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Welsh</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Pierce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Homotypic Vacuole Fusion Requires VTI11 and Is Regulated by Phosphoinositides</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1026</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssu019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24569132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera-Serrano</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Welsh</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Pierce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A small molecule inhibitor partitions two distinct pathways for trafficking of tonoplast intrinsic proteins in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e44735</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044735PONE-D-12-19870</pub-id> [pii].
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22957103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3434187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geldner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denervaud-Tendon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stierhof</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid, combinatorial analysis of membrane compartments in intact plants with a multicolor marker set</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. doi: TPJ3851 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03851.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19309456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4854200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blatt</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Ubiquitin-10 promoter-based vector set for fluorescent protein tagging facilitates temporal stability and native protein distribution in transient and stable expression studies</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04322.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20735773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benavente</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A recombineering-based gene tagging system for Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>712</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04524.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21294796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for <italic toggle="yes">Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillmor</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>W-R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positional cloning in Arabidopsis Why it feels good to have a Genome Initiative working for you</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>795</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>805</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.123.3.795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1539260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabanes-Macheteau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillikin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leborgne-Castel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lerouge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boston</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Protein recycling from the Golgi apparatus to the endoplasmic reticulum in plants and its minor contribution to calreticulin retention</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.12.5.739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC139924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrhardt</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffitts</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Random GFP: cDNA fusions enable visualization of subcellular structures in cells of Arabidopsis at a high frequency</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3718</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10737809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.97.7.3718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC16306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattolin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorieul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khonsari</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>In vivo imaging of the tonoplast intrinsic protein family in Arabidopsis roots</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>. doi: 1471-2229-9-133 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-9-133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2784467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leisse</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Genome-wide insertional mutagenesis of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>301</volume>(<issue>5633</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1086391301/5633/653</pub-id> [pii].
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daxinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jauvion</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasciolli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaucheret</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Unexpected silencing effects from T-DNA tags in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laxmi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morsy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Light Plays an Essential Role in Intracellular Distribution of Auxin Efflux Carrier PIN2 in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1510</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0001510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18231596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2200863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaillais</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fobis-Loisy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miege</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaude</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for a sorting endosome in Arabidopsis root cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: TPJ3338 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03338.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17999644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nov&#225;kov&#225;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feraru</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tejos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viaene</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>SAC phosphoinositide phosphatases at the tonoplast mediate vacuolar function in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2818</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1324264111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3932866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chitsaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derbyshire</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeWeese-Scott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>CDD: a Conserved Domain Database for the functional annotation of proteins</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(Database issue):<fpage>D225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq1189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21109532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3013737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Phytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>40</volume>(Database issue):<fpage>D1178</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3245001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vinegar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nahal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ammar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Provart</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>An &#8220;Electronic Fluorescent Pictograph&#8221; Browser for Exploring and Analyzing Large-Scale Biological Data Sets</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e718</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1934936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sachsenberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#228;tsch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Stress-induced changes in the Arabidopsis thaliana transcriptome analyzed using whole-genome tiling arrays</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1068</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03835.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19222804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama-Nakashita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The AtGenExpress hormone and chemical treatment data set: experimental design, data evaluation, model data analysis and data access</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>526</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0960-7412.2008.03510.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>. <article-title>A guide to choosing fluorescent proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>905</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamic coordination of cytoskeletal and cell wall systems during plant cell morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>R800</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.07.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tobena-Santamaria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laxalt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Divecha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Visualization of PtdIns3P dynamics in living plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>700</lpage>. doi: TPJ2830 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02830.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16856980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zouhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant vacuoles: where did they come from and where are they heading?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2009.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulledge</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vora</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loraine</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mining Arabidopsis thaliana RNA-seq data with Integrated Genome Browser reveals stress-induced alternative splicing of the putative splicing regulator SR45a</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1100355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22291167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0125621.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helt</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>SG</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loraine</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Integrated Genome Browser: free software for distribution and exploration of genome-scale datasets</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2730</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19654113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2759552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>