<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chem Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3127</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">chemsci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chemical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2041-6520</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2041-6539</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royal Society of Chemistry</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5523082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5523082.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5523082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5523082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28791090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c5sc01058f</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">c5sc01058f</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spatial regulation of a common precursor from two distinct genes generates metabolite diversity<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>
<fn id="fn1"><p>&#8224;Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available. See DOI: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c5sc01058f">10.1039/c5sc01058f</uri>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="SC-006-C5SC01058F-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></fn>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Chun-Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="WW">Wei-Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names initials="KS">Kenneth S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affb">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names initials="BR">Berl R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affc">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names initials="NP">Nancy P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affd">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="CCC">Clay C. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affa">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="affe">e</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="affa">
<label>a</label> Department of Pharmacology and Pharmaceutical Sciences , School of Pharmacy , University of Southern California , Los Angeles , CA 90089 , USA . Email: <email>clayw@usc.edu</email>
</aff><aff id="affb">
<label>b</label> Chemical and Biological Process Development Group , Energy and Environment Directorate , Pacific Northwest National Laboratory , Richland , WA 99352 , USA </aff><aff id="affc">
<label>c</label> Department of Molecular Biosciences , University of Kansas , Lawrence , KS 66045 , USA </aff><aff id="affd">
<label>d</label> Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology , University of Wisconsin-Madison , Madison , WI 53706 , USA </aff><aff id="affe">
<label>e</label> Department of Chemistry , College of Letters, Arts, and Sciences , University of Southern California , Los Angeles , CA 90089 , USA </aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">295032</issue-id><fpage>5913</fpage><lpage>5921</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-17 01:25:20.490"><day>17</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>This journal is &#169; The Royal Society of Chemistry 2015</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="SC-006-C5SC01058F.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="ga" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-ga.jpg"/>We have demonstrated that spatial regulation of the same product from two distinct genes generates metabolite diversity.</p></abstract><abstract><p>In secondary metabolite biosynthesis, core synthetic genes such as polyketide synthase genes usually encode proteins that generate various backbone precursors. These precursors are modified by other tailoring enzymes to yield a large variety of different secondary metabolites. The number of core synthesis genes in a given species correlates, therefore, with the number of types of secondary metabolites the organism can produce. In our study, heterologous expression of all the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> NRPS-like genes showed that two NRPS-like proteins, encoded by <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, release the same natural product, aspulvinone E. In hyphae this compound is converted to aspulvinones whereas in conidia it is converted to melanin. The genes are expressed in different tissues and this spatial control is probably regulated by their own specific promoters. Comparative genomics indicates that <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> might share a same ancestral gene and the gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is located in a highly conserved region in <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> species that contains genes coding for life-essential proteins. Our data reveal the first case in secondary metabolite biosynthesis in which the tissue specific production of a single compound directs it into two separate pathways, producing distinct compounds with different functions. Our data also reveal that a single <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-prenyltransferase, AbpB, prenylates two substrates, aspulvinones and butyrolactones, revealing that genes outside of contiguous secondary metabolism gene clusters can modify more than one compound thereby expanding metabolite diversity. Our study raises the possibility of incorporation of spatial, cell-type specificity in expression of secondary metabolites of biological interest and provides new insight into designing and reconstituting their biosynthetic pathways.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Filamentous fungi, such as species found within the genus <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic>, are well known producers of secondary metabolites (SMs) with interesting biological activities. The genome sequencing of <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> species revealed that the number of putative SM genes greatly exceeds the number of identified SMs, suggesting many novel types of SMs still remain to be discovered.<sup><xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> In general, these SM genes are clustered in the genome.<sup><xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> A typical cluster contains one key gene required for the synthesis of the precursor skeleton. These genes usually encode large multidomain enzymes belonging to the polyketide synthase (PKS) or non-ribosomal peptide synthetase (NRPS) class.<sup><xref rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Other adjacent genes encode enzymes that are involved in tailoring modifications, transport of the product, or co-regulation of the cluster genes.<sup><xref rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> In a given fungal species, the SM arsenal is usually governed by the number of key synthetic genes in the genome, and this diversity is multiplied by various tailoring enzymes that give rise to a considerable number of different natural products.<sup><xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> For instance, the fungus <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> has 27 PKS genes, 12 NRPS genes, 14 NRPS-like genes and one PKS/NRPS hybrid gene.<sup><xref rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> In a previous study, Ahuja <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> systematically characterized the polyketide products of eight non reducing PKSs (NR-PKSs) in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic>.<sup><xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> In combination with the six previously characterized NR-PKS genes, the study demonstrated that the 14 NR-PKS genes in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> could be divided into seven groups based on phylogenetic analysis. More importantly, each of these NR-PKSs produces a unique product which can be modified by other tailoring enzymes and incorporate into various SM biosynthetic pathways, indicating the potential of <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> for biosynthesizing a large variety of different PKS-derived SMs.<sup><xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>
</p><p>Recently, application of an efficient gene targeting system enabled us to link two NRPS-like genes <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">btyA</italic> to their corresponding SMs, aspulvinones and butyrolactones, respectively, in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> strain NIH 2624.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In this study, we demonstrated that one NRPS-like gene, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>, is involved in the synthesis of a brown conidial melanin in this fungus.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Compared to typical NRPSs, NRPS-like genes encode single module (A-T-TE) proteins missing the condensation (C) domain.<sup><xref rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The adenylation (A) domain is responsible for aryl acid substrate recognition and activation. The activated substrate is loaded onto the thiolation (T) domain. The thioesterase (TE) domain is suggested to be involved in the condensation and releasing of the final product.<sup><xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Therefore, the diversity of NRPS-like products is expanded by a combination of different A domains (substrate selection and activation) and TE domains (various cyclization and release mechanisms). The <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> genome contains 14 NRPS-like genes with predicted A-T-TE or similar domain architecture and the SM products for the majority of these are unknown.</p><p>Here we report our efforts to systematically characterize the products of these 14 NRPS-like genes. We heterologously expressed each gene in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> under the control of the inducible <italic toggle="yes">alcA</italic> promoter. Surprisingly, our study reveals that two NRPS-like genes, <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>, are responsible for the formation of the same intermediate, aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The aspulvinone E produced by AtmelA is further modified by a tyrosinase, AtmelB, and is incorporated into the brown melanin biosynthesis pathway in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). In parallel, the aspulvinone E synthesized by ApvA is further prenylated by a <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-prenyltransferase (AbpB) to produce aspulvinones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). AbpB also prenylates butyrolactones, and this reveals that modifying genes outside of specific clusters can be responsible for modifying compounds from more than one SM gene cluster, thus expanding the diversity of SMs produced by an organism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>(A) AtmelA and ApvA may synthesize the identical natural product <bold>1</bold> accumulated in different fungal tissues. (B) A <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-prenyltransferase, AbpB, prenylates two substrates, aspulvinones and butyrolactones.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-f1.jpg"/></fig><p>Our results suggest that the promoter of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> drives expression in hyphae resulting in the production of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>), which is modified to produce aspulvinone variants. The <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> promoter drives expression in conidia, also resulting in the production of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) but in this cell type it is converted to melanin. Further genetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> indicates that these two genes may share a common ancestral gene. The gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, which may result from duplication of the ancestral gene, is inserted in a genomic region consisting of genes that codes for life-essential proteins. Our study suggests an unprecedented pathway for conidial pigment biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> that incorporates an NRPS-like product aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) as its substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Our data also demonstrated how the SM diversity can be expanded by (1) allocating the same natural product in different fungal compartments to produce molecules with different functions; (2) encoding tailoring enzyme that is capable of chemically modifying more than one type of SMs.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Heterologous expression of the NRPS-like genes <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> both result in aspulvinone E production</title><p>Using a recently reported efficient heterologous expression (HE) system in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic>,<sup><xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> the individual NRPS-like genes identified in the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> genome were expressed at either the <italic toggle="yes">wA</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">yA</italic> locus of <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> under regulation of the inducible <italic toggle="yes">alcA</italic> promoter (Fig. S1A<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). In a previous study, targeted deletion of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> depleted production of aspulvinones in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> indicating that this NRPS-like gene is responsible for the biosynthesis of the aspulvinone core.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> As expected, heterologous expression of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> results in accumulation of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) which is speculated to be the first intermediate in the aspulvinone pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2A and B</xref>).<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Unexpectedly, our HE experiments revealed that AtmelA produces the same compound (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A and B</xref>). The gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is responsible for aspulvinone biosynthesis while <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> is involved in the synthesis of the brown conidial pigment.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The brown conidial melanin is still produced in the <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> deletant strain as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>. In contrast, deletion of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> generates an albino mutant that is still capable of synthesizing aspulvinones.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Together, these data reveal that despite having the same activity (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> synthesis of aspulvinone E), ApvA and AtmelA function in different roles in the fungus.</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>(A) Compounds related to this study. (B) HPLC profiles of extracts of HE strains as detected by total scan UV.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-f2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>(A) Phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> wild type and other <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> mutant strains growing on LCMM for 5 days. Morphological change of the fungal conidia can be observed if the deleted genes are involved in the biosynthesis of the brown conidial pigment. Total extracts (B), conidial extracts (C) and hyphal extracts (D) of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> wild type and mutant strains as detected by UV at 370 nm. Aspulvinone related natural products are labeled in red. In B&#8211;D, the black box represents the top layer agar as described in tissue-specific extraction. The green box represents the bottom layer agar in tissue-specific extraction. The numbering of the peaks corresponds to the natural products shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>. The aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) and its related natural products can be detected in LC/MS traces Bi, Bii, Biii, Ciii, Di, Dii, and Diii. Trace amount of <bold>1</bold> identified in D iii is due to the diffusion of this compound synthesized in the conidia of the mutant strain. *This metabolite is related with aspulvinones according to its UV absorption and MS spectrum.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-f3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Aspulvinone E occurs as a precursor in both aspulvinone and melanin pathways</title><p>To test our hypothesis that the aspulvinone E is an intermediate in two different pathways, the aspulvinone pathway and melanin pathway, we wished to delete the first tailoring gene in each pathway to accumulate the precursor produced by the gene responsible for the backbone metabolite. Since we have established the genetic linkage between <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and aspulvinones,<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> we set out to identify the first tailoring enzyme, which we presumed was responsible for prenylating <bold>1</bold> to give <bold>2</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). However, we could not locate a prenyl transferase (PT) gene proximal to <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> We then targeted each of the putative PT genes in the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> genome for deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The individual genes were knocked out using fragments created by fusion PCR.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The SM profiles of the correct mutants were examined by LC-MS, and of the 11 different mutants, only the ATEG_01730.1&#916; strain accumulated aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). Unexpectedly, removal of ATEG_01730.1 leads to the accumulation of butyrolactone II (<bold>5</bold>) as well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). A previous study showed that the NRPS-like gene <italic toggle="yes">btyA</italic> is responsible for the biosynthesis of butyrolactone core.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The expression of three genes, <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">btyA</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">abpB</italic> were also analyzed using real-time quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR). (Fig. S2C<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>) Our data showed that these three genes are co-expressed under aspulvinone and butyrolactone producing conditions. These pieces of evidence suggest that this single PT is responsible for the prenylation of two different metabolites, aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) and butyrolactone II (<bold>5</bold>). Thus, we name the gene <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> (aspulvinone) <italic toggle="yes">b</italic> (butyrolactone) <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> (PT) <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>HPLC profiles of extracts of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> prenyltransferase (PT) genes deletants as detected by UV at 330 nm and 370 nm. The numbering of the peaks corresponds to the natural products shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>. Compounds <bold>3</bold> and <bold>4</bold> are prenylated derivatives of compound <bold>5</bold>. The &#8220;*&#8221; compound is an aspulvinone derivative according to its UV absorption spectrum. ATXXXXX is abbreviated for &#8220;ATEG_XXXXX.1&#8221;. Deletion of the gene ATEG_00702.1, a homolog of <italic toggle="yes">tdiB</italic> involved in the asterriquinone biosynthesis, was not achieved due to the unsuccessful PCR amplification of its flanking region.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-f4.jpg"/></fig><p>Definitively establishing the role of AtmelA in the synthesis of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) required additional gene deletion experiments. We first deleted the gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> using the direct repeat (DR) strategy<sup><xref rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> followed by the recycling of the <italic toggle="yes">AfpyrG</italic> marker (Fig. S1B<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). This ensures that aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) identified in the later mutants is not from ApvA. However, limited information is available about the biosynthesis of the brown conidial melanin in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>. Our study suggests that the melanin pathway originates from the NRPS-like product aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>), which is unlike the two main precursors [di-hydroxyphenylalanin (DOPA) and dihydroxynaphthalene (DHN)] of currently known melanins.<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The biosynthesis of DOPA melanin starts with a tyrosine that is oxidized to either DOPA or dopaquinone (DAQ) by a tyrosinase.<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Considering that aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) shares the same phenol moiety as tyrosine, we speculate that a similar tyrosinase might catalyze the hydroxylation of <bold>1</bold> at the <italic toggle="yes">ortho</italic> position to give a dihydroxylated intermediate that becomes incorporated into the brown melanin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Following the cluster paradigm, we examined the genes surrounding <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and identified one gene ATEG_03564.1 (<italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic>) that encodes a putative tyrosinase. Removal of this gene in the <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916; background changed the strain's phenotype: the brown melanin was no longer synthesized and the conidia became bright yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). As expected, the yellow material is aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>), which accumulated in the metabolite profiles of the <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic> double deletion strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). We next deleted the gene <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> in the double <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic>&#916; strain. The LC-MS profile of this triple deletion mutant shows the abrogation of the aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) which had reappeared in the double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>), in accord with our HE results that AtmelA was also capable of producing Aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) produced by ApvA and AtmelA accumulates in different fungal tissues</title><p>Our studies indicate that ApvA and AtmelA synthesize the same product aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>). We next asked how the fungus is able to allocate the same chemical synthesized by different proteins into their own specific pathway without cross-interference. Previous literature reports have shown that the production of SMs and/or their precursors can be specific to both cellular organelle and fungal tissue.<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> We speculated that the aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) from the two genes might be generated in different fungal tissues. Since removal of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic> changes the phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> conidia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>), it is likely that aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) from AtmelA might be produced in conidia. Likewise aspulvinones, derived from <bold>1</bold> that is produced by ApvA, might be produced inside the hyphae and secreted into the medium.</p><p>To test this hypothesis, we performed tissue-specific extraction<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> to reinvestigate the SM profiles of the four strains ((1) wild type; (2) <italic toggle="yes">abpB</italic>&#916;; (3) <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic>&#916;; (4) <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>&#916;). Fungal cultures were divided into three fractions: (1) conidial (mostly conidia and minor conidiophore), (2) top layer agar (mixture of conidiophore, vegetative hyphae, minor invasive hyphae), (3) lower layer agar (mostly invasive hyphae) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C and D</xref>). Compared to the SM profiles of total extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>), extraction of the conidia showed the accumulation of <bold>1</bold> only in the <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic>&#916; strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), not in strains carrying <italic toggle="yes">abpB</italic>&#916; or <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>&#916;. This result indicates that aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) from AtmelA is produced in conidia. Extraction of the hyphal (mostly invasive) fraction showed the production of <bold>1</bold> in the <italic toggle="yes">abpB</italic>&#916; strain and compound <bold>2</bold> in wild type, indicating that aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) from ApvA and its derivative <bold>2</bold> are specifically produced in hyphae.</p></sec><sec><title>Exchanging <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, under control of the <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> promoter, restores melanin production in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>
</title><p>Next, we asked about the molecular mechanism for regulating the tissue-specific production of <bold>1</bold>. We first examined the expression profiling of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> in different tissues using Real-Time qRT-PCR (Fig. S2, see ESI<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref> for experimental details). As expected, the gene <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> is specifically expressed in conidia compartment (Fig. S2B<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>) while the gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is locally expressed in hyphae (Fig. S2C<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). We then probed this question by determining whether ApvA could replace AtmelA in brown melanin biosynthesis. We assumed that tailoring enzymes like AtmelB could still recognize aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) generated from either ApvA or AtmelA. Another study suggests that the products of two tubulin genes, <italic toggle="yes">benA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">tubC</italic>, are functionally interchangeable. The method they used was to disrupt <italic toggle="yes">benA</italic> and then put <italic toggle="yes">tubC</italic> under control of the <italic toggle="yes">benA</italic> promoter.<sup><xref rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Herein we implemented a similar strategy by replacing the coding region of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> with that of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, placing <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> under control of the <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> promoter (<italic toggle="yes">atmelAp</italic>) in the <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916; background (Fig. S1Ci<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>, the mutant stain (<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>) produces brownish conidia indicating that the brown conidial pigment is produced in the mutant strain (<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>). As anticipated, the production of aspulvinones (<bold>1</bold> or <bold>2</bold>) were not detected (Fig. S3<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). The pigment is not produced as much as in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>) probably because <italic toggle="yes">atmelAp</italic>, after all, is not the native promoter of ApvA. Quantitative analysis of their expression using Real-Time qRT-PCR reveals that the expression level of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, which is under the control of atmelA promoter, is lower than that of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>. (Fig. S2B<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>) This could be one of the reasons for reduced production of the conidial melanin in the mutant strain (<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>). But more importantly, our experiment shows that compound <bold>1</bold> from <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> can be incorporated into the melanin pathway when <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is regulated by <italic toggle="yes">atmelAp</italic>. As mentioned earlier, the production of <bold>1</bold> from <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> is conidia-specific. Thus, this experiment shows that the product of ApvA can also be produced inside conidia and incorporated into melanin, suggesting that the tissue specific allocation of their products may be due to cell-type specific expression of the genes <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> under regulation of their specific promoters.</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>(A) Phenotype of the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> mutant strain <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> (the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> wild type is used as positive control that produces melanin, the <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>&#916; strain is used as negative control). (B) Replacing <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic>. Top column: conidia. Bottom column: hyphae. Top row: GFP. Middle row: differential interference contrast (DIC). Bottom row: merged GFP.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="c5sc01058f-f5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Tissue specific expression of <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> occurs when the coding sequence of <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> replaces <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>
</title><p>To test our hypothesis, we generated two mutants (<italic toggle="yes">atmelAp-gfp</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">apvAp-gfp</italic>) in which the coding regions of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> were replaced by the green fluorescent protein coding sequence (<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic>), placing <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> under control of their specific promoters (Fig. S1Cii<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). Both the melanin pathway and aspulvinones biosynthetic pathways are active when <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> is cultivated on LCMM agar. Under this culture condition, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">atmelAp</italic> would turn on the expression of <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> specifically inside the conidia while the <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> regulated by <italic toggle="yes">apvAp</italic> would display a green fluorescent signal in the hyphae. As expected, we were able to visualize localization of GFP within the conidia only in the strain carrying <italic toggle="yes">atmelAp-gfp</italic> but not in the parental strain (used as control) or the strain <italic toggle="yes">apvAp-gfp</italic>. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>) In comparison, hyphal localization of GFP fluorescence was observed only in strain <italic toggle="yes">apvAp-gfp</italic>. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>) Thus, the tissue specific accumulation of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) is probably due to cell-type-specific expression of the two genes <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study suggests that metabolite diversity can be expanded by spatial regulation of the same precursor biosynthesized by two distinct genes. Melanin plays an important role in fungal pathogenesis as well as in the protection of the producing organisms from ultraviolet radiation.<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> No definite structures for melanins have been elucidated due to their large molecular weight, insolubility in aqueous or organic solvents, and heterogeneity.<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The characterized conidial melanin of most <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> species belongs to the dihydroxynaphthalene (DHN) melanin class.<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Our study reports a unique and unprecedented pathway of conidial pigment biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> that originates from the NRPS-like product aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). We also identified one putative tyrosinase encoded by the gene <italic toggle="yes">atmelB</italic> that is involved in a tailoring modification of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) to yield the brown conidial pigment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). We speculate that the function of the tyrosinase, AtmelB, might resemble that of its homolog which participates in dihydroxyphenylalanine (DOPA)-melanin biosynthesis<sup><xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and catalyzes the <italic toggle="yes">ortho</italic> hydroxylation of the phenol moiety in the aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). It is entirely possible that other genes are involved in the polymerization of the dual hydroxylated aspulvinone E and more efforts will be needed to decipher the complete biosynthetic pathway of the brown conidial melanin in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>.</p><p>Compounds in the aspulvinone family have been found to have anti-influenza A viral (H1N1) activity and are potent inhibitors of firefly luciferase.<sup><xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> The production of aspulvinones, as revealed in a previous study, is a general stress response of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>.<sup><xref rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> The biological functions of aspulvinones, and what role they play in the biology of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>, remain elusive. AtmelA shares 73% sequence similarity with ApvA. We noted that there is a 63 bp sequence in <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>, corresponding to the TE domain of AtmelA, that has strong nucleotide identity with a portion of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>, indicating that these two genes may share a common origin (Fig. S5C<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). Interestingly, homology analysis of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and its surrounding genes showed that <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is inserted into a conserved genome region consisting of genes that are essential for fungal survival (Fig. S4<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). It is possible that the insertion of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> is due to the duplication and translocation of its ancestral homolog. The production of aspulvinone-type SMs by <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>, in response to general stress, could be related to the chromosomal location of its producing gene <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>. However, more experiments are definitely necessary to elucidate the exact role the aspulvinone-type metabolites play in the growth, survival or metabolic processes of the fungus <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>.</p><p>Previous literature suggested that <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-hydroxylphenylpyruvate (HPP), which originates from the shikimate pathway, is the biosynthetic precursor of aspulvinones.<sup><xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The shikimate pathway, highly conserved in bacteria, fungi, and plant species, generates carbon skeletons for the aromatic amino acids including tryptophan, tyrosine, and phenylalanine.<sup><xref rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> HPP is proposed to be an intermediate in the conversion of prephenate to <sc>l</sc>-tyrosine in the shikimate pathway. Limited information has been reported regarding the tissue localization of HPP in fungi. Our study suggests that the distribution of HPP is not limited to certain types of fungal compartments since both the biosynthesis of brown conidial melanin and hyphae specific aspulvinones requires the presence of HPP. Our data indicate that the tissue-specific expression of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> are due to the promoters of the two genes. The promoter of <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> drives expression specifically in hyphae while the promoter of <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> drives expression in conidia. There are many examples of hyphal <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> spore specific gene regulation. For example, the expression of the melanin synthesis gene <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic> might regulated by spore specific transcriptional regulators as demonstrated in a recent study showing that BrlA, the transcription factor required to initiate conidiophore development in <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> spp., is necessary for fumiquinazoline gene expression and product production.<sup><xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> The fact that <italic toggle="yes">atmelAp</italic> is capable of turning on the expression of both <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> (SM gene) and the <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> (reporter gene), suggests that it might be a useful tool for directing the expression of genes specifically inside of conidia.</p><p>Besides spatial regulation of the intermediate, the SM diversity can be further expanded, as shown in our study, through tailoring enzymes that are capable of modifying SMs with different chemical scaffolds. Early literature reported the enzymatic characterization of aspulvinone dimethylallyltransferase in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>. This enzyme is capable of catalyzing the mono or dual prenylation of aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>).<sup><xref rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The substrate promiscuity of some PTs has also been tested <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> by feeding experiments.<sup><xref rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Our study reveals the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> versatility of AbpB, as it accepts substrates with different chemical scaffolds. Interestingly, the three genes are dispersed in the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> genome (<italic toggle="yes">abpB</italic> on chromosome II; <italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic> on chromosome III; <italic toggle="yes">btyA</italic> on chromosome IV), representing another deviation from the SM gene cluster paradigm. We have discovered in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> that in some cases, the corresponding PT genes are not located in the same cluster as the core PKS genes.<sup><xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Further comparison of the butyrolactones with aspulvinones shows that the chemical modifications after prenylation, including epoxidation and dehydrogenation, are very similar (Fig. S6<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). Thus, these two natural product families may share the same set of tailoring enzymes that specifically modifies the prenyl groups attached by AbpB.</p><p>Fungi are capable of producing a large variety of SMs with unique chemical scaffolds. It is usually expected that core synthetic genes, in a given species, are behind the biosynthesis of different core intermediates, as demonstrated in a study showing that all individual NRPKS in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> generate a unique PKS product.<sup><xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Phylogenetic analysis, using the protein sequences of those NRPS-like homologs obtained from the Broad Institute <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> comparative database, revealed several other characterized NRPS-like homologs including TdiA (terrequinone A biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic>),<sup><xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> RalA (ralfuranone biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Ralstonia solanacearum</italic>),<sup><xref rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> MicA (microperfuranone biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic>),<sup><xref rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> AtqA (asterriquinone biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>),<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> BtyA (butyrolactone biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>),<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> and EchA (echosides biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic> sp. LZ35)<sup><xref rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> (Fig. S5<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). These NRPS-like enzymes, with A-T-TE domain architecture, fall within Clade I of the phylogenetic tree (Fig. S5<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>). They are capable of synthesizing natural products with various chemical scaffolds using similar substrates like phenylpyruvic acid. Previous literature suggested that these pyruvic acid substrates could be produced <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the shikimate pathway.<sup><xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> The TE domains are proposed to catalyze various condensation, cyclization and releasing reactions to yield different chemical backbones.<sup><xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In comparison, another characterized NRPS-like protein (encoded by ATEG_03630.1), with A-T-R domain arrangement, belongs to Clade V (Fig. S5<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>).<sup><xref rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> In this case, the aryl acid substrate, generated by an adjacent PKS (encoded by ATEG_03629.1), is loaded onto the A domain and is reduced to its aryl-aldehyde precursor by the R domain. Thus, SM diversity is enriched from these disparate starting points. It is also common to identify two highly homologous core synthetic genes, in different species, that produces the same precursor. For example, in the biosynthesis of the meroterpenoids austinol (<italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic>) and terretonin (<italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic>), the two PKS genes <italic toggle="yes">ausA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">trt4</italic> synthesize the same intermediate 3, 5-dimethylorsellinic acid.<sup><xref rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our work indicates that chemical diversity in SM biosynthesis can be expanded <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> multiple dimensions. Prior to our work, the richness of the fungal SM pool was presumed to be determined by the number of SM gene clusters while the clustered genes are associated with the biosynthesis of a distinct type of SM, with some exceptions.<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> In our study, we have shown that <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> deploys an additional strategy to enrich its natural product pool. Although the same precursor aspulvinone E (<bold>1</bold>) is shared in two pathways (the aspulvinone pathway, a typical SM pathway and the melanin pathway, producing a self-protection pigment that might also be involved in the pathogenicity of this fungus), the tissue specific expression of their biosynthetic genes results in the production of the same compound in different fungal tissues and allows it to be modified into two different products that, we assume, confer selective advantages in the specific tissues in which they are produced. The localization of production is possibly regulated by their specific promoters, but it is entirely possible that a more complex regulatory mechanism underlies this phenomenon. This expands our insight into spatial regulation of SMs in fungi.<sup><xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> More investigation into these promoters might provide a means to the cell-type-directed biosynthesis of SMs or manipulating the location of the expression of some genes responsible for products with interesting biological activities. Finally, our data demonstrate that AbpB prenylates compounds in two pathways revealing that two pathways may share the same tailoring genes. It will be of interest to determine if this characteristic is common to, and specific to, prenyl transferases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Strains and molecular manipulations</title><p>Primers used in this study are listed in Table S1.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref> The fungal strains used in this study are listed in Table S2.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref> The scheme for heterologously expressing the NRPS-like genes of <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> is shown in Fig. S1.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref> The direct repeat (DR) deletion and <italic toggle="yes">AfpyG</italic> marker recycling experimental design is shown in Fig. S1.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref> The construction of fusion PCR products, protoplast generation, and transformation were carried out as previously described.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The scheme of diagnostic PCR is shown in Fig. S8.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>
</p><p>For real time qRT-PCR, the <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> wild type strain and the mutant strain (<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>&#916;, <italic toggle="yes">atmelA</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">apvA</italic>) were cultivated on LCMM agar for mRNA extraction from conidia. The <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> wild type strain was cultivated in LCMM liquid broth for mRNA extraction from hyphae. Total mRNA was extracted by using the Qiagen RNeasy Plant Mini Kit. The cDNA was made from the equal amount of mRNA. The expression of every gene was analyzed with the ABI 7900HT Fast Real-Time PCR system (see ESI for experimental details<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">&#8224;</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Fermentation and LC-MS analysis</title><p>(1) <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> strain LO4389 and other HE mutant strains were cultivated at 37 &#176;C in 50 ml LMM liquid medium (6 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> NaNO<sub>3</sub>, 0.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> KCl, 0.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 1.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 20 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> lactose supplemented with 1 ml l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> of trace element solution) at 1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> spore per ml per 125 ml flask with shaking at 180 rpm. The nutrients uridine, uracil, pyridoxine and riboflavin were supplemented if necessary. As previously reported,<sup><xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> 44 &#956;l (10 mM) cyclopentanone was added into the medium after 18 h of incubation. The incubator temperature was then changed to 30 &#176;C and the culture medium was collected 72 h after cyclopentanone induction. The medium was filtrated and extracted twice with ethyl acetate (EtOAc, 50 ml). Preparation of the HPLC-MS samples and the condition for MS analysis were as previously described.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</p><p>(2) For the prenyltransferase screening experiment, <italic toggle="yes">A. terreus</italic> NIH 2624 and the mutant strains were point inoculated at 30 &#176;C on LCMM agar plates (6 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> NaNO<sub>3</sub>, 0.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> KCl, 0.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 1.52 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 10 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup>
<sc>d</sc>-glucose, 20 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> lactose, 15 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> agar supplemented with 1 ml l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> of trace element solution) per plate (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = 10 cm). After 5 days, agar was chopped into small pieces and extracted with 50 ml MeOH followed by 60 ml 1&#8201;:&#8201;1 CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>/MeOH. The extract was evaporated <italic toggle="yes">in vacuo</italic> to yield a water residue, which was suspended in 25 ml H<sub>2</sub>O and partitioned with 25 ml EtOAc, twice. Preparation of the HPLC-MS samples and the condition for MS analysis were the same as previously described.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</p><p>(3) For the extraction of different fungal tissues for aspulvinone production, the procedure was similar to a previously reported procedure.<sup><xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Plates containing 20 ml LCMM agar (1.5% agar) were overlaid with another 10 ml of LCMM agar (0.75% agar). Plates were point inoculated with wild type or the DR mutant strains and grown at 30 &#176;C for 4 days. Conidia were harvested by adding 7 ml salt solution (8.5 g l<sup>&#8211;1</sup> NaCl) followed by gently scraping with a sterile spreader. The conidial solution was inspected under the microscope to be largely free of hyphae and conidiophores. The conidial fraction was sonicated for 1 h and extracted twice with an equal volume of EtOAc. The top layer was then washed with 10 ml sterile water twice and removed with a sterile spatula. The bottom agar layer was then chopped into small pieces and extracted as previously described. Preparation of the HPLC-MS samples from different tissues and the conditions for MS analysis were as previously described.<sup><xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of secondary metabolites</title><p>For scale up, <italic toggle="yes">A. nidulans</italic> HE strains were cultivated at 37 &#176;C in 1 liter LMM liquid medium (&#8764;100 ml per flask) at 1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> spores per ml with shaking at 180 rpm. The nutrients uridine, uracil, pyridoxine and riboflavin were supplemented if necessary. To induce expression, 88 &#956;l cyclopentanone was added into the medium after 18 h of incubation. The incubator temperature was then changed to 30 &#176;C and the culture medium was collected 72 h after cyclopentanone induction. The medium was filtrated and extracted three times with equal volume of EtOAc. The combined EtOAc layers were evaporated to a crude extract. Further purification of fractions with targeted compounds was carried out by gradient HPLC on a C18 reverse phase column [Phenomenex Luna 5 &#956;m C18, 250 &#215; 10 mm] with a flow rate of 5.0 ml min<sup>&#8211;1</sup> and measured by a UV detector at 254 nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence microscopy</title><p>The wild type and two mutant strains (<italic toggle="yes">atmelAp-gfp</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">apvAp-gfp</italic>) were cultivated on the two-layer agar plates as mentioned. Plates were point inoculated with wild type or the mutant strains and grown at 30 &#176;C for 5 days. The conidia were collected as previously described and the conidial solution was diluted 10 times with sterile water. A 10 &#956;l portion of the diluted solution was placed on a pre-cleaned microscope slide and covered with a coverslip. For imaging of the hyphal GFP fluorescence signal, the top layer was removed as previously described. A small portion of hyphae containing agar (&lt;10 &#956;l) was placed on a pre-cleaned microscope slide and covered with a coverslip. All the samples were examined under an optical microscope to confirm that the conidia and hyphae could be clearly visualized. Images were taken with a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta NLO (Thornwood, NY) confocal imaging system equipped with Argon, red HeNe, and green HeNe lasers and a Coherent Chameleon Ti&#8211;Sapphire laser mounted on a vibration-free table.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr James F. Sanchez, Dr Yi-Ming Chiang, and Dr Shu-Lin Chang for their insightful discussion. Chun-Jun Guo was supported by the National Science Foundation &#8211; Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation-MIKS (Grant 1136903). Research conducted in the lab of Clay C. C. Wang is supported by the National Institute of General Medical Sciences GM084077, the National Science Foundation &#8211; Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation-MIKS (Grant 1136903), the Department of Energy, Bioenergy Technologies office, the Department of Defense Strategic Environmental Research and Development program (SERDP), and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration Space Biology program.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="cit1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaldi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifuddin</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nierman</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>736</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20554054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fgb.2010.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2916752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>937</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrmicro1286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2006</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>3468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16895337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/cr0503097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelkar</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8643646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.93.4.1418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC39953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Praseuth</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>H.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>8212</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22510154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ja3016395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3357392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>von D&#246;hren</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>S45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fgb.2008.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Org. Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>3562</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23841722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ol401384v</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3833251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balibar</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard-Jones</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17704773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nchembio.2007.20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>7720</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23621425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ja401945a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3697937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>U. H.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>165</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17703973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fgb.2007.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Streibel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brakhage</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>143</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1087-1845(02)00526-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontoyiannis</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beebe</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huttenlocher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e1003289</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23592999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3623715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cell. Microbiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24612080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/cmi.12284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4114987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2267</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2681229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.109.5.2267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2115864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fgb.2003.11.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenman</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casadevall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>931</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22173481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00253-011-3777-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4318813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Pichel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>791</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21963801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrmicro2649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1776</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23411074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bmcl.2013.01.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auld</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaile</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacArthur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamayo-Castillo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inglese</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22118678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chembiol.2011.08.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3225805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit20"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <year>2006</year>, http://hdl.handle.net/1721.1/37692.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Pharm. Bull.</source><year>1983</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1528</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewick</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>1984</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6399353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/np9840100451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoefgen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>62</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpls.2013.00062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3608921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojima</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1978</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2696</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">678538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi00606a037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>737</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21643703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00253-011-3351-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaegashi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>4010</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21351751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ja1096682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3119361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>4709</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22329759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ja209809t</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3350773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wackler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>354</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21439480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chembiol.2011.01.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>H.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T.-K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>739</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22627757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00253-012-4098-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3713075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Gene</source><year>2014</year><volume>546</volume><fpage>352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24865933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gene.2014.05.053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Knaggs</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12636087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/b100399m</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Pharm. Bull.</source><year>1990</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>2929</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beissner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>257</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24412543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chembiol.2013.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3943900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>H.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Org. Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5684</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23116177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ol302682z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3538129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiemann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekonyela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>17065</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24082142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1313258110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3801025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25142354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c4np00083h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4162804</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>