<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6710492</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6710492.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6710492</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6710492</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31463387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e02221</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(19)35881-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e02221</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Turbidity matters: differential effect of a 2,4-D formulation on the structure of microbial communities from clear and turbid freshwater systems</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names initials="VL">V.L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names initials="CE">C.E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinocur</surname><given-names initials="AL">A.L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names initials="C">C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unrein</surname><given-names initials="F">F.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolansky</surname><given-names initials="MJ">M.J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names initials="HN">H.N.</given-names></name><email>hay@ege.fcen.uba.ar</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Universidad de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Departamento de Ecolog&#237;a, Gen&#233;tica y Evoluci&#243;n, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>CONICET, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Instituto de Ecolog&#237;a, Gen&#233;tica y Evoluci&#243;n de Buenos Aires (IEGEBA), Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Universidad de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Depto. de Biodiversidad y Biolog&#237;a Experimental, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Centro de Investigaciones Agua y Saneamientos Argentinos, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Instituto Tecnol&#243;gico de Chascom&#250;s (INTECH), UNSAM-CONICET, Chascom&#250;s, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>CONICET, Instituto de Qu&#237;mica Biol&#243;gica de la Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales (IQUIBICEN), Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Universidad de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Departamento de Qu&#237;mica Biol&#243;gica, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. <email>hay@ege.fcen.uba.ar</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">340022</issue-id><elocation-id>e02221</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>08</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>08</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-02 16:25:31.800"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2019 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We evaluated the effect of AsiMax 50&#174;, a commercial formulation of 2,4-D (2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid), on the structure of both micro + nano phytoplankton (&gt;2 &#956;m; species composition and abundance) and cytometric populations (photosynthetic picoplankton (PPP, 0.2&#8211;2 &#956;m), which included prokaryotic phycocyanin-rich picocyanobacteria (PC-Pcy), phycoerythrin-rich picocyanobacteria (PE-Pcy) and eukaryotic phototrophs (PEuk); and bacterioplankton (HB), heterotrophic bacteria), using a microcosms-based approach and a single 7-day exposure. Assays were performed on two different microbial assemblages sampled from freshwater bodies of two contrasting turbidity status: clear (chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> = 7.6 &#956;gL<sup>-1</sup>, turbidity = 1 NTU) and organic turbid systems (chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> = 25.0 &#956;gL<sup>-1</sup>, turbidity = 9 NTU). For each system, the herbicide was applied to 500 mL-Erlenmeyer flasks, at seven concentration levels of the active ingredient (a.i.): 0 (control = no addition), 0.02, 0.2, 2, 20, 200 and 2,000 mg a.i.L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. The impact of AsiMax 50&#174; seemed to be greater in the turbid system. In this system, total abundance of living (live) micro + nano phytoplankton showed a significant increase at lower concentrations and data were fitted to a humped-shaped curve. For both clear and organic turbid systems, micro + nano phytoplankton decreased in species richness and abundance at higher herbicide concentrations. These results suggest that 2,4-D may mimic hormonal function. Some species, such as <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp., showed different responses to herbicide exposure between water systems. In the turbid system, the increase in abundance of the PPP fraction observed at 7-d exposure was probably due to either an increase in PE-Pcy (thus suggesting the existence of auxin pathways) or a reduction in competitive pressure by micro + nano plankton. Our results provide some evidence of the importance of using community-scale approaches in ecotoxicological studies to predict changes in freshwater ecosystems exposed to a 2,4-D-based formulation. However, caution must be taken when extrapolating these effects to real scenarios, as assays were based on a laboratory microcosm experiment.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ecology toxicology</kwd><kwd>2,4-D</kwd><kwd>Organic turbidity</kwd><kwd>Microbial communities</kwd><kwd>Freshwater ecosystems</kwd><kwd>Microcosms</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">With the advent of genetically modified crops and the introduction of no-till methods, herbicides have become the &#8220;stars&#8221; of the chemicals used in industrial agriculture. Currently, glyphosate-based herbicides, whose main mode of action is through the disruption of aromatic amino acid biosynthesis (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Amrhein et&#160;al., 1980</xref>), are used worldwide, while other herbicides are applied as complementary tools for weed control. Herbicides have several different modes of action (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Peterson et&#160;al., 2015</xref>). Auxinic herbicides, which belong to a chemical family largely used in agriculture, mimic the biphasic effects of indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), which is the principal natural auxin in higher plants. It usually stimulates growth by cell division and elongation when targeted to cell sites of action at low concentration (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Grossmann, 2010</xref>). Auxin-derived herbicides such as phenoxy hormone products were used in an average of 22,916 tons worldwide between 1990-2002. The use of these herbicides was reported to increase an average of 30,436 tons of active ingredients between 2003-2014 (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">FAOSTAT, 2018</xref>). After more than 2 decades of glyphosate massive spraying in Argentina, the use of herbicides such as 2,4-D, paraquat and dicamba has sky-rocketed in the last years to prevent the spread of glyphosate resistance in target weeds. The 2,4-D was the third most imported herbicide into Argentina between 2013 and 2015 (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">SENASA, 2018</xref>), and now it is considered one of the most used agrochemicals worldwide (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Singh and Singh, 2016</xref>). Moreover, plants genetically modified to tolerate different herbicides, including 2,4-D, were recently approved for commercial production in Argentina (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">CONABIA, 2019</xref>). Under this scenario, 2,4-D application rates are expected to increase in Argentina.</p><p id="p0015">The 2,4-D (2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid) is an auxin-type selective herbicide that induces overgrowth of vascular cambium in dicotyledonous, ultimately leading to death (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Song, 2014</xref>). After application, it is transformed by bacterial metabolic pathways, such as the tricarboxylic acid cycle (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Singh and Singh, 2016</xref>). The persistence of 2,4-D in the environment depends on the availability of other carbon sources involved in microbial metabolism, its half-life being between 20 and 312 days (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Islam et&#160;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">Build-up of 2,4-D residues may cause important alterations in soil and aquatic ecosystems. The 2,4-D can produce disruptive effects in fungi (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bernat et&#160;al., 2018</xref>), insects (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#160;al., 2018</xref>), amphibians (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">LaChapelle et&#160;al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Aronzon et&#160;al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Van Meter et&#160;al., 2018</xref>), fish (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dehnert et&#160;al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">De Arcaute et&#160;al., 2018</xref>), and others (Islam et a. 2018). Other studies reported the effect of pure 2,4-D on microbial communities (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kobraei and White, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aguayo et&#160;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lozano et&#160;al., 2018</xref>), but little is known about the collateral impact of commercial formulations of this herbicide on wild biota in agricultural landscapes. These commercial formulations consist of the active ingredient (2,4-D), water and inert elements such as solvents, surfactants and humectants of unknown composition which increase plant cuticle permeability to 2,4-D (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lanct&#244;t et&#160;al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">The 2,4-D has different effects according to its concentration: low concentrations stimulate the growth of some phytoplanktonic species, whereas high concentrations inhibit their development (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Boyle, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kobraei and White, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Wong, 2000</xref>). In regard to other freshwater communities, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">De Lipthay et&#160;al. (2003)</xref> reported that low concentrations of the active ingredient (a.i.) (&lt;40 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) modify the structure of the bacterial community from a shallow aquifer, leading to an increase in 2,4-D degrading bacteria. In addition, an increase in Actinobacteria growth was detected at 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D in an oligotrophic lake (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aguayo et&#160;al., 2014</xref>), which resulted from the ability of <italic toggle="yes">Arthrobacter</italic> sp. to use 2,4-D and other aromatic compounds as sources of carbon and energy (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Sandmann and Loos, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Westerberg et&#160;al., 2000</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">It is well known that freshwater systems become contaminated either by direct spraying over water or indirectly via soil drift (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ensminger et&#160;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Aparicio et&#160;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Berman et&#160;al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Metcalfe et&#160;al., 2019</xref>). Algae and cyanobacteria from lakes, ponds and rivers share several metabolic pathways with vascular plants, suggesting that they can be similarly affected by herbicides (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Ferrari et&#160;al., 2018</xref>). Indeed, these organisms have shown to be severely altered, mainly at the population level (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Vera et&#160;al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lipok et&#160;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">P&#233;rez et&#160;al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et&#160;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Pizarro et&#160;al., 2016</xref>). They are important in freshwater ecosystems because of their role as main primary producers, either as free-living planktonic organisms or attached to diverse substrata (phyto-periphyton fraction). Taking into account the important ecosystem services supplied by freshwater systems, there is increasing concern about the deleterious effect of herbicides, as previously demonstrated for glyphosate (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">P&#233;rez et&#160;al., 2007</xref>).</p><p id="p0035">There are more than 10,000 shallow lakes in the Pampa plain of Argentina (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Dukatz et&#160;al., 2006</xref>), which is one of the most affected regions by agricultural activities worldwide. These water bodies switch between two alternative stable states with contrasting typologies (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Scheffer et&#160;al., 1993</xref>): clear-water lakes with very low phytoplankton abundance and turbid ones dominated by phytoplankton. Both states show different phytoplankton populations, as they are adapted to distinct nutrient and light conditions (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allende et&#160;al., 2009</xref>). In last decades, however, there are some evidences indicating that lakes remain turbid due to agrochemical contamination (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Quir&#243;s et&#160;al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Vera et&#160;al., 2010</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">In this work we evaluated the effect of AsiMax 50&#174;, a commercial formulation of 2,4-D, on the structure of freshwater microbial communities under different exposure conditions using microcosms. The assays were carried out with two different consolidated microbial assemblages. One of these was sampled from a clear freshwater system and the other from a turbid freshwater system. We analyzed the quali- and quantitative composition of micro + nano phytoplankton (&gt;2 &#956;m) and photosynthetic picoplankton (PPP, 0.2&#8211;2 &#956;m), which includes prokaryotic phycocyanin-rich picocyanobacteria (PC-Pcy), phycoerythrin-rich picocyanobacteria (PE-Pcy) and eukaryotic phototrophs (PEuk). Bacterioplankton (HB, heterotrophic bacteria) was also considered in the analysis}. All the microbial communities were exposed to a wide range of concentrations of the active ingredient for 7 d. We tested the following hypotheses: 1- the impact of AsiMax 50&#174; depends on water turbidity, which results from the different structure of the microbial communities; and 2- the impact of AsiMax 50&#174; depends on the 2,4-D concentration used.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="p0045">We performed a manipulative laboratory experiment with 48 microcosms, each of which consisted of a 500-mL Erlenmeyer flask filled with water (experimental unit = e.u.), taken from two outdoor water systems of contrasting turbidity status. Of these, 24 were filled with clear water (thereafter referred to as clear) and 24 with organic turbid water (thereafter referred to as turbid). The initial conditions of water samples were: chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> = 7.6 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, turbidity = 1 NTU for clear and chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> = 25.0 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, turbidity = 9 NTU for turbid. These environmental variables are usually used to characterize the shallow lakes typical of the Pampa plain from Argentina (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allende et&#160;al., 2009</xref>). Microcosms were randomly placed in a shaking chamber set at 25 &#176;C and 12:12 L:D photoperiod during the entire exposure to AsiMax 50&#174;. After a microcosm stabilization period of 3 days, the experiment started with the addition of 2,4-D as commercial formulation of AsiMax 50&#174;, randomly applied in triplicate, at seven concentration levels of the active ingredient (a.i.): 0 (control = no addition), 0.02, 0.2, 2, 20, 200 and 2,000 mg a.i. L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> to clear and turbid microcosms. The sampling scheme was as follows: a) samples were taken from 3 e.u. at zero time (T0, before addition of AsiMax 50&#174;) to determine the initial conditions of physical and chemical parameters and micro + nanophytoplankton; b) samples were taken from all treatments after 7d (Tf, final time) to determine treatment effect; c) considering the time scale at which populations of very small organisms react to an impact (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Peck, 2011</xref>), samples of PPP and HB were taken after 15 min (T1) and 7 d (Tf) of 2,4-D addition (n = 24 for both groups).</p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Physical and chemical parameters</title><p id="p0050">The real concentrations of 2,4-D were measured from water samples collected from all the e.u. and kept at -20 &#176;C for further processing. For 2,4-D determination, samples were unfrozen, homogenized and diluted 1:10 with Milli-Q water. Finally, the samples were collected in 2-mL glass vials and the analysis was performed using HPLC-UV technique coupled with UV detector at 232 nm (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">APHA, 2005</xref>). Turbidity was measured with a portable turbidimeter (Hach&#174; 2100 P).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Biological variables</title><sec id="sec2.2.1"><label>2.2.1</label><title>Chlorophyll a concentration</title><p id="p0055">For chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> determination, 200-mL water samples were filtered through Whatman&#174; GF/F filters and stored at -20 &#176;C. Chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration values were obtained by spectrophotometric absorbance, using acetone as solvent. Absorbances were read at 665 and 750 nm, before and after acidification with HCl 1 N. Before reading, samples were first left overnight in the solvent and then centrifuged at 3,000 rpm. Concentration values were obtained following <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Lilchtenthaler and Wellburn (1983)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2.2"><label>2.2.2</label><title>Micro and nano-phytoplankton (2&#8211;200 &#956;m)</title><p id="p0060">A 200-mL water sample from each e.u. was fixed with acidified Lugol's iodine solution and kept at 4 &#176;C for subsequent phytoplankton (&#707;2 &#956;m) counts. These were made according to Uterm&#246;hl's technique (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Uterm&#246;hl, 1958</xref>) to the lowest taxonomic level, distinguishing between live and dead organisms. Individuals were considered to be alive when they had an organized cell structure with undamaged chloroplasts and cell wall (e.g. frustules for diatoms), among other structures.</p><p id="p0065"><italic toggle="yes">A maximum</italic> counting error of 20% was accepted for the most abundant taxa (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Venrick, 1978</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2.3"><label>2.2.3</label><title>PPP and HB populations (&lt;2 &#956;m)</title><p id="p0070">Picoplankton, which comprised different PPP populations, and HB were analyzed using a FACSAria II (Becton Dickinson&#174;) flow cytometer equipped with a standard 15 mW blue argon-ion (488 nm emission) laser and a red laser diode (635 nm). Samples (3.6 mL) were fixed with 10% cold glutaraldehyde (1% final concentration), left in the dark for 10 min at room temperature and then stored at -80 &#176;C. Two subsamples were taken for separate counts of HB and PPP. For HB, 400-&#956;l samples were stained with SYBRGreen I (Sigma Aldrich&#174;) diluted in DMSO to a final concentration of 1X, left for about 10 min in the dark to complete the nucleic-acid staining and run in the flow cytometer. A known volume of beads (1-&#956;m diameter, Fluospheres&#174;) was added to unfrozen samples. HB were detected by their signature in plots of side scatter light (SSC) versus green fluorescence of nucleic acid-bound stains FITC (FL1 530 nm) and SSC (side scatter) axes (e.g. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gasol et&#160;al., 1999</xref>). Turbid samples were previously diluted with pre-filtered PBS (1:10). For PPP we used the same procedure as for HB, but without stain addition. Picoplanktonic algae were identified in plots of SSC versus blue laser-dependent red fluorescence (PerCP or FL3, 670 nm), orange fluorescence (PE or FL2 585/42 nm) versus FL3, and red laser-dependent far-red fluorescence (APC or FL4, 661 nm) versus FL3.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2.4"><label>2.2.4</label><title>Analysis of the contribution of autotrophic fractions to total autotrophic biomass</title><p id="p0075">To compare the contribution of micro + nanophytoplankton and PPP populations to the autotrophic biomass at Tf, the biovolume of each size fraction was calculated for control and herbicide treatments for clear and turbid systems at Tf. The biovolume of micro + nano phytoplankton was calculated following <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Rott (1981)</xref> and <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hillebrand et&#160;al. (1999)</xref>. In regard to PPP, a sphere with a theoretical size of 0.9 &#956;m was considered for PE-Pcy, PC-Pcy and PEuk, which represents a theoretical biovolume three times higher than that of Pcy (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Callieri, 2008</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Statistical and numerical analysis</title><p id="p0080">The homogeneity of the e.u. was verified in terms of water turbidity, for both turbid and clear systems, just before the addition of AsiMax 50&#174; by a Kruskal&#8211;Wallis non-parametric ANOVA by ranks test (KW). Statistical differences in turbidity, chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration and abundance of micro + nano phytoplankton between turbidity states were analyzed at Tf using one-way ANOVA (factor treatment = control and six AsiMax 50&#174; concentration levels). Multiple comparisons were carried out using Tukey test. The Holm-Sidak method was used to compare treated and control groups. RM-ANOVA was applied for testing the significance of PPP and HB counts, with two factors: time (T1 and Tf) and treatment (control and six AsiMax 50&#174; concentration levels). For nano + micro phytoplankton, a Pearson correlation matrix was calculated among the abundances of live organisms of species from all treatments, for each type of system. Species that were recorded more than five times in all samples and in at least two e.u. of the same treatment, were included in the analysis. These matrices were incorporated into Cytoscape&#174; v 3.7.1 software (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Shannon et&#160;al., 2003</xref>) to build networks among species. In addition, the following indices were calculated (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Magurran, 2013</xref>): richness (S); the Simpson index as 1-D, where D = <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, ni is the number of organisms of the ith species and N is the total number of organisms; and evenness E= (1/D)/S).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Physical and chemical parameters</title><p id="p0085">Real values of 2,4-D concentrations in water for each treatment at the beginning of the experiment (T1) are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Mean real values (&#177;SD) of 2,4-D concentrations measured in each treatment at T1 in clear and turbid systems. LOD = limit of detection.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#160;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">2,4-D (mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLEAR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TURBID</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;LOD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;LOD</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20 &#177; 0.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93 &#177; 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02 &#177; 0.29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.25 &#177; 0.59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.94 &#177; 1.17</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 &#177; 11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">238 &#177; 79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,911 &#177; 58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,133 &#177; 351</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0090">Turbidity values were 1.10 &#177; 0.30 NTU and 9.29 &#177; 0.85 NTU (mean &#177; SD) immediately before AsiMax 50&#174; input to the clear and turbid water systems, respectively. No significant differences were found before AsiMax 50&#174; addition between e.u. of the clear (KW, p = 0.511) and turbid (KW, p = 0.199) systems. At Tf, mean values of turbidity from all e.u. were 1.00 &#177; 0.00 and 13.33 &#177; 3.06 for the clear and turbid systems, respectively. In the turbid system, significant decreases in turbidity of 29%, 41% and 45% were observed at 20, 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D compared to control at Tf, respectively (ANOVA; p &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;1</xref>A).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;1</label><caption><p>A-B. Mean values (horizontal bars) and measurement of replicates (dots) of: A) water turbidity and B) chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration at Tf under clear and turbid conditions. (*) Significant differences (ANOVA, Holm-Sidak method) with respect to control (p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#160;1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Biological parameters</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Chlorophyll a</title><p id="p0095">At Tf, maximum chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentrations of 7.62 and 101.24 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> were recorded at the 2 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment under clear and turbid conditions, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;1</xref>B), while minimum values of 1.09 and 38.10 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> were obtained at the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment for the clear and turbid systems, respectively. There were significant decreases with respect to control in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment: 36.7%, for the turbid (ANOVA; p = 0.006), and 76.9% for the clear system (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Micro + nano phytoplankton (&gt;2 &#956;m)</title><p id="p0100"><xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref> shows a list of the species from the micro + nanoplanktonic fraction for the clear and turbid systems.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Phytoplankton taxa in clear and turbid microcosms present in all treatments at both T0 and Tf.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#160;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLEAR</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">TURBID</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cyanobacteria</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Leptolyngbya</italic> sp.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chlorophyta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Choricystis</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Botryococcus braunii</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Coelastrum microporum</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tetraedron minimum</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lagerheimia ciliata</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oedogonium</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oocystis solitaria</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Scenedesmus pulloides</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tetraedron minimum</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacillariophyceae</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achnanthes minutissimum</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nitzschia palea</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dinophyceae</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Peridinium</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Peridinium</italic> sp.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cryptophyceae</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cryptomonas erosa</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chrysophyceae</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0105">Chlorophyta was always the most important group, both in richness and abundance. Under the clear condition and considering T0 and Tf, this group made up 71% of the total micro + nanoplankton abundance, followed by Dinophyceae (12.1%), Bacillariophyceae (8.86%), Crysophyceae (7.8%) and Cryptophyceae (0.2%). At T0, Chlorophyta represented 38.8% of the total abundance of the micro + nano planktonic fraction. At Tf, this group showed significant increases in abundance between the AsiMax 50&#174; treatments and the control (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001), except for 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, where the percentages of all groups were similar to those at T0 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;2</xref>A). In the turbid system, Chlorophyta dominated in richness and abundance, followed by Crysophyceae (1.2%), Cyanobacteria (0.8%) and Dinophyceae (0.6%). At T0, Chlorophyta made up 95.7% of the total abundance, and a significant increase was observed at Tf (ANOVA p = 0.046), with a mean value of 97.7% for all treatments (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;2</xref>B).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;2</label><caption><p>A-B. Abundance percentages of micro + nanophytoplanktonic groups at T0 (control) and Tf (control and 2,4-D concentrations) for clear and turbid systems.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#160;2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0110">In the clear system, mean total abundance of micro + nano plankton at T0 was 2,324 &#177; 352 individuals (ind) mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, with 61.5% of live organisms (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>A). At Tf, mean total abundance for the control was &#8764;5 times greater than that at T0 (ANOVA, p = 0.003) while no AsiMax 50&#174; effect was found on total abundance. In the turbid system, mean total abundance of micro + nano plankton at T0 was 663,603 &#177; 40,174 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (mean &#177; SD), with 90.2% of live organisms (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>B). At Tf, no significant change was recorded for the control between T0 and Tf. Moreover, the 0.02, 0.2, 2 and 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments led to a significant increase in the total abundance compared to control (ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001, p = 0.003, p &lt; 0.001, and p &lt; 0.001, respectively). On the other hand, the 200 and 2000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments did not differ significantly in total live abundances with respect to control. For both clear and turbid systems, data of the abundance of live organisms at Tf were fitted to second-order polynomial curves from all the herbicide treatments (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> A and B). Better fit to a humped-shaped curve was found for the turbid (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.64) compared with the clear (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.41) system.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;3</label><caption><p>A-D. Phytoplankton abundances in relation to 2,4-D concentrations. Mean values (&#177;SD) of total abundances of live and dead organisms at T0 and Tf under A) clear and B) turbid conditions; results of one-way ANOVA in combination with Tukey's multiple comparisons test for abundance are shown in letters for live (plain) and dead (italic) abundances; different letters indicate significant differences (p &lt; 0.05). Comparison between linear dose-dependence curve (dotted line) of live abundances and treatments at Tf obtained by projecting control and 0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments, and the fitted curves (solid line) from our experimental data. Difference in abundance with respect to control for live and dead organisms of the most abundant species at Tf under clear C) and turbid D) conditions. (*) Significant differences with respect to control (p &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig.&#160;3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0115">The values of total live abundance of micro + nano plankton mentioned above were in agreement with the variations in abundance of the most abundant species for each type of system. In the clear system, <italic toggle="yes">Choricystis</italic> sp. was the dominant taxon in all treatments, followed by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. At Tf, the live abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Choricystis</italic> sp. showed a significant decrease with respect to control (ANOVA, p = 0.047), with a significant increase in dead abundance (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>C). Moreover, at Tf a significant increase in dead abundance was found for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 0.001, respectively). In the turbid system, <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. showed the highest value of live abundance, with significant increments in the 0.02, 0.2, 2 and 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>D). A significant increase in dead abundance was found in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (ANOVA, p&lt;0.001). This species was followed in live abundance by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp., whose live and dead abundances did not show any clear trend due to herbicide input (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>D). In summary, in the clear system the micro + nanoplanktonic fraction showed the largest difference in composition between control and the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment, while in the turbid system its quali- and quantitative composition in the 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments was similar to that in the control.</p><p id="p0120">Correlation networks of live abundance were constructed for micro + nanoplanktonic species to analyze the relationships among taxa exposed to AsiMax 50&#174; under clear and turbid conditions (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). The networks included 10 and 7 species for the clear and turbid systems, respectively. Taxa were more significantly and positively intercorrelated in the turbid (mean r = 0.62) than in the clear system (mean r = 0.56). As already mentioned, some species were present in both systems (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Tetraedron minimum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Peridinium</italic> sp.). However, they responded differently to the herbicide depending on the system. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. was negatively affected in the clear system but not in the turbid one (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>C). According to the correlation network, the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. was significantly and positively correlated with the most abundant species, <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. (r Pearson = 0.60; p = 0.002) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). In the clear system, no-significant correlation was observed between the abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. and of any of the species significantly stimulated by the herbicide. In the turbid system, S<italic toggle="yes">taurastrum</italic> sp. was the species most strongly stimulated by AsiMax 50&#174; (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>C) and the most correlated with the subdominant taxa (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>). This trend was not observed in the clear system, where the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. was not correlated with that of any other species. The abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. also varied depending on the type of system, i.e. its abundance decreased in the clear system, while it increased at low 2,4-D concentrations and decreased at higher concentrations in the turbid one (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;3</xref>C). The abundance of this species was significantly and positively correlated with that of <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. (r Pearson = 0.72; p = 0.0001), while it was not significantly correlated with that of any other species in the clear system (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;4</xref>).<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;4</label><caption><p>Correlation networks among the abundances of live organisms of micro + nano phytoplankton species for the clear and turbid systems. Dotted line: p&lt;0.05. n&#160;= 24. Networks were built with Cytoscape&#174; v3.7.1 software.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig.&#160;4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">At T0, mean values of richness, diversity and evenness were higher in the clear system (S = 7.00 &#177; 1.00, D = 0.74 &#177; 0.03 and E = 0.57 &#177; 0.14) than in the turbid one (S = 6.67 &#177; 0.58, D = 0.14 &#177; 0.03 and E = 0.17 &#177; 0.01. In general, at Tf, these parameters showed no significant differences between herbicide treatments and control for both types of systems, except for the following: (a) for the clear system, a significant decrease in D (ANOVA, p = 0.04) was observed in the 200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment with respect to control, with D = 0.29 &#177; 0.13; (b) for the turbid system, S and E decreased significantly in the 200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment, with S = 3.67 &#177; 0.58 (ANOVA, p = 0.006) and E = 0.29 &#177; 0.05 (ANOVA p = 0.041); and in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment, with S = 3.00 &#177; 1.00 (ANOVA p&#706;0.001) and E = 0.38 &#177; 0.12 (ANOVA, p = 0.001).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Cytometric populations (0.2&#8211;2 &#956;m): PPP and HB</title><p id="p0130">Cytograms of samples of control and herbicide treatments collected at T1 and Tf revealed four cytometric populations, of which one corresponded to HB, and the other three to photosynthetic populations: PEuk, PC-Pcy and PE-Pcy. The HB was more abundant than PPP, both in the clear and turbid systems, ranging between a maximum of 99.7% (clear, Tf, 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) and a minimum of 80.9% (turbid, Tf, 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>). RM-ANOVA revealed significant differences in the abundance of HB and PPP between T1 and Tf for the clear and turbid systems (RM-ANOVA, p = 0.018 and p = 0.001 respectively). In regard to treatment effects, PPP showed significant variations in abundance at 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D with a rapid significant increment of &#8764;5 times at T1 compared to control (RM-ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001 in both systems, <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>). This increase continued until Tf in the turbid system, while it did not in the clear one (RM-ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001). The same increase in abundance was observed in the 200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (RM-ANOVA, p = 0.003) for the turbid system at Tf. The abundance of the HB fraction was significantly increased by &#8764;3 times at Tf in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment only for the clear system (ANOVA, p&lt;0.001).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Mean values (&#177;SD) of the abundances of photosynthetic picoplankton (PPP) and heterotrophic bacteria (HB) at T1 and Tf, for all treatments and for the clear and turbid systems. Bold: significant difference compared to control (RM-ANOVA, p &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#160;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="2">Treatment</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">CLEAR<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">TURBID<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPP</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HB</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPP</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HB</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">T1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CONTROL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7E+04 &#177; 1.9E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5E+06 &#177; 1.5E+05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5E+05 &#177; 9.3E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4E+06 &#177; 7.5E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5E+04 &#177; 2.9E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6E+06 &#177; 4.7E+05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9E+04 &#177; 4,4E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1E+06 &#177; 1.1E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2E+04 &#177; 1.0E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1E+06 &#177; 9.7E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3E+05 &#177; 4.5E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5E+06 &#177; 1.2E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6E+04 &#177; 4.8E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0E+06 &#177; 1.4E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2E+05 &#177; 4.1E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8E+06 &#177; 1.1E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8E+04 &#177; 2.4E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9E+06 &#177; 3.0E+05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0E+05 &#177; 3.0E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6E+06 &#177; 1.2E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4E+04 &#177; 2.7E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5E+06 &#177; 7.3E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6E+05 &#177; 8.8E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0E+06 &#177; 2.6E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.7E+05 &#177; 4.9E+04</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9E+06 &#177; 3.6E+05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.9E+05 &#177; 6.5E+04</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7E+06 &#177; 5.6E+05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Tf</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CONTROL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3E+04 &#177; 6.8E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6E+06 &#177; 1.4E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7E+05 &#177; 4.9E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0E+06 &#177; 2.1E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2E+04 &#177; 1.3E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5E+06 &#177; 1.6E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7E+05 &#177; 3.4E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5E+06 &#177; 6.8E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4E+04 &#177; 1.2E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2E+06 &#177; 1.4E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5E+05 &#177; 2.3E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9E+06 &#177; 6.1E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2E+04 &#177; 3.8E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8E+06 &#177; 1.3E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2E+05 &#177; 1.7E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1E+06 &#177; 1.2E+06</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6E+04 &#177; 9.0E+02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8E+06 &#177; 1.4E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6E+05 &#177; 5.5E+04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2E+06 &#177; 8.4E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5E+04 &#177; 4.1E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1E+06 &#177; 1.2E+06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5.2E+05 &#177; 1.4E+05</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1E+06 &#177; 3.3E+05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2E+04 &#177; 5.3E+03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7.9E+06 &#177; 4.3E+06</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>8.7E+05 &#177; 2.3E+05</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0E+06 &#177; 1.3E+06</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0135">The abundance of the PPP cytometric populations was, on average, higher in turbid than in clear systems.</p><p id="p0140">PE-Pcy was the best represented group of the PPP populations, ranging from 53.8% (Tf, 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 99.2% (T1, 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) for the clear system and from 96.0% (Tf, 0.2 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 99.0% (Tf, 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) for the turbid system (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;5</xref>). For the clear system at T1, PEuk abundance ranged between a minimum of 856 &#177; 202 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to a maximum of 1,284 &#177; 466 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup>), with no significant differences among treatments (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>A). At Tf, PEuk abundance ranged from 509 &#177; 111 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 9,118 &#177; 2,268 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (control). RM-ANOVA analysis showed no significant growth of PEuk in microcosms treated with 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (RM-ANOVA, p = 0.580), while this population showed a significant growth response in the rest of the treatments, including controls. Such growth inhibition at 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> led to a significant decrease in PEuk abundance of &#8764;18 times at Tf, compared to control (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>A). In the turbid system at T1, PEuk abundance ranged from 6,621 &#177; 368 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 39,887 &#177; 11,842 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>). At this time, a significant increment of &#8764;5 times compared to control was measured in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>B). At Tf, the abundance of this fraction ranged from 2,950 &#177; 223 (20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 10,979 &#177; 4,271 (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>), with no significant differences between treatments and control. The abundance of this population decreased significantly between T1 and Tf for the 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments (RM-ANOVA, p = 0.026 and p&lt;0.001 respectively), resulting from an early growth and a subsequent decrease.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;5</label><caption><p>Abundance percentages of PPP populations in relation to treatments at T1 and Tf under clear and turbid conditions. PE-Pcy: phycoerythrin-rich picocyanobacteria; PC-Pcy: phycocyanin-rich picocyanobacteria; PEuk: eukaryotic picoplankton.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig.&#160;5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;6</label><caption><p>A-F: Mean values (columns) and measurements of replicates (dots) of PPP population abundances (ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) determined by flow cytometry at 15 min (T1) and 168 h (Tf). A. picoeukaryotes (PEuk); clear; B. picoeukaryotes (PEuk); turbid; C. phycocyanin-rich picocyanobacteria (PC-Pcy), clear; D: phycocyanin-rich picocyanobacteria (PC-Pcy), turbid; E: phycoerythrin-rich picocyanobacteria (PE-Pcy) clear; F: phycoerythrin-rich picocyanobacteria (PE-Pcy) turbid. Bars &#177;1 SD. Results were compared by a one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's multiple comparisons test. Different letters mean significant differences (p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig.&#160;6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0145">In the clear system, PC-Pcy abundance ranged from a minimum mean (&#177;SD) value of 166 &#177; 29 (200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to a maximum of 282 &#177; 87 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at T1, while it ranged from 80 &#177; 75 (0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 286 &#177; 91 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at Tf (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>C). In the turbid system, its abundance ranged from 80 &#177; 77 (0.2 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 206 &#177; 86 (200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at T1, and from 187 &#177; 90 (0.2 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 333 &#177; 207 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at Tf (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>D). No significant effects between treatments were found in any case for this population.</p><p id="p0150">PE-Pcy, the most abundant PPP fraction, at T1 ranged from 22,969 &#177; 2,530 (200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 164,130 &#177; 48,443 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) in the clear system. At this time, a significant increase in PE-Pcy abundance of &#8764;5 times was observed in relation to control in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (ANOVA, p&#706;&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>E). At Tf, there were no significant variations, with a minimum of 15,527 &#177; 8,418 (0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) and a maximum of 23,553 &#177; 4,497 ind mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (control). RM-ANOVA revealed an early increase (at T1) in the abundance of this fraction in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment, with a subsequent decline at Tf (RM-ANOVA, p&lt;0.001). In the turbid system, this fraction ranged from 62,626 &#177; 44,171 (0.02 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 651,631 &#177; 68,514 ind L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at T1 and from 115,508 &#177; 16,676 (2 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) to 853,987 &#177; 230,227 ind L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) at Tf (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>F). This population showed a significant increase in abundance of &#8764;4 times at T1, and of &#8764;5 times at Tf in the 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment compared to control (ANOVA, p0.001 in both cases). Also, an increase in abundance of &#8764;3 times was recorded in the 200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatment (ANOVA, p&#706;0.001) at Tf for the turbid system (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#160;6</xref>F). These increases persisted between T1 and Tf for the 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> treatments (RM-ANOVA, p = 0.004 and p = 0.017, respectively).</p><p id="p0155">At Tf, the percentage contribution of the different size autotrophic fractions to total autotrophic biomass varied among groups (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#160;4</xref>). For the turbid system, micro + nano phytoplankton showed a lower contribution in the treatments at higher concentrations (200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) (ANOVA, p = 0.005 and p&lt;0.001, respectively). This decrease was in accordance with the increase in the percentage contribution of the PE-Pcy fraction at 200 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> (ANOVA, p = 0.004), as well as with the increase in the percentage contribution of both PE-Pcy (ANOVA, p&lt;0.001) and PEuk (ANOVA, p = 0.002) fractions at 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;4</label><caption><p>Mean values of percentage contribution of different size autotrophic fractions to autotrophic biomass at Tf, for all treatments and for clear and turbid systems. Bold: significant difference with respect to control (RM-ANOVA, p &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Table&#160;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Clear<hr/></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Turbid<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Micro + nano</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PEuk</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PC-Pcy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PE-Pcy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Micro + nano</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PEuk</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PC-Pcy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PE-Pcy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.814</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.099</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.33E-04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.987</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.87E-05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.529</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.259</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.212</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.997</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.16E-06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.520</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.276</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.202</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.995</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.44E-06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.674</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.172</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.153</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.997</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.74E-06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.607</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.242</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.149</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.995</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.83E-06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.708</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.147</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.144</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>99.961</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70E-05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.038</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.767</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.89E-03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.214</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>99.940</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81E-05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.057</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0160">In general, in the turbid system there were significant correlations between chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration and the percentage contribution of micro + nano phytoplankton (r Pearson = 0.66; p = 0.0012), PEuk (r Pearson = -0.62; p = 0.0029) and PE-Pcy (r Pearson = -0.66; p = 0.0011). On the contrary, no correlations were found between these variables in the clear system.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0165">Our results strongly suggest that the degree of water turbidity affects the response of the studied freshwater populations exposed for 7 days to the 2,4-D-based herbicide Asimax 50&#174;. We found differences in the structural integrity of the phytoplankton and picoplankton communities from low to high concentrations of the active ingredient.</p><p id="p0170">The impact of AsiMax 50&#174; on micro + nano phytoplankton seemed to be greater in the turbid than in the clear system, in terms of both richness and abundance. An experimental effect of the clear system on this fraction was likely to occur between T0 and Tf, compared to control. This was not observed in the turbid system and may be attributable to a &#8220;confinement effect&#8221; (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Pesce et&#160;al., 2009</xref>), which takes place after samples collected from a natural system are placed into microcosms of lower volume. At T0, phytoplankton diversity, richness and evenness were higher in the clear than in the turbid system. At Tf, no decrease in phytoplankton richness was observed for any treatment in the clear system, while it decreased significantly at 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D in the turbid system. This suggests that some species cannot survive at the higher herbicide concentrations, in agreement with that reported for 2,4-D by <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kobraei and White (1996)</xref>. Communities with high levels of diversity tend to be more resilient to environmental changes (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Oliver et&#160;al., 2015</xref>), due to redundancy among different species sharing similar functions. Resilience increases if these species also show differential resistance to a contaminant. Indeed, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Girvan et&#160;al. (2005)</xref> have demonstrated that bacterial diversity in soils promotes community stability and resilience after benzene perturbation. In the case of phytoplankton, it is expected that the differential sensitivity of species to herbicides (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Huertas et&#160;al., 2010</xref>) as well as their presence and relative abundance, will determine the response of the community as a whole. The richer the community, the greater the chance for the presence of tolerant or resistant species to a contaminant, and the response of the community will rely upon the evenness and sensitivity of the dominant species, if any.</p><p id="p0175">In general, natural or anthropogenic agents induce a wide range of responses in biological entities, according to their scale of complexity (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Peck, 2011</xref>). For example, variations in total abundance may reflect different physiological strategies. In our study, phytoplanktonic species that survived at 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D in the clear system and at 200 and 2,000 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D in the turbid system showed low abundance values due to decreased reproduction. A similar behavior was observed for phytoplankton exposed to the commercial glyphosate-based formulation RoundUp&#174;, which had no effect on species richness but produced a significant strong decrease in total abundance (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">P&#233;rez et&#160;al., 2007</xref>).</p><p id="p0180">The abundance of the micro + nano phytoplankton community decreased at higher concentrations and increased at lower concentrations of 2,4-D (0.02; 0.2; 2 and 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>), with a humped-shaped, dose-dependent response. This effect was more clearly noted in the turbid than in the clear system. Although we used a commercial formulation with undeclared ingredients to obtain a more realistic approach, stimulation effects on phytoplankton are consistent with those previously reported for the active principle. In this regard, further experiments comparing the effects of pure 2,4-D and AsiMax&#174; are required for a more conclusive assessment. Nevertheless, the stimulation of phytoplankton at low doses of 2,4-D has been already reported in studies involving algal monoculture trials and mesocosms (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Boyle, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kobraei and White, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Wong, 2000</xref>). The auxin pathways and their modes of action are well-known for vascular plants, but not for algae (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">&#381;i&#382;kov&#225; et&#160;al., 2016</xref>) and after many years of debate (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lau et&#160;al., 2009</xref>), the presence of auxin pathways in algae and cyanobacteria was finally confirmed by <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Sergeeva et&#160;al. (2002)</xref>. Certainly, the fact that 2,4-D induces growth at low doses and causes growth inhibition at higher ones provides evidence that it may mimic hormonal function.</p><p id="p0185">Moreover, the presence or absence of auxin pathways in the different species (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp., dominant in the turbid system) occurring in each community, could be determinant for the whole community response. <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">&#381;i&#382;kov&#225; et&#160;al. (2016)</xref> demonstrated that some cyanobacteria and algae that differ taxonomically possess different concentrations of IAA. They found that four species of Chlamydomonales have low IAA concentration, while some Desmidiales, the same group as that of <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp., have high IAA concentration. Different sensitivity was observed for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. and <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. that were present in both kinds of systems. These species tended to decrease in abundance with respect to control in the clear system while they tended to increase in the turbid one. The impact of 2,4-D on the community may not only be direct, according to species sensitivity but also indirect, via the interactions among community members. The differential absorption and/or utilization of the 2,4-D by certain species may indirectly affect the total abundance of others. In our case, it is possible that the intake of 2,4-D by the dominant <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. limited the exposure of other species to the herbicide. In addition, the 2,4-D may indirectly affect the freshwater community through ecological interactions such as competition, facilitation and/or predation. Numerous examples of these indirect effects due to different contaminants can be found in the comprehensive review by <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fleeger et&#160;al. (2003)</xref>. In our study, the sensitivity of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. to 2,4-D detected in the clear system was probably masked in the turbid one by <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. growth. A similar process would have occurred for <italic toggle="yes">Ochromonas</italic> sp. The correlation network analyses suggest that the 2,4-D stimulated the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. when it was predominant through a putative auxin pathway, and that this allowed the development of other species that are actually sensitive to 2,4-D. In brief, the capacity of <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. to rapidly absorb the contaminant may have decreased the exposure of other species in the turbid system. The fact that <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. occurred in the clear system but in a very low proportion may indicate that not only species composition but also their relative abundance are important to predict the behavior of the system in response to a contaminant. The comparison of the correlation networks indicated that species were less intercorrelated in the clear system than in the turbid one, suggesting greater community stability for the former than for the latter under herbicide stress. In a less stable community, the change in one species affects the other species. The difficulty of determining the processes that control the responses of a given species strongly underlines the need to be cautious when extrapolating results from monospecific assays to realistic field situations.</p><p id="p0190"><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lozano et&#160;al. (2018)</xref>, who performed a microcosm experiment with the same <italic toggle="yes">Staurastrum</italic> sp. as used here but collected from a phytoplanktonic community with different structural characteristics, reported that it always decreased in abundance after exposure at different concentrations of 2,4-D in pure form. This suggests that the same species may respond differently to agrochemicals depending, on one hand, on the characteristics of their phytoplankton community and, on the other hand, on the form of the chemical assayed (i.e. pure <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> formulation). AsiMax 50&#174; is a commercial formulation based on 2,4-D as active ingredient, with coadjuvants and other substances. The use of active ingredient and/or commercial formulations makes the comparison across assays difficult. The impacts of active ingredients and commercial formulations on freshwater organisms and/or communities have been well documented for different herbicides (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Tsui and Chu, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Annett et&#160;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lipok et&#160;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">De Stefano et&#160;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">The significant increase in the abundance of HB was only observed at the highest 2,4-D concentration in the clear system, probably because the herbicide acted as a nutrient source for bacterial growth. On the other hand, the HB did not show a significant growth in the turbid system probably because its initial abundance was sufficient to metabolize the herbicide. <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Pizarro et&#160;al. (2016)</xref> studied the impact of glyphosate formulation Glifosato Atanor&#174; on microbial communities from clear and organic turbid freshwater systems. In agreement with our study, they found that abundance of bacteria only increased in clear water, most likely because the herbicide was used as nutrient source. The effect of 2,4-D on bacterial communities has been studied by <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aguayo et&#160;al. (2014)</xref>, who observed that the phylum Actinobacteria was predominant at 20 mg L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of 2,4-D, using water from a cold and pristine oligotrophic lake. Likewise, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">De Lipthay et&#160;al. (2003)</xref> reported that a long-term exposure of a subsurface aquifer to a mixture of auxinic herbicides at low concentrations (&lt;40 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) induced the increment of phenoxy acid-degrading bacteria.</p><p id="p0200">The PPP fraction also seemed to experience more pronounced changes in the turbid than in the clear system. It showed a rapid response after 15 min at the highest herbicide concentration in both clear and turbid systems, which was determined by the different behavior of their respective components. This effect was due to a rapid increase in the abundance of PE-Pcy in the clear system and of PEuk and PE-Pcy in the turbid one. The PPP fraction also showed an increase in abundance at the higher herbicide concentrations at Tf in the turbid system. This was mediated by an increase in the PE-Pcy fraction, which was probably stimulated by the combination of direct and indirect effects of AsiMax 50&#174;. The herbicide would act directly on the PE-Pcy fraction if it had auxin pathways, and in this regard <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">&#381;i&#382;kov&#225; et&#160;al. (2016)</xref> found that two species of cyanobacteria (<italic toggle="yes">Chroococcus minutus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Phormidium animale</italic>) contained very high amounts of endogenous auxin (IAA). On the other hand, the decrease in the micro + nano plankton in the same treatments could have indirectly stimulated the growth of PE-Pcy due to decreased competitive pressure.</p><p id="p0205">Changes in micro + nano phytoplankton and PPP abundance accounted for changes in chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration; this is particularly true for the former fraction, which represented more than 99% of the total phytoplanktonic biomass. This phenomenon was more clearly observed in the turbid system, where chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration followed a similar hump-shaped, dose-dependence pattern as that obtained for micro + nano phytoplankton abundance. Changes in turbidity resembled those in chlorophyll <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> concentration, especially for the turbid system, where both variables decreased to lower levels.</p><p id="p0210">The Pampa Plain in Argentina has plenty of permanent shallow lakes with contrasting water turbidity and phytoplankton biomass. It is one of the principal agricultural regions worldwide, where millions of liters of agrochemicals are used each year. The present investigation provides new evidence on the mode of action of the 2,4-D-based herbicide Asimax 50&#174; in freshwater, which is one of the most frequently used commercial formulations in agricultural fields of Argentina. The observed variations in the essential constituents of microbial food chains can produce major functional changes, which are mainly concerned with carbon fluxes affecting the whole dynamics of a freshwater ecosystem. National regulatory agencies establish environmentally safe concentrations of agrochemicals mainly based on results from monoculture experiments. However, this study provides evidence that such concentrations can be unrealistic because species exhibit different behavior when growing in a community. Despite the limitations of the experimental system, our results highlight the importance of using community-scale approaches in ecotoxicological studies to predict the sense, magnitude and direction of changes in freshwater ecosystems exposed to 2,4-D formulations.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0215">Lozano V.L.: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0220">Pizarro H.N.: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0225">Miranda C.E., Gonz&#225;lez C., Unrein F., Wolansky M.J, Vinocur A.L.: Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0230">The work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">ANPCyT</funding-source> (PICT, 2014 1586), <funding-source id="gs2">CONICET</funding-source> (PIP 11220130100399) and <funding-source id="gs3">UBACyT</funding-source> (20020170100020BA) all under H. Pizarro direction.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0235">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0240">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguayo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becerra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbicides induce change in metabolic and genetic diversity of bacterial community from a cold oligotrophic lake</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24158391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11274-013-1530-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allende</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tell</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zagarese</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torremorell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustingorry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytoplankton and primary production in clear-vegetated, inorganic-turbid, and algal-turbid shallow lakes from the pampa plain (Argentina)</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><volume>624</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schab</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinr&#252;cken</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mode of action of the herbicide glyphosate</article-title><source>Naturwissenschaften</source><volume>67</volume><issue>7</issue><year>1980</year><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>357</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Annett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hontela</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of glyphosate and glyphosate-based herbicides on the freshwater environment</article-title><source>J.&#160;Appl. Toxicol.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jat.2997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Ger&#243;nimo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guijarro</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portocarrero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Los plaguicidas agregados al suelo y su destino en el ambiente</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>INTA Ediciones</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Argentina</publisher-loc><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>APHA/AWWA/WEF</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Standard Methods for the Examination of Water &amp; Wastewater</chapter-title><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Centennial Edition</publisher-name><comment>Sec 6640</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aronzon</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herkovits</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez Coll</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stage-dependent toxicity of 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic on the embryonic development of a South American toad, Rhinella arenarum</article-title><source>Environ. Toxicol.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20112415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/tox.20564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>D.J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quiroga</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zagarese</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrence and levels of glyphosate and AMPA in shallow lakes from the Pampean and Patagonian regions of Argentina</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>200</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29501888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.02.103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nykiel-Szyma&#324;ska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stolarek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#322;aba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#243;&#380;alska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid-induced oxidative stress: metabolome and membrane modifications in Umbelopsis isabellina, a herbicide degrader</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0199677</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0199677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6014680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29933393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the aquatic herbicide 2, 4-D DMA on the ecology of experimental ponds</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut. Ecol. Biol.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1980</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callieri</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Picophytoplankton in freshwater ecosystems: the importance of small-sized phototrophs</article-title><source>Freshwater reviews</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>CONABIA</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>eofplsflwp</chapter-title><year>2019</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.agroindustria.gob.ar/sitio/areas/biotecnologia/ogm/" id="intref0010">https://www.agroindustria.gob.ar/sitio/areas/biotecnologia/ogm/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Arcaute</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larramendy</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soloneski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotoxicity by long-term exposure to the auxinic herbicides 2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid and dicamba on Cnesterodon decemmaculatus (Pisces: poeciliidae)</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut.</source><volume>243</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>670</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30228061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2018.09.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Lipthay</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuxen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrechtsen</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerg</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aamand</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ exposure to low herbicide concentrations affects microbial population composition and catabolic gene frequency in an aerobic shallow aquifer</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.69.1.461-467.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC152397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Stefano</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatt&#225;s</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinocur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cataldo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative impact of two glyphosate-based formulations in interaction with <italic toggle="yes">Limnoperna fortunei</italic> on freshwater phytoplankton</article-title><source>Ecol. Indicat.</source><volume>85</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>584</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehnert</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeQuattro</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karasov</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of low, subchronic exposure of 2, 4-Dichlorophenoxyacetic acid (2, 4-D) and commercial 2, 4-D formulations on early life stages of fathead minnows (Pimephales promelas)</article-title><source>Environ. Toxicol. Chem.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2550</fpage><lpage>2559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29920774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/etc.4209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dukatz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canziani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clasificaci&#243;n de lagos someros pampeanos mediante im&#225;genes Landsat</article-title><source>TM. Biolog&#237;a Acu&#225;tica.</source><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ensminger</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pesticide occurrence and aquatic benchmark exceedances in urban surface waters and sediments in three urban areas of California, USA, 2008&#8211;2011</article-title><source>Environ. Monit. Assess.</source><volume>185</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>3697</fpage><lpage>3710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10661-012-2821-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>FAOSTAT</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>eofplsflwp</chapter-title><year>2018</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/" id="intref0015">http://www.fao.org/faostat/en/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proost</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruprecht</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutwil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PhytoNet: comparative co-expression network analyses across phytoplankton and land plants</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gky298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6030924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleeger</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carman</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisbet</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indirect effects of contaminants in aquatic ecosystems</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><volume>317</volume><issue>1-3</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0048-9697(03)00141-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasol</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zweifel</surname><given-names>U.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>&#197;.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of size and nucleic acid content heterogeneity as measured by flow cytometry in natural planktonic bacteria</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>65</volume><issue>10</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>4475</fpage><lpage>4483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aem.65.10.4475-4483.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC91596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girvan</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killham</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prosser</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial diversity promotes community stability and functional resilience after perturbation</article-title><source>Environ. Microbiol.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00695.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mode of action of auxin herbicides: a new ending to a long, drawn out story</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science. Research News.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1360-1385(00)01791-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#252;rselen</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschtel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollingher</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zohary</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biovolume calculation for pelagic and benthic microalgae</article-title><source>J.&#160;Phycol.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>424</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huertas</surname><given-names>I.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Rodas</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the capability of different phytoplankton groups to adapt to contamination: herbicides will affect phytoplankton species differently</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><volume>188</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20630023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03370.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;os</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential impact of the herbicide 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid on human and ecosystems</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><volume>111</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29203058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envint.2017.10.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobraei</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of 2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid on Kentucky algae: simultaneous laboratory and field toxicity testings</article-title><source>Arch. Environ. Contam. Toxicol.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8975831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00212442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LaChapelle</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruygrok</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toomer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oost</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monnie</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stebbins-Boaz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hormonal herbicide, 2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid, inhibits Xenopus oocyte maturation by targeting translational and post-translational mechanisms</article-title><source>Reprod. Toxicol.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17055699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.reprotox.2006.08.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanct&#244;t</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauli</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trudeau</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of glyphosate-based herbicides on survival, development, growth and sex ratios of wood frog (Lithobates sylvaticus) tadpoles. II: agriculturally relevant exposures to Roundup WeatherMax&#174; and Vision&#174; under laboratory conditions</article-title><source>Aquat. Toxicol.</source><volume>154</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24912403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aquatox.2014.05.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#252;rgens</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin signaling in algal lineages: fact or myth?</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19285905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tplants.2009.01.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilchtenthaler</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wellburn</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinations of total carotenoids and chlorophylls a and b of leaf extracts in different solvents</article-title><source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1983</year><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>592</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipok</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Studnik</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruyaert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The toxicity of Roundup&#174; 360 SL formulation and its main constituents: glyphosate and isopropylamine towards non-target water photoautotrophs</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><volume>73</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20813408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2010.08.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinocur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>y Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allende</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristos</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolansky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of glyphosate and 2, 4-D mixture on freshwater phytoplankton and periphyton communities: a microcosms approach</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><volume>148</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magurran</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Measuring Biological Diversity</chapter-title><year>2013</year><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helm</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaltenecker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowierski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pesticides related to land use in watersheds of the Great Lakes basin</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><volume>648</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30125850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.08.169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Procter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eigenbrod</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity and resilience of ecosystem functions</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26437633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tree.2015.08.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organisms and responses to environmental change</article-title><source>Marine genomics</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22118635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.margen.2011.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torremorell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mugni</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do Nascimento</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the herbicide Roundup on freshwater microbial communities: a mesocosm study</article-title><source>Ecol. Appl.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>2310</fpage><lpage>2322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18213971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1890/07-0499.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Effects of herbicide glyphosate and glyphosate-based formulations on aquatic ecosystems</chapter-title><source>Herbicides and Environment</source><year>2011</year><publisher-name>InTech</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batisson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fajon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montuelle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohatier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of spring and summer riverine microbial communities following glyphosate exposure</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><volume>72</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1905</fpage><lpage>1912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19646758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2009.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoup</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Herbicide Mode of Action</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Kansas State University Agricultural Experiment Station and Cooperative Extension Service</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinocur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helman</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dos Santos Afonso</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glyphosate input modifies microbial community structure in clear and turbid freshwater systems</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Control Ser.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>5143</fpage><lpage>5153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-015-5748-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26552793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and biochemical responses of Microcystis aeruginosa to glyphosate and its Roundup&#174; formulation</article-title><source>J.&#160;Hazard Mater.</source><volume>248</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23357506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2012.12.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quir&#243;s</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rennella</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boveri</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosnovsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factores que afectan la estructura y el funcionamiento de las lagunas pampeanas</article-title><source>Ecolog&#237;a austral</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>185</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rott</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some results from phytoplankton counting intercalibrations</article-title><source>Schweiz. Z. Hydrol.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1981</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandmann</surname><given-names>E.R.I.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aromatic metabolism by a 2, 4-D degrading Arthrobacter sp</article-title><source>Can. J. Microbiol.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1988</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosper</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeppesen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative equilibria in shallow lakes</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><year>1993</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21236168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0169-5347(93)90254-M</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SENASA</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>eofplsflwp</chapter-title><year>2018</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.senasa.gob.ar/tags/agroquimicos" id="intref0020">http://www.senasa.gob.ar/tags/agroquimicos</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sergeeva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liaimer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for production of the phytohormone indole-3-acetic acid by cyanobacteria</article-title><source>Planta</source><volume>215</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00425-002-0749-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markiel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozier</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramage</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwikowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>2498</fpage><lpage>2504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.1239303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC403769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidimensional relationships of herbicides with insect-crop food webs</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><volume>643</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1522</fpage><lpage>1532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30189568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.06.312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial degradation of herbicides</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/1040841X.2014.929564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into the mode of action of 2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid (2, 4-D) as an herbicide</article-title><source>J.&#160;Integr. Plant Biol.</source><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24237670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jipb.12131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aquatic toxicity of glyphosate-based formulations: comparison between different organisms and the effects of environmental factors</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>52</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12821000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0045-6535(03)00306-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uterm&#246;hl</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zur vervollkommnung der quantitativen phytoplankton-methodik: mit 1 Tabelle und 15 abbildungen im Text und auf 1 Tafel</article-title><source>Internationale Vereinigung f&#252;r theoretische und angewandte Limnologie: Die Mitteilungen</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1958</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Meter</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glinski</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purucker</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of exposure to pesticide mixtures on the metabolomic profile in post-metamorphic green frogs (Lithobates clamitans)</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><volume>624</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29929247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.12.175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6020053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venrick</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How many cells to count?</article-title><source>Phytoplankton manual</source><year>1978</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>180</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Fiori</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagomarsino</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinistro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escaray</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iummato</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect effects of the glyphosate formulation Glifosato Atanor&#174; on freshwater microbial communities</article-title><source>Ecotoxicology</source><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22539117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10646-012-0915-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagomarsino</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylvester</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mugni</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New evidences of Roundup&#174;(glyphosate formulation) impact on the periphyton community and the water quality of freshwater ecosystems</article-title><source>Ecotoxicology</source><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20091117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10646-009-0446-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westerberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elv&#228;ng</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthrobacter chlorophenolicus sp. nov., a new species capable of degrading high concentrations of 4-chlorophenol</article-title><source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>2083</fpage><lpage>2092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11155983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/00207713-50-6-2083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of 2, 4-D, glyphosate and paraquat on growth, photosynthesis and chlorophyll&#8211;a synthesis of Scenedesmus quadricauda Berb 614</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>41</volume><issue>1-2</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10819198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0045-6535(99)00408-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#381;i&#382;kov&#225;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kube&#353;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrev</surname><given-names>P.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#345;ibyl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;imura</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahajsk&#225;</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of cytokinin and auxin homeostasis in cyanobacteria and algae</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><volume>119</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27707748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aob/mcw194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5218379</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>