<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9617909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9617909.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9617909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9617909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36309570</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-22691-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">22691</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High-gradient magnetic fields and starch metabolism: results from a space experiment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names initials="KH">K. H.</given-names></name><address><email>hasenstein@louisiana.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="MR">M. R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names initials="SP">S. P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajala</surname><given-names initials="C">C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266621.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9831 5270</institution-id><institution>Biology Department, </institution><institution>University of Louisiana at Lafayette, </institution></institution-wrap>Lafayette, LA 70504-43602 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Central Area Crop Breeding Div., National Institute of Crop Science, Suwon, 16429 Gyeonggi-do Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Present Address: Cemvita Factory, 9350 Kirby Drive, Suite 100, Houston, TX 77054 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">397528</issue-id><elocation-id>18256</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-05 20:25:20.700"><day>05</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2022_Article_22691.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Directing plant growth in weightlessness requires understanding the processes that establish plant orientation and how to manipulate them. Both gravi- and phototropism determine directional growth and previous experiments showed that high gradient magnetic fields (HGMF) can induce curvature in roots and shoots. Experiments with <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> verified that that gravitropism-like induction of curvature is possible in space and that the HGMF-responsive organelles are amyloplasts. We assessed the effect of space and HGMF based on 16 genes and compared their transcription with static growth and clinorotation. Amyloplasts size in root tips increased under weightlessness but decreased under clinorotation but not in response to magnetic fields. Amyloplast size changes were correlated with reduced amylase transcription in space samples and enhanced transcription after clinorotation. Mechanostimulation and weightlessness have opposite effects on the size of amyloplasts. The data show that plants perceive weightlessness, and that their metabolism adjusts to microgravity and mechanostimulation. Thus, clinorotation as surrogate for space research may lead to incorrect interpretations.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biological techniques</kwd><kwd>Biophysics</kwd><kwd>Plant sciences</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>NASA</institution></funding-source><award-id>NNX10AP91G</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2022</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The perception of the gravity stimulus and the involvement of amyloplasts have long been the focus of plant biology because of the cryptic nature of essential steps in the response of a biological system to physical stimuli such as gravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. While the first step of the gravitropic response primarily depends on the interaction of intracellular particles with Earth&#8217;s gravitational field, the ability to respond to the gravity signal depends on biological conditions such as auxin sensitivity and transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>, time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, the cytoskeleton<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and physical parameters such as temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, orientation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, osmotic conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, mechanical noise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, cytoplasmic viscosity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and high-gradient magnetic fields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The redundancy contributes to the stability of the graviresponse system and can integrate additional signals such as hydrotropism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and touch<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Because any physiological response is a function of the accumulated signal (auxin, altered gene expression, pH, ion, or charge shifts), control of the response shifts from the original signal to downstream events such as signal processing (translation) and response variables that are related to signal strength and persistence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Therefore, the analysis of mechano-sensing and (gravi)response depends on the elimination of the gravity effects by experimenting under weightlessness conditions in space. The study of HGMF on amyloplast movements was attempted in ground studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> and was the focus of a shuttle experiment in 2003 (STS-107)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, the disintegration of the Shuttle during reentry made the intended analyses impossible. Nonetheless, this experiment provided strong evidence that mechano-sensitivity increased in microgravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Here we report data from a space experiment on the Space-X Crew Resupply Service 3 mission. The aim of this investigation was to repeat the ill-fated experiment on STS-107. However, instead of flax (<italic toggle="yes">Linum usitatissimum</italic>) we used <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seeds to study the effect of magnetic gradients and to take advantage of its Arabidopsis-related genome to assess transcriptional responses of genes related to growth, metabolism, auxin, and stress. Because of the dual effort to characterize the effect of HGMF and transcriptional analysis the remainder of the introduction covers separately each aspect.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>HGMF</title><p id="Par5">Induction of curvature by magneto-mechanical forces depends on the magnetic susceptibility (&#1008;), which is characteristic of a given substance and describes its ability to acquire magnetization I as a result of the (inducing) magnetic field H such that I&#8201;=&#8201;&#1008;H. Diamagnetic substances have negative susceptibility and include the vast majority of biological substances. However, some metal-containing proteins such as hemoglobin, cytochrome, ferritin etc., can have positive susceptibility and are paramagnetic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The magnetic susceptibility of dia- and paramagnetic compounds is proportional to their density and their behavior in a magnetic gradient is analogous to that in the gravity field<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Magnetic susceptibility and density of the cytoplasm are equal to that of water, &#1008; <sub>w</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;7.2&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8211;7</sup> emu (electromagnetic units, table value), and that of starch &#1008;<sub>st</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;(8&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.2)&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8211;7</sup>, thus the differential susceptibility between starch and cytoplasm &#916;&#1008; &#8776; 8&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8211;8</sup> emu. The density of starch &#961;<sub>st</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.5&#160;g/cm<sup>3</sup>, and cytoplasm&#8201;~&#8201;1&#160;g/cm<sup>3</sup>; therefore &#916;&#961;&#8201;=&#8201;0.5&#160;g/cm<sup>3</sup> and &#916;p/&#916; &#1008; &#8776; &#8722;&#160;6&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>6</sup> (g/cm<sup>3</sup>)/emu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Although other methods of generating HGMF are available<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, the generation of a magnetic gradient in the experiments described here, was realized by inserting into a uniform, strong magnetic field ferromagnetic wedges. The wedges become magnetized and create a HGMF (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) such that the gradient &#8711;H is directed toward the tip of the wedge. Therefore, the force acting on a diamagnetic body (&#1008;&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0) repels starch-filled amyloplasts from the inserted object. In contrast, a para- or ferromagnetic body (&#1008;&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0) would experience an attractive force. The force generated by the HGMF utilized in the employed setup has been determined previously to be about 0.6 g<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and exceeds the acceleration that plants respond to (about 10<sup>&#8211;3</sup> g<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The design of the magnetic field chamber (MFC) with 10 magnets arranged in two stories with a total of eight compartments. The magnetic field was contained with two ferromagnetic yokes. Each compartment contained two ferromagnetic wedges and two pieces of activated charcoal cloth (ACC), and one seed cassette each. The diagram on the upper right shows the distortion of the magnetic field by the wedges (applicable to all compartments) and the projected growth of the seedling roots. The flow path of the fixative from a single fill port (F) to the drain port (D) is shown as white canals for front-visible paths; connections on the rear side between the individual compartments are shown as dark lines.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">In contrast to cultivation on earth where orienting factors are provided by gravity as constant and light as intermittent influence, plant growth in space cannot rely on gravitational clues; it depends on the plants&#8217; (intermittent) phototropic response. However, in the absence of light, especially root elongation is variable, and orientation responds mostly to water gradients (hydrotropism)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Removing the two most consequential vectors for plant orientation, i.e., growing plants under weightlessness conditions in the dark, provides an opportunity to examine the role of amyloplasts for directional growth analogous to their role in gravity sensing. Probing magnetophoretic effects and the space conditions on root growth was the objective for the experiment described here.</p><p id="Par8">The investigation included transcription analyses of 16 genes that represent auxin effects (<italic toggle="yes">IAA5, PIN 1, 3, 7</italic>) as the main growth regulator of differential elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, starch katabolism (<italic toggle="yes">Amy1</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, sucrose synthase (<italic toggle="yes">SUS,</italic> cell wall formation)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">UBQ1</italic> (ubiquitin1; a putative reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> and indicator of protein metabolism)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">TUB1</italic> (tubulin1; reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, cell growth, mitosis), <italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic> (actin7; putative reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, root growth and germination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>), <italic toggle="yes">ADH1</italic> (alcohol dehydrogenase; stress response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>), <italic toggle="yes">COX</italic> (cytochrome oxidase subunit1; metabolism, stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>), <italic toggle="yes">G6PDH5</italic> (glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase5; oxidative pentose phosphate pathway, basic metabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>), <italic toggle="yes">GLK</italic> (glucokinase; carbohydrate metabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>) HXK (hexokinase 1; glucose metabolism and developmental regulator<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>), <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic> (phosphofructokinase; carbohydrate metabolism, hypoxia stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>), and <italic toggle="yes">TAGL</italic> (triacylglycerol lipase; lipid metabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>). The transcription pattern of these genes under conditions such as space (weightlessness), clinorotation (enhanced mechanostimulation), and static controls provided information on how seedlings respond to the respective conditions.</p><p id="Par9">This report describes an experiment that built on prior experience (i.e., Biotube1 on STS-107) but used genetically better-characterized plant material, <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic>. Our data support HGMFs as suitable method to establish plant orientation in space but also show that mechanostimulation affects gravisensing-related metabolism. The report demonstrates that plants perceive weightlessness (&#8220;micro-gravity&#8221;) and respond by enhanced starch production in gravity perceiving cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par10"><italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa, var. rapa</italic> seeds were commercially sourced. No approvals were required for the study, which complied with all relevant regulations. Seeds were attached to germination paper with polyvinyl acetate (clear Elmer&#8217;s) glue such that the micropyle was oriented toward the opening of seed cassettes (Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The seeds cassettes were designed to fit into specially designed magnetic field chambers (MFCs, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Experimental setup</title><p id="Par11">The experiment was a follow-up of the STS-107 experiment that was lost as a result of the shuttle accident in 2003. A computer (PC104 stack) controlled all aspects and was remotely operated such that no crew involvement was necessary. The experimental principle of the hardware (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and the arrangement of the components is shown in Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>. Experiment initialization, water dispensation, image acquisition, temperature and pressure recording, and termination of the experiment by fixation were remotely initiated and controlled by the hardware&#8217;s own computer. The entire hardware was custom built at the Kennedy Space Center using several iterations and named Biotube-MICRo (<bold>M</bold>agnetic <bold>I</bold>nduction of <bold>C</bold>urvature in <bold>Ro</bold>ots).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Hardware</title><p id="Par12">The MFCs consisted of machined aluminum cases each containing 10 Neodymium Iron Boron (NdFeB) magnets, 12.7&#160;mm thick with a magnetization of about 30,000 Oe (~&#8201;3 Tesla, Magnet Sales and Manufacturing, Culver City, CA). The magnetic circuit was closed by two yokes. To the surface of each magnet, two wedges of ferromagnetic steel (equilateral cross section, 6&#160;mm high, 50&#160;mm long) were attached that generated the magnetic gradients (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Between each pair of magnets seed cassettes were inserted that contained 10 <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seeds. Five seeds each were glued (Elmer&#8217;s clear glue) along the long edges of germination paper. Roots that emerged from the seed cassettes were expected to curve away from the wedges.</p><p id="Par13">A camera system consisting of eight cameras on either side was installed between two of the three MFCs such that the cameras were positioned opposite a window that permitted viewing the seed cassettes. Illumination was achieved by a single IR LED (750&#8211;800&#160;nm) to avoid phototropic stimulation. The LEDs were activated only during imaging. The cameras acquired images in two-minute intervals and the video signal together with temperature, and atmospheric pressure data and position number were transmitted to the Kennedy Space Center (Florida) as well as recorded internally on a hard drive.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Space flight parameters</title><p id="Par14">The experiment was launched on Space-X3 (April 18, 2014) and initiated after 19&#160;days by dispensing 400&#160;&#956;L deionized water to each seed cassette from a Micro Effusion Device for Space Applications (MEDUSA). The seeds germinated after about 22&#160;h. The experiment was terminated after 48&#160;h by the injection of RNA-Later&#174; into MFC-C (first in the fixation sequence, not imaged), injection of 4% formaldehyde in PHEMD buffer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> in MFC-A (image sequences designated &#8216;Y&#8217;). MFC-B received RNALater, was designated &#8216;Z&#8217; and third in the fixation sequence. MFC-C did not contain magnets but Al blocks of identical dimensions as the magnets and served as control. The dispensation of the respective fixative was initiated by pressurizing an aluminum chamber that contained sealed bags with fixative, one for each MFC. A solenoid valve controlled fixative flow to one MFC at a time. Excess liquid was collected in a second bag housed in a plastic cage. The entire hardware and fixed plant material deorbited on May 20, 2014. After 2&#160;days the hardware was received at the Kennedy Space Center, and sample processing was completed during the next 3&#160;days. A ground control using the space hardware was performed at the Kennedy Space Center on a large clinostat (8/12&#8211;8/15/14, 1.5&#160;rpm) and at the University of Louisiana using single clinorotated MFCs without imaging but under otherwise identical conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par15">Image sequences were obtained from HD-stored files and compiled as video sequences (Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Root curvature was recorded from seed cassettes that were submersed in the same buffer as during fixation in an upright position and photographed from four sides. After disassembly of the seed cassettes, root appearance was categorized as germinated, straight, or curved. Curvature was evaluated as affected by HGMF only if the root length was sufficient to reach the HGMF area and corresponding curvature was visible. Only roots that were exposed to HGMF were used for the transcriptome analysis.</p><p id="Par16">Microscopy was performed on seedlings fixed in 4% (v/v) formaldehyde in PHEMD buffer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Samples were dehydrated in a graded ethanol series and 100% acetone and embedded in Spurr&#8217;s resin. Longitudinal median sections (2&#160;&#956;m thick) were cut on an ultra-microtome (Sorvall MT2-B) and stained with toluidine blue (0.1% [w/v] in 0.1% [w/v] boric acid). The serial sections were photographed with a digital camera (Sony DKC-ST5) and measured using ImageJ (v.1.53).</p><p id="Par17">RNA extraction was performed in four separate sections of seedlings (root tip, root proper, hypocotyl, and cotyledons) using a kit (Spectrum&#8482; Plant Total RNA Kit, Sigma STRN250) following the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. Transcription analysis was performed after reverse transcription (High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit, Applied Biosystems, USA) and qPCR reactions for 16 different genes using specific primers, with stable and suitable efficiencies (Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Conditions for the amplification on a Step-one real-time PCR system (ThermoFisher Scientific) included a 2&#160;min incubation at 95&#160;&#176;C, followed by 40 cycles (95&#160;&#176;C for 10&#160;s; 60&#160;&#176;C for 10&#160;s) with fluorescent readings taken at the end of the annealing cycle. Quality control included melt curve analyses and capillary electrophoresis (QIAxcel Advanced).</p><p id="Par18">The assessment of the space environment on seedling biology was examined using qPCR data of 16 genes. Typically, qPCR data rely on so-called reference or housekeeping genes, but this approach does not consider that the environmental conditions (space flight, clinorotation, and static growth conditions) are likely to affect reference genes themselves. Therefore, we compared the entire data sets against each other based on all studied conditions. If no difference exists between the two data sets, then such plots result in a diagonal line with a slope of one. The evaluation based on slope and variance (R<sup>2</sup> value) as indicator of overall stability of gene activity also provides information on significantly affected genes. Such data points will show up as &#8216;outliers&#8217; from the bulk distribution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. This approach was evaluated based on four individual tissues of the seedlings, resulting in 64 data points (16 genes&#8201;&#215;&#8201;4 tissue types), for each treatment.</p><p id="Par19">The most relevant comparison of the explained type focuses on the effect of weightlessness and HGMFs in addition to the effect of clinorotation and static, 1&#160;g controls. The complete set of comparisons is provided as Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>. Transcription data were evaluated based on correspondence plots of pairwise comparisons. Significant changes in transcriptions were evaluated by the Mean Method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, and statistical significance was based on Z-scores.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Growth and seedling development</title><p id="Par20">Each MFC contained eight seed cassettes with ten seeds each. Seed germination in the two MFCs with HGMFs was higher than in the non-magnetic chamber (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), indicating that the presence of magnets and magnetic fields did not negatively affect germination.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Germination and root length of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seeds in magnetic field chambers with (A&amp;B) and without magnets (C).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Cassette:</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">MFC-A (HGMF)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N&#8201;=&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">MFC-B (HGMF)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N&#8201;=&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">MFC-C (no magnets)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N&#8201;=&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>There was no difference between chambers or seed cassettes.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Curvature induction by HGMF</title><p id="Par21">Exposure to HGMF induced curvature (Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, substantial curvature occurred in both presence and absence of magnetic gradients. The non-magnetic chamber showed 81% curvature in roots within the seed cassette around the germination paper (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Germination and curvature in the presence and absence of HGMFs of a total of 80 seeds per MFC.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not germinated</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Straight<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Curved</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Curved (HGMF)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MFC-A (HGMF)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MFC-B (HGMF)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MFC-C (No magnets)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Refers to roots that never emerged from the seed cassette or were too short to reach the HGMF area (as shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Example of root orientation inside seed cassettes. The predominant curvature and elongation occurred onto and along the surface of the germination paper.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">MFCs with magnets showed curvature that was independent of the HGMF because of growth patterns or curvature occurring inside the seed cassettes where the magnetic gradient was too weak to affect curvature.</p><p id="Par23">The comparison of space-grown or static ground control seedlings exposed to HGMF with seedlings grown in the non-magnetic field chamber (#1 and #23 in Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>) shows strong correspondence between the two conditions (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), indicating that magnetic fields do not affect general metabolism or transcription activity. This notion is in line with reports that failed to detect effects of magnetic fields on growth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> but contrasts with effects of weak magnetic fields on root curvature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> and effects of the geomagnetic field on stress response and hormesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. The geomagnetic field (typically about 0.5 G) is orders of magnitude weaker than the employed magnetic fields in this research (ca. 30 kG).<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Transcription values between space grown <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seedlings (<bold>A</bold>, #1) and static ground controls (<bold>B</bold>, #23) in the presence and absence of HGMFs show strong correlation (unity slope) and low scatter (R<sup>2</sup>&#8201;=&#8201;0.85 and 0.95), indicating no or low effect of magnetic fields on transcription. Panels (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>) identify the examined tissues in (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>), respectively. The data sets use <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic> as reference and show efficiency-corrected &#916;C<sub>q</sub> and log(2) transformed values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">These data indicate that factors other than HGMF induce curvature and the most likely factor is hydrotropism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. The lack of a gravity stimulus and the distance between the germination paper and the HGMF-generating wedges resulted in a large number of roots confined to the germination paper. The same factor also applied to seedlings in the magnetic chambers and resulted in reduced numbers of roots reaching the HGMF. However, the unambiguous evidence for curvature in space (see Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) and clinorotated seedlings (Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) indicates that HGMFs do have the ability to induce curvature as had been demonstrated earlier in roots, coleoptiles, inflorescences, and hypocotyls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">The presumably hydrotropic growth reduced the number of roots that reached the influence of the HGMFs. Therefore, the overall number of roots curving in response to the magnetic gradient was low (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">Examining the gravisensing mechanism includes measuring the size of the presumptive sensors as previous work has shown that gravisensitivity depends on the amount of starch in amyloplasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Assuming equal density, the diameter of amyloplasts determines the relative mass. Measurements of amyloplasts in columella cells differed between the space-grown, clinorotated, and statically grown ground controls (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and indicates that the amyloplast size and therefore the gravisensing mechanism is responsive to the growth condition, notably weightlessness and clinorotation that respectively reduces and enhances mechanostimulation.<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Size distribution of amyloplasts in the root cap of Brassica rapa seedlings grown in space, on the ground or in a clinostat. The data were compiled from 2&#160;&#956;m thick longitudinal sections of root cap tissue after fixation in paraformaldehyde. The difference between space and clinostat amyloplasts was highly significant (P&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8211;4</sup>); the difference between static ground control and clinorotated amyloplasts was significant at the 5% level. Data were normalized based on 290, 243, and 210 amyloplast measurements for space, clinorotated, and static ground control plants, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">Earlier analyses of starch from space and ground controls found that ethylene reduces starch particle size and that in cotyledons starch particles sizes in space and ground controls were of equal size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Since we used activated charcoal cloth to absorb volatile organic compounds (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), we assume that ethylene was not a factor in the different experiments. In addition, we examined the size distribution of amyloplasts in the root columella. Earlier work showed that amyloplasts in gravisensing tissues (root cap and endodermis) are about twice the size of other tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Our data (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) indicate that the amyloplast size is responsive to the gravitational and mechanical stimulation. The reduced size after clinorotation, the average size in static 1-g controls, and the enlarged size in roots grown under &#8216;micro-gravity&#8217; conditions support the notion that the extent of gravitational stimulation is inversely proportional to the mass of the amyloplasts. Thus, plants not only perceive the direction of an accelerative force but adjust their (starch) metabolism according to the amount of stimulation. If this concept is correct, then it should be supported by gene transcription data. The following analyses confirm that amylase activity indeed is affected by mechanostimulation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Transcript analyses</title><p id="Par28">Since four different tissue types were analyzed, tissue variability and response to spaceflight and clinorotation can be assessed for all examined tissues and genes. Based on distributions of transcription patterns (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), a comprehensive analysis of all treatment and tissue combinations was performed such that the scatter for each comparison and gene was determined based on the formula
<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sum_{i=1}^{n}\sum_{j=1}^{4}\sqrt{{\left({X}_{ij}-\overline{{X }_{j}}\right)}^{2}+{\left({Y}_{ij}-\overline{{Y }_{j}}\right)}^{2}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:munderover><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Article_Equa.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula><fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Transcription values for space grown and clinorotated KSC ground controls. <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seedlings (<bold>A</bold>, #2) show strong reduction of <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription in clinorotated seedlings (circle). A comparison between static and clinorotated seedlings (<bold>B</bold>, #27) shows higher <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription in non-clinorotated seedlings. Panels (<bold>C</bold>) and (<bold>D</bold>) identify the tissues in (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>), respectively. The circled data indicate <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription relative to <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic>. In both cases average <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription was significantly different (p&#8201;=&#8201;0.002, left and p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, right; n&#8201;=&#8201;64). The data sets use <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic> as reference and show efficiency-corrected &#916;C<sub>q</sub> and log(2) transformed values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
where j represents the tissue types (root tip, root proper, hypocotyl, cotyledons) and i the individual experimental comparisons (28, Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>) or examined genes (16). This value was calculated for each analyzed gene and the smallest value (scatter in Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) was identified as the most stably transcribed gene (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Assessment of the consistency of transcription data based on the average of examined tissues.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">All tissues</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PIN1</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">TUB1</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">GLK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Root tip</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PIN1</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PIN3</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SUS</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">GLK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Root proper</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">COX</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SUS</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HXK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Hypocotyl</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HXK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SUS</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ADH1</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Cotyledons</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ADH1</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PIN7</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The top four choices of all combinations (as in Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>) are based on the percentage that resulted in the least scatter of all 448 combinations (16 genes by 28 comparisons).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par29">The distribution of the least variable gene transcription varied greatly (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Although common reference genes (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">TUB1, ACT7</italic>) are represented (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), the observation that individual tissues differed in the genes of greatest stability and that the average of all tissues resulted in different assortments suggested that referring transcription data to the average of all measurements (i.e., the regression lines in Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) is superior to relying on a single gene. Because <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic> showed the greatest stability for all tissues, we placed <italic toggle="yes">PFK</italic> at the origin of the coordinate system (0/0). However, the results explained below are independent of this selection.</p><p id="Par30">The comparisons (Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>) show the least and most significant effect on gene expression and can be used to identify the conditions that induce physiological responses in brassica seedlings. The greatest stability in gene transcription was seen for treatments with similar mechanical load, for example, static growth with and without HGMF, or clinorotated samples (KSC and Lab). The largest scatter or least consistent transcription pattern was associated with different mechanical loads such as flight (i.e., no mechanical load) and clinorotation (enhanced mechanical load), or static and space flight conditions. The main conclusion of these evaluations is that HGMFs or more generally, strong magnetic fields, do not affect transcription; HGMF data are equally present in the most and least affected conditions (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). However, a comparison between clinorotated experiments with the original flight hardware at KSC and experiments in our lab (comparison # 17 and # 22) show statistically significant differences (Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The similarity of gene transcription between pairs of treatments based on high gradient magnetic fields (HGMF) or no magnetic fields (no-MF) that were applied during the space flight (Flight), on ground controls (static), or during clinorotation (Clino) at the Kennedy Space Center (KSC) or in the laboratory (Lab).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">#<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup>, %</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STDEV,%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparisons (all genes)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="28" colspan="1">
<inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1797" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Figa_HTML.gif"/></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC static HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Lab Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flight-no MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC static HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC static no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC static HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC static no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KSC Clino no-MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lab Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-no MF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC Clino HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC Clino no-MF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KSC static HGMF <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> Flight-HGMF</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The values were obtained by averaging the R<sup>2</sup> values that resulted from using each of the 16 genes as reference (i.e., origin in graphical comparisons such as Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Sup. Figs.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3 and 4</xref>).</p><p><sup>a</sup>Numbers refer to Sup. Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Sensitivity of <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic></title><p id="Par31">Data sets comparing space-grown with clinorotated seedlings show large scatter and offset (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A and Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>A), suggesting that the shift in the transcription pattern is not dependent on HGMF but differences in mechanostimulation (i.e., clinorotation). This effect is especially noticeable for <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic>. The effect of clinorotation on amylase transcription is independent of the HGMF because transcription of <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> in the absence of HGMF was higher in static seedlings than clinorotated seedlings (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). Space flight and clinorotation resulted in reduced and elevated transcription, respectively. A similar pattern was observed between clinorotated and static samples; however, HGMF had no effect (Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The altered <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription between clinorotation at KSC and our lab is related to different stabilities of the hardware. The flight hardware contained a webbing-like base mount (implemented because of weight concerns), which provided stable support during space flight but flexed readily during clinorotation compared to a rigid assembly on the laboratory clinostat.</p><p id="Par32">The transcription data correspond with the observed size distribution of amyloplasts (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and indicate that amyloplast size is regulated by starch degradation in clinorotated seedlings and amylase repression (starch accumulation) in space samples. Together these observations indicate that plant adapt to the weightlessness of space by increasing their amyloplast size which likely enhances their gravisensitivity. In contrast, clinorotation represents excessive mechanostimulation and leads to a reduction of amyloplast size through enhanced degradation (amylase transcription).</p><p id="Par33">The observed <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> levels between space-grown and clinorotated seedlings were independent of reference genes; the effect persisted regardless of whatever gene was used as reference. This observation supports using transcription of all available genes as a reliable approach to identifying transcriptional changes of individual genes.</p><p id="Par34">The <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> data correspond to earlier observations of enhanced gravisensitivity of space-grown lentil seedlings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> and reduced starch after clinorotation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Although the STS-107 flight experiment could not be retrieved to measure amyloplast size, the image analysis of flax seedlings indicated that the magnetic gradient had stronger effects than during previous ground experiments because the root curvature started at a greater distance from the HGMF-inducing wedge<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> than during ground controls. This observation is in line with the present data and strongly supports greater (gravi)sensitivity of plants growing in a microgravity environment.</p><p id="Par35">The current report is the first to associate starch metabolism with amyloplasts size and gravisensitivity. The larger amyloplasts in space-grown plants suggest that the application of HGMFs in space is more effective than in earth-grown and especially in clinorotated plants. However, the unreliable growth direction of roots makes HGMF difficult to implement.</p><p id="Par36">Gravisensitivity has also been linked to changes in calcium in statocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> and calcium has been shown to stabilize &#945;-amylase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Therefore, Ca<sup>2+</sup> and amylase are controlling element for the starch content in statocytes. However, starch content is the result of homeostasis for catabolic and anabolic metabolism. Starch biosynthesis depends on a complex set of enzymes that include phosphoglucose isomerase (PGI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>, phosphoglucomutase (PGM)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>, and starch synthases (SSs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> among others. Data on the balance between starch degradation and starch biosynthesis undoubtedly would provide a more comprehensive assessment of the sensitivity of starch metabolism to reduced and enhanced mechanostimulation. However, the limited set of transcriptionally analyzed genes prevents a more thorough assessment of starch biosynthesis in response to altered mechanostimulation. Future space experiments might remedy this shortcoming.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Genes other than <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic></title><p id="Par37">Although weightlessness is the dominant difference between ground and space flights, the lack of density-driven gas exchange and water distribution are equally significant alterations for plant growth in space. Because the flight hardware was enclosed in a hermetically sealed (triple-contained) chamber, atmospheric effects can be excluded. Therefore, the following considerations only apply to gravity effects. Comparing the number of significantly (P &lt; 0.05) affected combinations (genes by reference), shows the largest effect on <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The percentage of significant (P&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) changes in gene transcription in response to space, HGMF and clinorotation of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seedlings. Compared to <italic toggle="yes">AMY1,</italic> all other genes showed fewer significant alterations (% of 16 genes&#8201;&#215;&#8201;16 references).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par38">Genes other than <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> responded to specific conditions but at reduced power. <italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic> showed modifications only when comparing clinorotation at KSC with static growth (Comparisons #19 &amp; #20); <italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic> was not affected by HGMF but sensitive to vibrations (higher frequency movements in excess to the 1.5&#160;rpm of the clinostat). This relationship is similar to the enhanced AMY1 transcription addressed in Sup. Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">4</xref>. The enhanced oscillation can be verified by the jitter in Sup. Video <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>. To improve visibility, the individual frames were aligned, but the inconsistent position of imprinted data confirms the added vibrational stimulation that affected <italic toggle="yes">ACT7</italic> activation (and enhanced <italic toggle="yes">AMY1</italic> transcription) compared to regular (smooth) clinorotation.</p><p id="Par39"><italic toggle="yes">COX</italic> showed the strongest upregulation in space flight material compared with static growth conditions (#4, #5, #10 #11) but was not affected by HGMF. This observation further supports the claim that magnetic fields do not affect transcription. Instead, COX responds to space flight associated stress as has been shown previously for fish brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> and skeletal muscle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. Changes in <italic toggle="yes">G6PDH5</italic> were limited to treatment differences between space flight and clinorotation (#8, #12, #15, #16) and correspond to earlier reports of altered enzyme activities of pine seedlings after exposure to clinorotation and hyper-g<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup> and enzyme activities in artemia cysts after space flight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>. <italic toggle="yes">IAA5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PIN7</italic> responded to HGMF both under flight (<italic toggle="yes">PIN7</italic>) and clinorotation (<italic toggle="yes">IAA5</italic>) and underscores their relevance for auxin modification of growth. Although the number of roots that curved in response to HGMF was low (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), it is possible that differential growth (curvature in response to hydrotropism?) affected the transcription of these genes. GLK did not respond significantly; changes were not limited to any particular condition and therefore cannot be associated with specific experimental conditions but likely represent natural variations. <italic toggle="yes">UBq1, Tub1, ADH1, HXK, PFK, SUS, PIN1</italic> showed no significant changes in transcription and therefore could all serve as references. The lack of response of <italic toggle="yes">ADH1</italic> is surprising as this gene was previously identified as space stress indicator<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. TAGL is the only gene that shows reduced transcription in the presence of magnetic fields but only in clinorotated samples. While there is precedence that the lipid metabolism is affected by hypergravity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup> and clinorotation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>, this is the first observation that magnetic fields might contribute to such changes.</p><p id="Par40">In summary, our data support plant proprioception of weightlessness and metabolic control of amyloplast size. The adjustment of size and mass of amyloplasts indicates that plants perceive gravity and ponderomotive forces, which provide not only enhanced gravisensitivity but also explain some metabolic responses to space conditions. The advantage of a sealed environment suggests that this effect is not an artefact but related to gravitational and mechanosensory responses. The results also demonstrate that HGMF do not influence gene transcription. Future work needs to investigate the role of other starch-related genes to understand the entire dynamic of metabolic plasticity that relates to weightlessness.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_MOESM1_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Video 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_MOESM2_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Video 2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2022_22691_MOESM3_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Information 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-022-22691-2.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration grants NNX10AP91G, NNH18ZHA004C, and 80NSSC17K0344 to KHH. The authors are grateful for the help of KSC personnel, especially Allison Caron, Ralph Fritsche, Howard Levine, Carole Miller, Bradley Burns and Dave Reed. We also acknowledge the assistance of Allison Mjoen, Carlos Gill, George Guerra, James Smodell.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>K.H.H. received funding, designed the experiment, analyzed the data, and wrote the paper. M.R.P. performed qPCR work, S.P.J. and C.A. performed microscopy and measured amyloplast size. All authors reviewed the text.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are available upon request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par41">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant responses to gravity&#8212;insights and extrapolations from ground studies</article-title><source>Gravit. Space Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant gravitropism. Unraveling the ups and downs of a complex process</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>1677</fpage><lpage>1690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.032169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1540347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jancewicz</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of root gravitropism</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>R964</fpage><lpage>R972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2017.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28898669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravitropism and mechanical signaling in plants</article-title><source>Am. J. Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1200408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23281392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levernier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pouliquen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forterre</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrative model of plant gravitropism linking statoliths position and auxin transport</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>651928</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.651928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33854523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8039511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The onset of gravisensitivity in the embryonic root of flax</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.073296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16377740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1326040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajala</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmentation of root gravitropism by hypocotyl curvature in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2019.05.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31203886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cytoskeleton and gravitropism in higher plants</article-title><source>J. Plant Growth Regul.</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s003440010041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12024227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gravity persistent signal 1 (gps1) reveals novel cytochrome p450s involved in gravitropism</article-title><source>Am. J. Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1200436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23284057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toal</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of root angle and gravitropism</article-title><source>Genes Genomes Genet.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3841</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.118.200540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6288823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30322904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dummer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forreiter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravitropism in Arabidopsis thaliana: Root-specific action of the EHB gene and violation of the resultant law</article-title><source>J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2015.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26496692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth and microtubule orientation of <italic toggle="yes">Zea-mays</italic> roots subjected to osmotic-stress</article-title><source>Int. J. Plant Sci.</source><year>1995</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/297301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11540311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noise amplification of plant gravisensing</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asr.2006.12.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microinjection&#8212;a tool to study gravitropism</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2221</fpage><lpage>2227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0273-1177(03)00248-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The response of lazy-2 tomato seedlings to curvature-inducing magnetic gradients is modulated by light</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1999</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004250050534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11536901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetophoretic induction of curvature in coleoptiles and hypocotyls</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>1997</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1951</fpage><lpage>1957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jexbot/48.316.1951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11541075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curvature in Arabidopsis inflorescence stems is limited to the region of amyloplast displacement</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/41.6.702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10945339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gene essential for hydrotropism in roots</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>4724</fpage><lpage>4729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0609929104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1810325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Root hydrotropism is controlled via a cortex-specific growth mechanism</article-title><source>Nature Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>17057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2017.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Touch modulates gravity sensing to regulate the growth of primary roots of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01637.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In touch: Plant responses to mechanical stimuli</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2004.01263.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of mechanostimulation on gravitropism and signal persistence in flax roots</article-title><source>Plant Signal Behav.</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.6.9.16601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21847020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3258067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular magnetophoresis of statoliths in Chara rhizoids and analysis of cytoplasm viscoelasticity</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0273-1177(01)00182-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11594372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kuznetsov, O. A. &amp; Hewaparakrama, H. K. In <italic toggle="yes">Scientific and Clinical Applications of magnetic carriers</italic> (eds Urs, H. <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.) Ch. 33, 429&#8211;444 (Plenum Press, 1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetophoretic response of barley coleoptiles</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>140</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular magnetophoresis of amyloplasts and induction of root curvature</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1996</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00197590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8580774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravisensing in flax roots&#8212;results from STS-107</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asr.2005.01.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Senftle, F. &amp; Hambright, W. In <italic toggle="yes">Biological Effects of Magnetic Fields (2. vol)</italic> (ed Madeleine, F. B.) 261&#8211;306 (Plenum Press, 1969).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferritin: Structure, gene regulation, and cellular function in animals, plants, and microorganisms</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.56.070187.001445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3304136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Povinelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mopper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of magnetic gradients to study gravitropism</article-title><source>Am. J. Bot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1200304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23174915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen-Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinchman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thresholds for georesponse to acceleration in gravity-compensated avena seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1968</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.43.3.338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16656768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1086843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrotropism and Its interaction with gravitropism in maize roots</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.96.2.558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11538004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1080806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blilou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The PIN auxin efflux facilitator network controls growth and patterning in Arabidopsis roots</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>433</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cations on hormone transport in primary roots of <italic toggle="yes">Zea mays</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.86.3.890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11538240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1054589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PIN-dependent auxin transport: Action, regulation, and evolution</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.114.134874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25604445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4330589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deikman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of alpha amylase messenger RNA accumulation by gibberellic acid and calcium in barley aleurone layers</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.78.1.192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16664196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1064700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose synthase affects carbon partitioning to increase cellulose production and altered cell wall ultrastructure</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>13118</fpage><lpage>13123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0900188106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2722352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>da-Silva-Santos</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection and validation of reference genes by RT-qPCR under photoperiodic induction of flowering in sugarcane (<italic toggle="yes">Saccharum</italic> spp.)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4589</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-83918-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33633157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>FQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin-proteasome system in plant responses to environments</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2019</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2931</fpage><lpage>2944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.13633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31364170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection and evaluation of novel reference genes for quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR) based on genome and transcriptome data in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica napus</italic> L.</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2014</year><volume>538</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2013.12.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24406618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>LU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawloski</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandasamy</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis actin gene ACT7 plays an essential role in germination and root growth</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01626.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papdi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional identification of Arabidopsis stress regulatory genes using the controlled cDNA overexpression system</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.116897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18441225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2409023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cytochrome c oxidase biogenesis factor AtCOX17 modulates stress responses in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenases in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02293.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klepikova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasianov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerasimov</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Logacheva</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A high resolution map of the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> developmental transcriptome based on RNA-seq profiling</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27549386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilera-Alvarado</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Nieto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant hexokinases are multifaceted proteins</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcx062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28449056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression profile analysis of hypoxia responses in Arabidopsis roots and shoots</article-title><source>J. Plant Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12374-011-9172-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlew</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An annotated database of Arabidopsis mutants of acyl lipid metabolism</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-014-1710-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25487439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4371839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oil is on the agenda: Lipid turnover in higher plants</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1861</year><volume>1253&#8211;1268</volume><fpage>2016</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2016.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27155216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organization of cortical microtubules in graviresponding maize roots</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1993</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11537991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00199754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deoli</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mean method: A specific outlier boundary for arbitrary distributions</article-title><source>Theor. Math. Appl.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaplin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of a one Tesla magnet on human fibroblast growth</article-title><source>Bios</source><year>2005</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1893/0005-3155(2005)076[0193:TEOAOT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gellrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strieth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Static magnetic fields increase tumor microvessel leakiness and improve antitumoral efficacy in combination with paclitaxel</article-title><source>Cancer Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2013.09.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24075957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kordyum</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogatina</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalinina</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheykina</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A weak combined magnetic field changes root gravitropism</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asr.2005.05.103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic field effects on plant growth, development, and evolution</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25237317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4154392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paponov</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fliegmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential root and shoot magnetoresponses in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9195</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-88695-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33911161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8080623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of arabidopsis ecotypes reveals a role for brassinosteroids in root hydrotropism</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>2720</fpage><lpage>2736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.01563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29439211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The response of the lazy-2 tomato mutant to HGMF and red light</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravitropism of inflorescence stems in starch-deficient mutants of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Int. J. Plant Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>521</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/314142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11542271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amyloplasts are necessary for full gravitropic sensitivity in roots of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1989</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00392808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11539759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Composition and physical properties of starch in microgravity-grown plants</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0273-1177(01)00374-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driss-Ecole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legue</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carnero-Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perbal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravisensitivity and automorphogenesis of lentil seedling roots grown on board the International Space Station</article-title><source>Physiol. Plant.</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2008.01121.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18429941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tewinkel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravisensitivity of cress roots</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0273-1177(97)00637-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11541374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piastuch</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Starch metabolism in germinating soybean cotyledons is sensitive to clinorotation and centrifugation</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>1994</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.1994.tb00301.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11537973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bizet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Both gravistimulation onset and removal trigger an increase of cytoplasmic free calcium in statocytes of roots grown in microgravity</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-29788-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30061667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6065396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polarity of statocytes and the gravisensitivity of roots are dependent on the concentration of calcium in statocytes</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.pcp.a077827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11540943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kordyum</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for the cytoskeleton in plant cell gravisensitivity and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-signaling in microgravity</article-title><source>Cell Biol. Int.</source><year>2003</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1065-6995(02)00315-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12681314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of a Ca2+-ATPase gene and the role of cytosolic Ca2+ in the gibberellin-dependent signaling pathway in aleurone cells</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>1997</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1997.11030363.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9107028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saboury</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability, activity and binding properties study of alpha-amylase upon interaction with Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>2+</sup></article-title><source>Biologia</source><year>2002</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashem</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible involvement of phosphoinositide-Ca2+ signaling in the regulation of alpha-amylase expression and germination of rice seed (<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/41.4.399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahaji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plastidial phosphoglucose isomerase is an important determinant of seed yield through its involvement in gibberellin-mediated reproductive development and storage reserve biosynthesis in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2082</fpage><lpage>2098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.18.00312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30099384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6181017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations in growth, photosynthesis, and respiration in a starchless mutant of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (L.) deficient in chloroplast phosphoglucomutase activity</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.79.1.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16664354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1074821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gravitropism in a starchless mutant of Arabidopsis&#8212;implications for the starch-statolith theory of gravity sensing</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1989</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00392807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11539758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Starch synthesis in Arabidopsis is achieved by spatial cotranscription of core starch metabolism genes</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1582</fpage><lpage>1595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.144196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19759345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2773087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kortje</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slenzka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of altered gravity and cytochrome oxidase activity in the developing fish brain</article-title><source>J. Brain Res.</source><year>1996</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8964968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitts</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of prolonged space flight on human skeletal muscle enzyme and substrate profiles</article-title><source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00489.2013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23766501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faraoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glyoxylate cycle activity in <italic toggle="yes">Pinus pinea</italic> seeds during germination in altered gravity conditions</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2019</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2019.03.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30959447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaubin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enzyme activities and membrane lipids in Artemia cysts after a long duration space flight</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>1996</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0273-1177(96)00043-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porterfield</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musgrave</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spaceflight exposure effects on transcription, activity, and localization of alcohol dehydrogenase in the roots of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.3.685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9085569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC158186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transgene expression patterns indicate that spaceflight affects stress signal perception and transduction in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.126.2.613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC111153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolzumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in membrane lipid composition in azuki bean epicotyls under hypergravity conditions: Possible role of membrane sterols in gravity resistance</article-title><source>Adv. Space Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asr.2007.02.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nedukha</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kordyum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vorobyova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity of plant plasma membrane to simulated microgravity</article-title><source>Microgravity Sci. Technol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12217-020-09865-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>